The <ORGANIZATION>State University of New York’s Board of Trustees</ORGANIZATION> on Tuesday endorsed an ambitious vision for how <ORGANIZATION>SUNY</ORGANIZATION> might use prior-learning assessment, competency-based programs, and massive open online courses to help students finish their degrees in less time, for less money.
The plan calls for “new and expanded online programs” that “include options for time-shortened degree completion.” In particular, the board proposed a huge expansion the prior-learning assessment programs offered by <ORGANIZATION>SUNY</ORGANIZATION>’s <ORGANIZATION>Empire State College</ORGANIZATION>.
The system will also push its top faculty members to build MOOCs designed so that certain students who do well in the courses might be eligible for <ORGANIZATION>SUNY</ORGANIZATION> credit.
Ultimately, the system wants to add 100,000 enrollments within three years, according to anews release.
Even before the <ORGANIZATION>SUNY</ORGANIZATION> announcement, it had already been a big week for nontraditional models for awarding college credit. The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Education Department</ORGANIZATION> on Mondaysaid it had no problemwith spending federal student aid on college programs that give credit based on “competency,” not the number of hours students spend in class.
<ORGANIZATION>Empire State College</ORGANIZATION>’s prior-learning assessment programs operate on a similar principle. Students who can demonstrate that they have acquired certain skills can get college credit, even if they did not acquire those skills in a college classroom.
The new <ORGANIZATION>SUNY</ORGANIZATION> effort will aim to copy the Empire State model across the system, said <PERSON>Nancy L. Zimpher</PERSON>, the chancellor.
“This resolution opens the door to assurances to our students that this kind of prior-learning assessment will be available eventually on all our campuses,” said Ms. <PERSON>Zimpher</PERSON> in an interview.
<ORGANIZATION>SUNY</ORGANIZATION> is just the latest state system to use novel teaching and assessment methods to deal with the problem of enrolling, and graduating, more students.
<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> have enlistedWestern <ORGANIZATION>Governors University</ORGANIZATION>,a nonprofit online institution that uses the “competency” method, to help working adults in those states earn degrees.PennsylvaniaandWisconsinare building programs aimed at helping their own adult students redeem their on-the-job skills and knowledge for credit toward degrees. And Californiamay soon use MOOCs to deal with overcrowdingin some courses at its public colleges and universities.
Ms. <PERSON>Zimpher</PERSON> said the prior-learning expertise at <ORGANIZATION>Empire State</ORGANIZATION> would make it possible for the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> system to undertake the new effort without calling in outsiders.
“Usually when you have an outside vendor, it’s to deliver something that you don’t know how to do,” she said. “In our case we actually know how to do this, and we know how to do it well.”
This entry was posted inDistance Education,MOOCs. Bookmark thepermalink.<PERSON>Steve Kolowich</PERSON>