<PERSON>Karen Head</PERSON> joins us today and in the coming months to report on her group’s efforts to develop and offer a MOOC (massive open online course) in freshman composition. She’s an assistant professor in the <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Institute of Technology’s School of Literature</ORGANIZATION>, Media, and Communication, and director of the institute’s <ORGANIZATION>Communication Center</ORGANIZATION>. So far higher education hasn’t seen many introductory writing courses taught in such a format, so we expect there’ll be lots of interest in this experiment. Thanks for joining us, <PERSON>Karen</PERSON>.
This entry was posted inDistance Education,MOOCs,Teaching. Bookmark thepermalink.<PERSON>Carolyn Mooney</PERSON>