<ORGANIZATION>NewsFor Golden State</ORGANIZATION>'s Public Colleges, No Silver BulletDoing More With Less at <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> StateSince the recession began, state financial support for the <ORGANIZATION>California State University</ORGANIZATION> system has dropped, then risen, then plunged. Two tables show the details.
If Prop 30 Fails, What Then?To save higher education in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, a tax referendum needs to pass in November. And lawmakers are also hoping for a tax windfall from <ORGANIZATION>Facebook</ORGANIZATION> options. After that, not...
Tying Lawmakers' Hands in <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>Over the past 79 years, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> voters helped shape the current higher-education-spending crisis.
Shrink My Board, PleaseSome colleges have decided that fewer is better when it comes to the trustee count.
The Future of Peer Review in the Humanities? It's OpenNobody likes the current system, and most everybody agrees it should move online, but from there, opinions diverge.
Push for Open Access to Publicly Financed Research Swells AbroadThe debate goes global, with policy makers in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, the Continent, and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> signaling a warming trend.
Real-Time Data Show 2-Year Colleges What Employers Need NowCommunity colleges are using new software to get a glimpse of the labor market.
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Program Enourages Foreign Female Students to <ORGANIZATION>Dream BigThe State Department</ORGANIZATION> effort brought 20 women to <ORGANIZATION>Saint Mary's College</ORGANIZATION>, in <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>.
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> Puts Out the Welcome MatThe country is hoping to draw half-a-million foreign students to its shores by 2020.
Foreign Scientists and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Policy Makers Seek Ways Around Visa StalemateEven academic entrepreneurs preparing to take their new scientific breakthroughs to market find it difficult, if not impossible, to stay in the country legally.
Top Executive at <ORGANIZATION>U. of Virginia Resigns</ORGANIZATION> in Wake of Leadership <PERSON>CrisisMichael Strine</PERSON>, executive vice president and chief operating officer, drew criticism after the president's forced resignation.
5 Professors Join <ORGANIZATION>Vanderbilt</ORGANIZATION>'s Bid to <ORGANIZATION>Bridge Health</ORGANIZATION> and SocietyThe university's growing Center for Medicine, Health, and <ORGANIZATION>Society</ORGANIZATION> has just hired its first full-time faculty members.
Transitions: Administration Official to Return to <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Temple U.</ORGANIZATION> Appoints New PresidentCass <PERSON>R. Sunstein</PERSON>, <PERSON>Obama</PERSON>'s regulatory chief, is going back to being a law professor. Read about that and other job-related news.
A Delicate Operation for an Ex-Surgeon: Leading a Young Business SchoolBernard <PERSON>T. Ferrari</PERSON>, once a surgeon and corporate strategist, is leading the <PERSON>Johns Hopkins</PERSON>' business school, which emphasizes management of health-care industries.
In Struggling <LOCATION>South Texas</LOCATION>, a New Fund Raiser Focuses on <PERSON>AlumniVeronica Gonzales</PERSON>, a vice president at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas-Pan American</ORGANIZATION>, sees private giving as one way to make up for the loss of state support.
Transitions: <PERSON>Alexander Doty</PERSON>, Expert on Gay Culture, Dies at 58; Other Notable DeathsMr. <PERSON>Doty</PERSON>, the author of books on queer film theory and gay culture, died of injuries he suffered when he was hit by a motorcycle.
Selected New Books on Higher EducationThe Chronicle ReviewDoes Religion Really Poison Everything?A new science of religion says God has gotten a bad rap.
Scholars, Spies, and Global StudiesIt took a world war to propel Americans to make a serious commitment to global study. Now we have the time and the need to do it more deliberately.
<PERSON>Hoover</PERSON>, <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, and Spying at BerkeleyFor decades the agency claimed it was protecting the nation. The author's FOIA requests show different.
A Healthy Mania for the MacabreDeath is on exhibit in a futuristically old-fashioned way. What makes us want to buy tickets?
The New Aesthetic of 'Aww'Let's get over the sublime. It's the cute we should be thinking about.
Ghost CampusIn summer a campus reboots; students are only an afterthought.
The Life of Leisure"The most intriguing aspect of the article is that its main argument ends up in a paradox."
The Vanishing Conservative Intellectual"There is plenty of intellectual thought on the right."
CommentaryDon't Confuse Technology with TeachingThough universities are rushing to embrace online courses, true education requires one mind engaging with another.
Why Online Education Won't Replace CollegeMassive Open Online Courses raise complications.
Making Sure Learning Takes PlaceA writing instructor gives a student an F for a paper on which she had help, and learns something in the process.
Fix the Remediation Problem Before It Starts"Our task force on remediation will determine how <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s colleges, schools, community partners, and government officials can best collectively address our needs."
Gates Symbolizes What's Wrong With Education Reform"Because he is wealthy and successful (if the accumulation of wealth guarantees a person's "success"), he is accepted as an expert on anything that he chooses to talk...
Governance? It's in the Hands of Corporate Elites"Things are so far gone that talk of shared governance is at this point idle. It is in effect peasants appealing to the czars."
AdviceEmbrace Your Inner North DakotanIn searching for your first job, persuade yourself to appreciate different—not "lower"—standards.
