NewsThe Professors Behind the MOOC HypeThe New Faculty MinorityWhile expressing concern about the working conditions of the growing ranks of their contingent colleagues, those with tenure prefer to keep governance to themselves.
A Bold Move Toward MOOCs Sends Shock Waves, but Details Are ScarceLeaders agree on the urgent need to improve student access to courses. But some are wary of the hopes placed on new technology.
'Not Your Grandfather's Comp. Class': Model Mixes Face Time and <PERSON>TechnologyTeachers</PERSON> and students alike say they like the addition of more low-tech face-to-face interaction.
As Role of Librarians Evolves, Some Colleges End Their Faculty StatusSome administrators say the position must shift with the changing model for college libraries.
Overhaul of Rules for Human Research Hits ImpasseEfforts to revise rules that govern the ethics of biomedical and behavioral human-subjects research appear stalled, perhaps by a divided mission.
Cheap Natural Gas Makes Dumping Coal an Easy Decision for Many CollegesEnergy analysts see few downsides for campus utility operators, but climate activists disagree.
Business-School Programs Turn Felons Into EntrepreneursCertificates from <ORGANIZATION>Baylor University</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>University of Virginia</ORGANIZATION> help ex-cons find jobs faster and even start their own businesses.
In 2014 Budgets, Republicans and Democrats Offer Competing Plans for AcademeWith attention focused on legislation for 2014, <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> lawmakers are still trying to craft spending measures for the 2013 fiscal year, already nearly half over.
Wired Campus: <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION>'s Search of Staff E-Mail Sparks Questions About Policies NationwideWhat expectations of privacy should university employees have when it comes to their work e-mail accounts? It depends, says one expert.
<LOCATION>Myanmar</LOCATION> Takes Steps to Rebuild Its Ruined Universities, With American HelpBut after decades of neglect, the higher-education system will need "millions and millions of dollars" to get up to speed, one expert warns.
Percolator: Do Atheists Really Believe in God?A forthcoming study suggests a gap between what atheists say they believe about God and what they really believe. And a related question: What are atheists for, anyway?
Chancellor to Join <ORGANIZATION>Facebook</ORGANIZATION>'s Board; <ORGANIZATION>Huntsville Provost</ORGANIZATION> to Lead U. of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> at ArlingtonSusan <PERSON>Desmond-Hellmann</PERSON>, of the <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, will be the second woman on that board. Read about that and other job-related news.
In Sexual-Assault Crises, an Outside Voice Offers <PERSON>GuidanceGina M. Smith</PERSON>, a former sex-crimes prosecutor in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, has advised many colleges on how to better handle sexual-assault accusations.
<ORGANIZATION>National-Security Scholar Leads New Institute</ORGANIZATION> to Support Study of IsraelAriel <PERSON>Ilan Roth</PERSON> is the new executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Israel Institute</ORGANIZATION>, which will encourage American universities to do more research on <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>.
Law-School Dean Takes On Urban ChallengeRichard <PERSON>L. Revesz</PERSON> will lead a new institute at <ORGANIZATION>New York University</ORGANIZATION> focused on cities and the urban environment.
President Emeritus of <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> State <PERSON>U. Dies</PERSON> at 77; <ORGANIZATION>Dostoyevsky Scholar Dies</ORGANIZATION> at 94Donald <PERSON>W. Zacharias</PERSON>, who led <ORGANIZATION>Mississippi State</ORGANIZATION> from 1985 to 1997, died on March 2. Read about that and other deaths.
The Chronicle ReviewThe Sun Sets on the Modern Merchant ClassBut in the historically cyclical patterns of power, who will replace it—the technocrats or the soldiers?
Reason, Emotion, and <PERSON>HitlerThree</PERSON> new books help us consider: How is a figure of such vast iniquity most enlighteningly viewed?
The Spiritual Autobiography of Christian WimanIn his new book, the critic contemplates the meaning of poetic incarnation in spiritual terms.
Fleshing Out Those BonesAn ornithological illustrator pecks at preconceptions of textbook birds.
Sharing Those Woods, Dark and <PERSON>DeepA Robert Frost</PERSON> poem whispers the wintry bleakness of brittle lives.
Video Gamers Find Failure an AttractionHow failure is part of the fun of video games.
<ORGANIZATION>ViewsFor College Endowments</ORGANIZATION>, Ethical Stands Can Be ComplicatedThere's no easy way to distinguish between issues that are and are not relevant to a college's educational mission.
They're Transfer Students, Not Cash CowsAll colleges should tell students early and at no charge whether their previously earned credits will count at their new institutions.
'Someone Searched for You': Academia.edu and MeA mound of data, both tantalizingly suggestive and wholly inconclusive, presents itself for consideration.
What Fossil-Fuel Divestment Would CostExcluding investments based on socially responsible criteria could trigger hundreds of millions of dollars in losses. Have the critics thought this through?
