<ORGANIZATION>Princeton University</ORGANIZATION> announced on Sunday that <PERSON>Christopher L. Eisgruber</PERSON>, a constitutional scholar who has been the institution's provost for close to nine years, would be its next president. He will take office on July 1.
Mr. <PERSON>Eisgruber</PERSON>, who is 51, will replace <PERSON>Shirley M. Tilghman</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION>'s first female president, who announced last fall that she wouldstep downat the end of the academic year.
A physics major as an undergraduate at <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION>, where he earned his bachelor's degree in 1983, Mr. <PERSON>Eisgruber</PERSON> has been a member of the university faculty since 2001. He was the unanimous recommendation of the university's 17-member presidential-search committee, the university said.
"<PERSON>Chris Eisgruber</PERSON> has all of the qualities we were looking for in <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION>'s next president," said <PERSON>Kathryn A. Hall</PERSON>, chair of the <ORGANIZATION>Board of Trustees</ORGANIZATION> and of the search committee. "He has keen intelligence and excellent judgment; he cares passionately about teaching and research of the highest quality; he is deeply committed to principles of excellence, equity, and integrity; and he is devoted to <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION>."
When Mr. <PERSON>Eisgruber</PERSON> joined the <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION> faculty, in 2001, he was a professor of public affairs and the director of the Program in Law and Public Affairs. He became provost in 2004, continuing to teach some courses, including a freshman seminar last fall on the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> and constitutional democracy.
Mr. <PERSON>Eisgruber</PERSON> spent two years at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Oxford</ORGANIZATION> as a Rhodes scholar, received his law degree from the <ORGANIZATION>University of Chicago</ORGANIZATION>, and served as a clerk to Justice <PERSON>John Paul Stevens</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>. He also taught at the <ORGANIZATION>New York University Law School</ORGANIZATION> for more than a decade.
"As an undergraduate, faculty member, and provost, I have developed a heartfelt appreciation for <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION>'s distinctive mission as a great research university with an unmatched commitment to liberal-arts education," Mr. <PERSON>Eisgruber</PERSON> said. He praised Ms. <PERSON>Tilghman</PERSON>'s leadership, saying it has made <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION> "more vibrant, energetic, and inclusive than ever."
"One of <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION>'s most-attractive characteristics," he added, "is its drive not only to sustain past successes but also to build new strengths in response to changing needs and opportunities."
Mr. <PERSON>Eisgruber</PERSON> is a member of several boards, including the academic advisory board of <LOCATION>Coursera</LOCATION>, a provider of massive open online courses, and the <ORGANIZATION>Board of Trustees of the Educational Testing Service</ORGANIZATION>. He also serves as vice chair of the <ORGANIZATION>Board of Trustees of Princeton University Press</ORGANIZATION> and chair of its executive committee.
He and his wife, <PERSON>Lori A. Martin</PERSON>, a securities litigator, have a 14-year-old son, <PERSON>Danny</PERSON>, who is a freshman at <ORGANIZATION>Princeton High School</ORGANIZATION>.
<PERSON>Sara Hebel</PERSON>