Two major providers of massive open online courses have announced new expansions of their stables of university partners, which now overlap for the first time.
Coursera, already the largest <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION> provider, announced that it would build courses with 29 new partners, nearly doubling the number of universities in its network, to 62.
Meanwhile, edX, a nonprofit project started last year by <ORGANIZATION>Harvard University</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>, announced it would add six new partners, including three universitiesﾑ<ORGANIZATION>Rice University</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>University of Toronto</ORGANIZATION>, and the ツole Polytechnique F仕屍ale de <LOCATION>Lausanne</LOCATION> (in <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>)ﾑthat already offer MOOCs through Coursera.
The moves represent efforts by both <LOCATION>Coursera</LOCATION> and edX to bring more institutions outside the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> into their folds. Sixteen of the new Coursera partners are beyond <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> borders, as are five of the new edX partners. Some new MOOCs on Coursera will be available in Chinese, French, Italian, and Spanish, the company said in a news release.
But perhaps more intriguing to MOOC watchers is that there are now three institutions that have agreed to build courses with both edX and Courseraﾑproviders that have been vying for partners, and the spotlight, from opposite coasts and opposite sides of the nonprofit/for-profit divide.
Among other differences, Coursera and edX propose different models for sharing any revenue that their MOOCs might generate. (For details on edXﾕs financial terms with its university partners, and how its agreements differ from Courseraﾕs, seethis article.)
But for universities weighing whether to put courses on edX or Courseraﾑor bothﾑthe considerations are not merely financial, especially since neither organization is making any serious money yet.
At <ORGANIZATION>Rice University</ORGANIZATION>, in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, the decision to sign with edX, despite having already struck a deal with <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON>, came from the faculty, said <PERSON>Caroline Levander</PERSON>, the universityﾕs vice provost for interdisciplinary initiatives.
ﾒIt may be that there are courses that are aligned with the technical capabilities of the edX platform,ﾓ Ms. <PERSON>Levander</PERSON> toldThe Chronicle, ﾒas well as the not-for-profit and open-source featuresﾓ of that platform.
For example, <PERSON>Rice</PERSON> plans to integrate its existing analytics tools, which measure student engagement with the free learning materials in the universityﾕs OpenStax database, into edXﾕs open-source platform.
Ms. <PERSON>Levander</PERSON> demurred when asked how large of a role faculty preference for nonprofit partners had played in the groundswell of support for edX. But she did say that many faculty members had been moved by a recent presentation on the campus by <PERSON>Anant Agarwal</PERSON>, president of edX, who has not been shy about pitching his organization as the more natural ally of nonprofit higher education.
edX, which has grown at a much slower pace than <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON>, in recent months has relaxed its attitude toward <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION> monogamy with its institutional partners. The nonprofitﾕs agreement with the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION> system, signed last October, forbade the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> system to enter into ﾒa collaboration with or similar agreement with,ﾓ or to provide ﾒsignificant institutional resources to,ﾓ any other MOOC provider, according to a copy of that agreement obtained byThe <LOCATION>Chroniclevia</LOCATION> a public-records request.
As recently as January, edX was seeking ﾒa pretty stringent exclusivity clauseﾓ in its negotiations with <PERSON>Rice</PERSON>, according to Ms. <PERSON>Levander</PERSON>. ﾒSince then, theyﾕve loosened their exclusivity clause significantly,ﾓ she said.
The new university partners of the two MOOC providers are as follows:
edX
Australian <ORGANIZATION>National UniversityDelft University of Technology</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>)<LOCATION>ツole Polytechnique F仕屍ale de Lausanne</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>)<ORGANIZATION>McGill University</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>)Rice UniversityUniversity of <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>)<ORGANIZATION>Coursera
Autonomous University of Barcelona</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>)<ORGANIZATION>California Institute of the ArtsCase Western Reserve UniversityChinese University of Hong KongCurtis Institute of Musicツole Polytechnique</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>)<ORGANIZATION>IE Business School</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>)<ORGANIZATION>Leiden University</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>)<ORGANIZATION>Ludwig Maximilian University of MunichMonterrey Institute of Technology and Higher Education</ORGANIZATION>ﾕs <ORGANIZATION>Virtual University</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>)<ORGANIZATION>National Autonomous University of MexicoNational Taiwan UniversityNational University of SingaporeNorthwestern UniversityPennsylvania State UniversityRutgers UniversitySapienza University of RomeTechnical University of DenmarkTechnical University of MunichUniversity</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> at San DiegoUniversity of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Santa CruzUniversity</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> at <ORGANIZATION>BoulderUniversity of CopenhagenUniversity of GenevaUniversity of Minnesota-Twin CitiesUniversity</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Chapel HillUniversity of RochesterUniversity of TokyoUniversity</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION> at MadisonThis entry was posted inDistance Education,MOOCs. Bookmark thepermalink.<PERSON>Steve Kolowich</PERSON>