NewsColleges Seek 'Noncognitive' Measures of ApplicantsChinese Summer Schools Sell Quick American CreditsThe private programs have allowed Chinese students to transfer credit back to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> colleges where they're enrolled, but <LOCATION>American</LOCATION> officials have started taking a closer...
Female Philosophers Shake Up Their FieldDespite the advent of feminist philosophy decades ago, the discipline is more male-dominated than any other in the humanities. Some women are trying to change that.
Law Deans Confront a 'New Normal' as Schools Adjust to Job-Market ChangesMeeting over the weekend, law-school leaders discussed dwindling applicant pools, staff cuts, and how to serve students' needs better.
<ORGANIZATION>Lumina Foundation</ORGANIZATION> Adopts New Tactics to Reach College-Completion GoalIn a new four-year plan, the group seeks to further its goal of increasing the proportion of Americans who hold a degree to 60 percent by 2025.
Staying On, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> Chief Signals an Alliance With the GovernorJ. <PERSON>Bernard Machen</PERSON> will postpone his retirement and take one last shot at making the <ORGANIZATION>University of Florida</ORGANIZATION> a "top 10" public institution.
Colleges Ponder Students' Calls for Divestment in Fossil FuelsWhile at least two institutions have changed their policies, most are holding back because of fears about harming their returns.
<ORGANIZATION>Private-College</ORGANIZATION> Presidents Urge a Commitment to Need-Based AidA draft pledge unveiled at a weekend meeting reflects concern that using merit aid to compete for top students hurts those who can least afford to attend.
Bottom Line: Declines in Tuition Revenue Leave Many Colleges Financially SqueezedA survey by <ORGANIZATION>Moody’s Investors Service</ORGANIZATION> shows that median net tuition per student will grow more slowly than it did last year.
Wave of <ORGANIZATION>Diverse College Applicants Will Rise RapidlyMinority</ORGANIZATION> students will account for nearly half of public high-school graduates by 2020, says a report from the <ORGANIZATION>Western Interstate Commission for Higher Education</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> Says Colleges Must Be 'Reasonable' When Calculating Adjuncts' HoursPreparation time, not just hours in the classroom, should be counted, the agency says in a proposed rule. Eligibility for health benefits is at stake.
It's Time to Tell the Big Story, Says New President of <ORGANIZATION>American Historical Association</ORGANIZATION>"We need to try and claim a little bit bigger piece of the space in the public square," declares <PERSON>Kenneth Pomeranz</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> scholar at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Chicago</ORGANIZATION>.
New 'Right to Work' Laws Could Hobble Faculty UnionsA look at faculty groups in states that already have such laws shows, however, that collective bargaining can survive.
Wired Campus: Coursera Announces Details for Selling Certificates and Verifying Identities“Keystroke biometrics”—analyzing a user’s typing pattern and rhythm—will be a key part of the <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION> provider’s validation process.
Wired Campus: eCornell Offers a MOOC That Steers Students to a Paid Follow-UpStudents who finish the free course, in hospitality marketing, can enroll in a second, for-credit course and earn a certificate. The follow-up course costs $1,200.
The 'Alt-Ac' Track: Careers Without TenureIt came up again and again at this year's meeting that graduate education needs to be updated to prepare students for the labor realities they'll face.
After More Than 44 Years, <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Longest-Serving College</ORGANIZATION> President Finds His Work Still UnfinishedNorman <PERSON>C. Francis</PERSON>, who began leading <ORGANIZATION>Xavier University of Louisiana</ORGANIZATION> in 1968, has not lost his energy for his job.
Decades of Teaching End With One Last Crowd-Drawing LectureThe Rev. <PERSON>James V. Schall</PERSON>'s students at <LOCATION>Georgetown</LOCATION> asked if he could teach one more time before he retired. More than 700 people showed up.
Former <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> Mayor to <PERSON>Lead Kaplan</PERSON>; U. of <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> Gets Its First Chief Compliance OfficerTom <PERSON>Leppert</PERSON> became president of the <ORGANIZATION>Washington Post Company</ORGANIZATION>'s higher-education subsidiary. Read about that and other job-related news.
The Chronicle ReviewThe Delights of DisgustRevulsion can be a many-splendored thing. Recent books on it by philosophers are missing some of its nifty, nasty nuances.
Sex in the <ORGANIZATION>Muslim</ORGANIZATION> CityA savvy, eye-opening new book investigates intimacy in the Arab world.
Making Math PopTales of biographical and intellectual adventure inspire all kinds of students. Mathematicians are no exception.
When Bad Things Happen to Untenured PeopleCalculating the "appropriate" tenure-clock extension in cases like the illness and death of a child is next to impossible, but it's worth trying.
Shelf LifeForget the e-book buzz. Print is back.
An Anthropologist Goes IndieIndependent films and their relentless social critique have found an observer in <PERSON>Sherry Ortner</PERSON>.
CommentaryHow <ORGANIZATION>Facebook Can Ruin Study AbroadCellphones</ORGANIZATION> and social media protect students from culture shock, and that's a loss.
A Law-School Lesson, Learned the Hard WayIf law schools cannot clean up their marketing act, then authorities may take well-deserved action against their administrators.
Letter: A Better Placement Test Helps a Math Department in Multiple Ways“Improvement of the placement-exam structure needs to be recognized as a characteristic of a good university.”
AdviceWe Know You Can Read. So Can We.In which I sit through a conference panel and do not obtain enlightenment.
