
The latest discussions of MOOCs and other online courses often leave out consideration of minority students and the obstacles they might face in gaining access to technology, argues <PERSON>Corey Davis</PERSON>, director of online learning at Our Lady of the <ORGANIZATION>Lake University</ORGANIZATION>, in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. He challenges the Tech Therapy team and others to tell more-diverse stories as they consider the recent online boom.
Links mentioned in this episode:MOOC 2.0 blog
Each monthThe Chronicle’sTech Therapy podcastoffers analysis of and advice on what the latest gadgets and buzzwords mean for professors, administrators, and students. Join your hosts, <PERSON>Jeff Young</PERSON>,The <ORGANIZATION>Chronicle</ORGANIZATION>’s technology editor, and <PERSON>Warren Arbogast</PERSON>, a technology consultant who works with colleges, for a lively discussion—as well as interviews with leading thinkers in technology.
This entry was posted inUncategorized. Bookmark thepermalink.<PERSON>Jeffrey R. Young</PERSON>