
What are the biggest ideas in education technology this year, and who's driving them? For the second year in a row,The Chroniclehas identified a group of key innovators who are rebooting the academy, and we've profiled 10 of them on the pages that follow. This is not an endorsement of their projects: In some cases, the subjects of the profiles disagree with one another on how best to change higher education. But all of the people you'll meet here think technology could break established molds and help students learn more effectively, researchers make discoveries more easily, and colleges operate more efficiently. Earlier this year we invited readers and higher-education leaders to submit their nominations for this project, and we receivedmore than 125 entries.Ultimately, the selections were made by a group ofChronicleeditors and reporters, with a goal of considering innovators in various sectors.
<PERSON>Juan E. GilbertClemson U.
Al FilreisU</PERSON>. of <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>
Carol A. TwiggNational Center for Academic Transformation






<PERSON>William G. BowenIthaka S+R
Amy LaitinenNew</PERSON> <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> Foundation
<PERSON>Mohammad H. QayoumiSan Jose State U.
William D. LawSt</PERSON>. <ORGANIZATION>Petersburg College
Bethany</ORGANIZATION> NowviskieU. of <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>
<PERSON>Jason HoytPeerJ




Dan RosensweigChegg</PERSON>
Opinion
My Modern MOOC Experience
2013: Year of the Seminar
MOOCs and the Material World
Massive Open Online Adventure
Btw paper is due 2day
Go Where the Students Are
Twitter Meets Polonius
Illustration
Major Players in the MOOC Universe
