Professors in the philosophy department at <ORGANIZATION>San Jose State University</ORGANIZATION> wrote the following letter to make a direct appeal to <PERSON>Michael Sandel</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> professor whose <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION> on "Justice" they were being encouraged to use as part of the <ORGANIZATION>San Jose State</ORGANIZATION> curriculum.(See arelated articleand aresponse from Mr. <PERSON>Sandel</PERSON>.)
San Jose State U. Open Letter (PDF)San Jose State U. Open Letter (Text)