NewsYou're Distracted. This Professor Can Help.Cuts May Force Eagerly Awaited Efficiencies on NIHSequestration means an immediate 5-percent reduction in spending at an agency whose budget doubled from 1998 to 2003.
Efficiency and Academic Freedom Clash at CUNYFueling the debate are broader worries about the marginalization of the faculty and impatience with the slow pace of change at a time of shrinking public support.
In Win for Libraries Over Publishers, <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> Upholds Reselling of Foreign BooksThe case stemmed from a graduate student's importing of less-expensive textbooks to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> from abroad, and then reselling them at a profit.
The Unintended Consequences of Ending Merit AidThe discounts that colleges give applicants for good grades are coming under criticism. But cutting such merit aid won't necessarily mean more money for need-based aid.
Why One University Became a Hispanic-Serving <ORGANIZATION>InstitutionNotre Dame de Namur University</ORGANIZATION>, in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, saw significant advantages in acknowledging reality. The move has paid off.
The White House 'Nudger' Is Back on <PERSON>CampusCass Sunstein</PERSON>, former regulatory czar, is teaching "Inside Governemnt," a course at <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> with <PERSON>Lawrence Summers</PERSON>, and has written a memoir of his time in the <PERSON>Obama</PERSON>...
Researchers Protest Canadian Government's <ORGANIZATION>New Restrictions on Sharing DataCritics</ORGANIZATION> say the confidentiality rule is the latest in a series of efforts to limit public access to government-sponsored research.
Average Pay Increases for Academic Professionals Trailed Inflation This YearThe median base salary for professional staff members on college campuses increased by 2 percent in 2012-13.
Aspen Prize Honors 2 Community Colleges for Students' <ORGANIZATION>SuccessesSanta Barbara City College</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Walla Walla Community College</ORGANIZATION> were chosen, respectively, for achievements in academic and job-training efforts.
Student Aid Can Be Awarded for 'Competencies,' Not Just Credit HoursIn a long-awaited letter, the <ORGANIZATION>Education Department</ORGANIZATION> spells out how colleges may apply to use federal aid for new models of education.
Outrage Over Lavish Spending at St. <PERSON>John</PERSON>'s U. Threatens Its PresidentThe suicide of a dean on trial for theft from the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> university hasn't eased a crisis that may reach the highest levels of the administration.
Double Majors Produce Dynamic Thinkers, Study FindsDouble majors tend to gain creative-thinking skills, and they do so largely on their own, despite obstacles put in their way by academe.
Professors See a Lack of Professionalism Among StudentsMore than one-third of those surveyed said fewer than half of their upper-class students exhibited traits associated with being professional in the workplace.
In <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, the Ultimate Teaching Evaluation Comes With a $100,000 PrizeFour business professors delivered lectures before a group of students who would determine which one deserved a sizable award.
Foundation Chief Is Named Dean of <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Journalism School</ORGANIZATION>; <LOCATION>Oberlin Dean</LOCATION> to Lead <PERSON>Kenyon CollegeSteve Coll</PERSON>, departing president of the <ORGANIZATION>New America Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, will succeed <PERSON>Nicholas Lemann</PERSON>. Read about that and other job-related news.
A Cal State Chief Is Named Sole Finalist for Top Job at LSUIf confirmed, F. King <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON> would step into a new position at <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> State that merges the posts of system president and flagship chancellor.
Psychology Professor Engages a Whole Campus in Protecting Student Mental HealthFor a year, <PERSON>Robin D. Everall</PERSON> looked into mental-health needs at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Alberta</ORGANIZATION>. Now she's helping lead efforts to improve emotional health on the campus.
Selected New Books on Higher EducationTopics include the first-year college experiences of five "at risk" Mexican-American students and guidance for unemployed college graduates.
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Commerce Secretary Is Tapped to Lead U. of <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION> at <PERSON>MadisonRebecca M. Blank</PERSON>, a former public-policy dean at <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, will lead a campus that has been at the center of debates over the role of public flagship institutions.
The Chronicle ReviewThe New Industrial RevolutionThe next wave of robots could change the meaning of work.
Robots Aren't the Problem: It's UsAutomation will engender neither utopia nor dystopia. Humans alone are responsible for our society's economic future.
The Existential Quandaries of Robo-Serviced UtopiaThe gravest danger of offloading work is not a machine uprising but a human downgrading.
The Soul of InventionTechnology shifts gears. The workers who control it need to learn how to shift gears, too.
Robots Behind BarsCan robots commit crimes? And if so, a law scholar wonders, should they be rehabilitated or reprogrammed?
I Don't Want to Be Mooc'dCreative destruction is a fine economic theory, until you become its object.
ViewsLet's Do LunchTreating graduate students as people, not just scholars in training, will make them better professionals.
Considering Adjunct MiseryAlex Kudera's novel offers a realistic depiction of the life and psychology of a contingent faculty member.
Walk Deliberately, Don't Run, Toward Online EducationLet's experiment, but in assessing outcomes and cost savings, let's also insist on hard evidence.
The <ORGANIZATION>Brave New World of College</ORGANIZATION> BrandingElite colleges are ultimately in the business of maximizing status, not revenue. That's one of the reasons they don't mind running MOOCs at a loss.
