<ORGANIZATION>NewsA Research University for All PeopleBig Science</ORGANIZATION>'s Fuzzy MathIn the battle over the budget, the <ORGANIZATION>NIH</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>NSF</ORGANIZATION> look for new metrics to prove their worth.
<ORGANIZATION>New National Tally of College Completion Tries</ORGANIZATION> to Count All StudentsA report by the <ORGANIZATION>National Student Clearinghouse Research Center</ORGANIZATION> takes account of nontraditional and transfer students, whom federal data miss.
The Controversial Contradictions of <PERSON>Thomas JeffersonA</PERSON> new book on one of the founding fathers wins raves, but not from specialists in the field.
College, Reinvented: The FinalistsWhat kind of college would you create if you could start one from scratch?Chroniclereaders submitted their ideas, and now it's time to vote.
Economy Affects Students' Academic Performance as Well as Spending DecisionsThis year's National Survey of Student Engagement indicates that financial worries may be affecting classroom performance.
Grades and Tests May Miss What Matters Most in Learning"Deep approaches" to learning figure prominently in the new edition of the National Survey of Student Engagement.
Professors of the Year Advise Their Peers: Keep Learning and AdaptingThe four national winners of the coveted award share their ideas about effective teaching.
Tenure Decisions at <ORGANIZATION>Southern Cal Strongly Favor White Men</ORGANIZATION>, Data in Complaint SuggestA rejected candidate and a colleague collected data on decisions in a dozen departments over 14 years. They found "stark" disparities by ethnicity and gender.
Court Strikes Down <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s Ban on Race-Conscious AdmissionsA divided appellate court held that the state law unconstitutionally made it harder for minorities to seek preferences than for other groups.
Education Department Adopts Crucial Reform for Disabled BorrowersAfter a ProPublica investigation published by The <ORGANIZATION>Chronicle</ORGANIZATION> spurred public pressure, the agency conducted a sweeping overhaul of its troubled disability-review program.
Storm Damage at <ORGANIZATION>NYU</ORGANIZATION> Library Offers Lessons for Disaster Planning in the StacksIn an era of supersize disasters like <PERSON>Hurricane Sandy</PERSON>, academic libraries need to be ready for more than just burst-pipe scenarios.
Indian Students Crowd Private Campuses, Despite Concerns Over QualityIn a country without enough college seats, proprietary institutions like <ORGANIZATION>Lovely Professional University</ORGANIZATION> rush to fill the gap.
Old, Boring, White, and Mean: How Professors Appear on the Small ScreenThey may be fictional characters, but TV shows' images of professors can have a big effect on real-life students, a researcher suggests.
<PERSON>Deans</PERSON>' Ideas About Hiring Adjuncts Differ From Reality, Survey FindsMany would prefer having more faculty on the tenure track, but feel trapped by the need to keep costs down and ensure access.
<ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>'s Take a <ORGANIZATION>Major Step Toward College</ORGANIZATION> CreditIn a pilot project, the council will consider five to 10 Coursera offerings and certify them if it finds them equivalent to courses taught by accredited colleges.
Wired Campus: 10 Highly Selective Colleges Form Consortium to Offer Online CoursesStudents at the institutions can earn credit from any college in the group, while students who are not enrolled at those colleges can apply to take the courses.
Wired Campus: Ed-Tech Start-Ups Are Grilled by Venture Capitalists in Business CompetitionEducause held its first contest pitting new businesses against one another, a move that brought a dose of American Idol to its annual conference this week.
U. of <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>'s New President Tweets the Word OutSanta <PERSON>Jeremy Ono</PERSON>, a self-described "gregarious guy," isn't shy about trumpeting his university's strengths.
Met Veteran Leads a University's New Museum on the Irish FamineGrace <PERSON>Brady</PERSON> is executive director of <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>'s Great Hunger Museum, started at <ORGANIZATION>Quinnipiac University</ORGANIZATION> because of the interest of the president and two donors.
Transitions: Head of White House Effort to Lead Morehouse; U. of <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> Gets New PresidentJohn <PERSON>S. Wilson Jr.</PERSON>, who directs a White House program on historically <PERSON>black</PERSON> colleges, will be <ORGANIZATION>Morehouse College</ORGANIZATION>'s next president. Read about that and other job-related news.
The Chronicle ReviewEurope May Be Hurting, but <ORGANIZATION>E.U.</ORGANIZATION> Studies Is Going StrongThe booming field may be too enthusiastic about its subject, critics say.
The Evolutionary Mystery of HomosexualityIf reproduction is key to a trait’s endurance, why has this anti-reproductive trait endured?
Gender, Generations, and Faculty ConflictWill academe's mothers and daughters repeat the errors of its fathers and sons?
My Communist GrandfatherA scholar wrestles with the legacy of her grandfather, onetime leader of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>’s <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION>.
A Feast of Jewish Culture, in 10 VolumesMore than a decade ago, <PERSON>Felix Posen</PERSON> had a big idea.
CommentaryPut Your Endowment Money Where Your Mission IsColleges should demand that the companies in which their endowments are invested disclose their political spending.
The Genius in the ClassroomOne remarkable student with progressive ideas can elevate an entire class.
To Teach Evolution, You Have to Understand CreationistsScientists' blundering hostility toward creationism actually encourages creationist belief. We need to add respect to our efforts at persuasion.
Adjuncts Earn Respect With Union's Help"We negotiated a contract (just renewed) that gave us, for the first time, job security, benefits, a hike in the measly pre-unionization pay."
AdviceYour Unofficial Job-Application ChecklistIt's time for an update and recasting of the role of social media in academic career advancement.
