NewsPay and Perks Creep Up for <ORGANIZATION>Private-College</ORGANIZATION> PresidentsAt <LOCATION>Ohio State</LOCATION>, Sports Plays It StraightThe Buckeyes are spending more than $1-million a year to supersize their rules-enforcement staff.
In a Secret Classroom in <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, Immigrants Learn to <ORGANIZATION>HopeFreedom University</ORGANIZATION> offers them a path to college in a state where they are banned from several top universities.
School's Curriculum Director Wins Build-Your-Own-College ContestCollege of the Global Village, envisioned by <PERSON>Peter Schmidt</PERSON>, would emphasize experiential learning in eight-week blocks of study.
From Freedom U. to <LOCATION>Syracuse</LOCATION> U.: One Student's StoryKeish <PERSON>Kim</PERSON> had a lifetime of being told to be guarded, in both actions and ambitions. Then she heard about a classroom in <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga</LOCATION>.
Doctoral Degrees Rose in 2011, but Career Options Weren't So <ORGANIZATION>RosyA National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> survey shows a gain in degrees awarded and a decline in the share of degree recipients with job or postdoc commitments.
<ORGANIZATION>NSF</ORGANIZATION>'s Premier Graduate Grant Program Gets an Overseas ExpansionSome research fellows will now be offered a fourth year working at a university lab abroad.
After Century of Dispute, <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION> Join Together to Give Incan Artifacts a HomeEven during the public fight, academics from both countries were collaborating on the best way to preserve the legacy of Machu Picchu.
Educators, Employers, and Jobless Graduates Point Fingers at Roots of UnemploymentLack of communication and understanding among the three groups help explain the millions of young graduates without jobs, a report says.
Providers of Free MOOC's Now Charge Employers for Access to Student DataSeveral high-profile tech companies have already signed up for <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON>'s new employee-matching service. Udacity offers a similar service.
<ORGANIZATION>AAUP</ORGANIZATION> Outlines Concerns About <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION>'s Collaboration With SingaporeIn an open letter, the association asks <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION> to release information about how it is dealing with issues related to <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION>'s record on political and civil liberties.
'Metro' Unionizing Strategy Is Viewed as a Means to Empower Adjunct FacultySpeakers at a forum praised a strategy being tried in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, that seeks to rally local support for adjuncts and turn market forces to their advantage.
<LOCATION>Michigan Union</LOCATION>'s Report Challenges Assumptions About Adjuncts' PayThe report, which comes as contract talks begin, seeks to compare and value the services provided by major segments of the academic work force.
Ph.D.'s From Top Political-Science Programs Dominate Hiring, Research FindsDepartments at 11 elite universities provide half of the field's tenured and tenure-track professors, according to an analysis of more than 3,000 professors.
<PERSON>Carnegie</PERSON>, the Founder of the <LOCATION>Credit-Hour</LOCATION>, Seeks Its MakeoverIdeas for what should replace the century-old metric include some measure of competency instead of time spent in class.
Players: Report Describes Disturbing Racial Inequities in 6 Powerful Sports ConferencesAt institutions that won the four most recent BCS national championships, just 42 percent of black athletes graduate within six years, a new study has found.
U. of <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>'s New President Will Look at How Faculty Measure UpSandra <PERSON>K. Woodley</PERSON>, who struggled to finish college herself, is a champion of using data analysis to cut costs and predict student success.
Policy Leader to <ORGANIZATION>Shift From Gates Foundation to College</ORGANIZATION> <PERSON>BoardStefanie Sanford</PERSON>, who favors making educational standards more consistent across the country, will join the <ORGANIZATION>College Board</ORGANIZATION>, which oversees the SAT.
Transitions: <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> Tech Gets New President; Controversy Over Former Mexican President's Appointment at HarvardAn online petition asks <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> not to let <PERSON>Felipe Calderón</PERSON> become a fellow there. Read about that and other job-related news.
The Chronicle ReviewThe Constitution: Who Needs It?<PERSON>Louis Michael Seidman</PERSON> wants to scrap <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s foundational document, and he has anticipated your objections.
Book-Review AngstBracing for readers' reactions to one's book is agony, but something would be terribly wrong if you didn't care.
Long Walks, Deep ThoughtsWhen the legs are in motion, intellectual history suggests, the mind often follows.
The Saint Who Would Be SantaNo, <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, there is not a <LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION>. But there was a St. <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON>.
Size Isn't EverythingLearning mash-ups have more potential than MOOC-centered, profit-squeezing, online economies of scale.
Poetry Makes You WeirdMore important, it helps you understand the weirdness around you.
What We'll Settle ForWhile a choice may not be optimal, making it anyway, and accepting the inherent trade-offs, might be the best move you can make.
CommentaryAthletes Need Education for Life, Not Eligibility at Any CostAcademic advisers who work with college sports programs need to push back against stereotypes by putting students first.
How <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s Elite Universities Will Have to ChangeAs Chinese universities move up in world rankings, their systems for peer review must meet world-class standards.
Become Need-Blind? For Colleges, It's the Wrong QuestionLook beyond the label to get to the heart of the matter. Is the college committing resources to a socioeconomically diverse student body? Or just talking about it?
Phony Majors for Athletes Signal Our Surrender“Crafting yet another phony major signals that we have given up in the important goal of providing athletes with the same quality college education that all students...
AdvicePlagiarism in Grant ProposalsSome federal agencies are using software to detect unattributed copying in scholars' research proposals.
