Udacity, a <LOCATION>Silicon Valley</LOCATION> start-up that creates online college classes, will announce on Tuesday a deal with <ORGANIZATION>San Jose State University</ORGANIZATION> for a series of remedial and introductory courses,The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Timesreported. Courses in the pilot program—which will include remedial algebra, college-level algebra, and introductory statistics—will be limited 300 students. The cost of each three-unit course will be $150, significantly less than regular San Jose State tuition.
Source:NytimesVia:The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> TimesThe state university’s deal with Udacity is the first time that professors at a university have collaborated with a provider of a MOOC—massively open online course—to create courses with students first watching videos on their own, with support from online mentors, and then coming to class to work on assignments with a professor. Eventually, such blended courses could be offered to hundreds of thousands of students in the state.
Read more at:www.nytimes.com
<PERSON>Charles Huckabee</PERSON>