Nominee's nameNominee's institutionCategoryThe big ideaEd CabellonBridgewater State UniversityStudent LifeExtraordinary speaker, blogger and tech guru.<PERSON>Christoph BreglerNew York UniversityResearch</PERSON> and ScholarshipPioneer in motion capture.Professor <PERSON>Kris ManjapraTufts</PERSON> UniversityTeachingLinking two classrooms across the world.<PERSON>Michael D.</PERSON> <ORGANIZATION>AbbiattiArkansas Research and Education Optical NetworkOtherExecutive</ORGANIZATION> director of ARE-ON, a high-speed network touching every higher education institution in <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>.<PERSON>Allan WalkerUtah</PERSON> State UniversityBusiness ModelsCreated an interactive Safety map of campus.<PERSON>Mike RichwalskyJohn Carroll</PERSON> UniversityPublishingMajor proponents of using social media, the cloud and WordPress usage in higher education.<PERSON>Brian D. VossUniversity</PERSON> of <PERSON>MarylandAdministrationHonest</PERSON> and realistic approach to IT problems.<PERSON>Ronald YarosUniversity</PERSON> of MarylandTeachingUses blogger.com for portfolio grades and twitter in his #jour150 class.<PERSON>Shane StroupInver</PERSON> Hills Community CollegeTeachingMaking class more accessible with <ORGANIZATION>Facebook</ORGANIZATION> and recorded lectures on <ORGANIZATION>YouTube</ORGANIZATION>.The <ORGANIZATION>UGLC EnvisioneersThe University of Texas</ORGANIZATION> at El PasoTeachingPushing the boundaries from new classroom designs to app development.<PERSON>David WeinbergerHarvard</PERSON> law school libraryLibrariesHeads up the <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> library innovation lab.<PERSON>Scott Brandt</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jake Carlson</PERSON>, andamp; <PERSON>MIchael WittPurdue</PERSON> UniversityLibrariesImplemented the Data Curation Profiles Toolkit.<PERSON>David P. Pursell</PERSON>; <PERSON>Joseph C. Sloop</PERSON>; <PERSON>Richard L. Pennington</PERSON>; <PERSON>Julia B. Paredes</PERSON>; <PERSON>Mai Yin Tsoi</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>Sonal DekhaneGeorgia Gwinnett</ORGANIZATION> CollegeTeachingLaunched  organic chemistry course accessible in its entirety via smartphones.<PERSON>Nico CloeteCenter</PERSON> for Higher Education Trust, South AfricaOtherFoundational to the burgeoning field of Learning Spaces Research. He has provided solid empirical evidence to supportMr. <PERSON>Tim PorterUniversity</PERSON> of the Incarnate Word and AppdictionStudioAccessCreated anti-bullying software for school districts.<PERSON>James Kenigsberg2U</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Inc.</ORGANIZATION>AccessBuilt a game-changing delivery system for top-tier universities to deliver high-quality instruction online.Dr. <PERSON>Najib Manea</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>PhDUniversity of New Mexico Valencia</ORGANIZATION> CampusOtherEquipped 60% of classrooms on campus with the ability to capture lectures.<PERSON>Nish</PERSON> SonwalkarUnited States Distance Learning AssociationTeachingOften referred to as the "Father of Adaptive Learning."<PERSON>Anthony RotoloiSchool</PERSON> at <ORGANIZATION>Syracuse</ORGANIZATION> UniversityTeachingTaught an innovative course called "Social Media and the 2012 Election", know as #ElectionClass on twitter.<PERSON>Nadine DexterUniversity</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Central Flroida College of MedicineLibrariesUses</ORGANIZATION> latest technology available for medical students to use with patient care, research and educational activities.<PERSON>John FontaineBlackboardOtherOne</PERSON> of the original developers of Blackboard Learn, the mostly widely adopted <ORGANIZATION>LMS</ORGANIZATION> in higher educations.<PERSON>Alison DoubledayUniversity</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> - ChicagoTeachingIntegrating iPads into gross anatomy education.<PERSON>Ken ElliotCatawba</PERSON> <ORGANIZATION>Valley Community</ORGANIZATION> CollegeAdministrationMaintaining an amazingly tech saavy and efficient staff.<PERSON>Alec CourosUniversity</PERSON> of ReginaTeachingFacilitated an open, online graduate course that is now seen as a fundamental influence for the early MOOC movement.<PERSON>Noah FinkelsteinUniversity</PERSON> of ColoradoTeachingRevamping the way in which STEM subjects are taught at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Colorado</ORGANIZATION>.<PERSON>Lance MerkerOmniUpdateOtherPresident</PERSON> of OmniUpdate, a leading content management system (CMS) serving higher education.Paulinne SaligaSociety of Architectural HistoriansPublishingLaunched three online academic resources that have revolutionized the field of architectural history.<PERSON>D. Christopher BrooksUniversity</PERSON> of MinnesotaResearch and ScholarshipMajor reseacher in the burgeoning field of Learning Spaces Research.<PERSON>Paul FreedmanAltiusEdAccessMaking</PERSON> education accessible to everyone and increase success rates by creating an platform that tailors to student's interest.<PERSON>Salman KhanKhan AcademyOtherCreated Khan Academy</PERSON>, a non-profit education site with more than 4,000 micro lectures.<PERSON>Patricia HoganNorthern Michigan UniversityTeachingApplied Wix</PERSON> technology to promote an active learning model for undergraduate students.<PERSON>Kyle PeckPenn</PERSON> State UniversityBusiness ModelsPioneering the area of badges in higher education.<PERSON>Maciej</PERSON> Olpinskitravelmooc.comBusiness ModelsFounded Travelmooc, enabling students to join experimental learning environments.Dr. <PERSON>Candis BestLearningatewayAccessDeveloping</PERSON> virtual education and support model that targets students with weak academic foundationsCharles SeveranceUniversity of MichiganTeachingChampion of open licensing, open content and open software standards.<PERSON>Samantha Adams</PERSON> BeckerNew Media Consortium (<ORGANIZATION>NMC</ORGANIZATION>)Research and ScholarshipDirector of communications for the <ORGANIZATION>NMC</ORGANIZATION>, and the lead writer/researcher for the Horizon Report series.<LOCATION>Altius</LOCATION> EducationAltius Education / Ivy Bridge CollegeOtherOffers a high-quality, flexible online education that appeals to students of all ages.Dr.<PERSON>Juan GilbertClemson</PERSON> UniversityResearch and ScholarshipNamed by President <PERSON>Obama</PERSON> as one of the top ten STEM mentors in nation.<PERSON>Harpreet SinghAcademic RoomResearch</PERSON> and ScholarshipCo-founder of Academic Room, a social platform connecting industry with academic experts within communities of practice.<ORGANIZATION>Jeannie CrowleyBank Street College of EducationTeachingStarted</ORGANIZATION> an Online Learning Collective <ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION>+ community to bring together professionals to experiment with new forms of online ed.<PERSON>Jeet BanerjeeStatFuseStudent LifeCo-founded</PERSON> website that helps high school students and their parents with a variety of college-related affairs.<PERSON>Brian ShawKnowledge ElementsTeachingBehind</PERSON> the innovations released by Knowledge Elements that improve student online learning.<PERSON>Jason Thatcher</PERSON>, PhDClemson UniversityResearch and ScholarshipCatalyzing research on the social web on campus and across the nation.Dr. <PERSON>Patrick JuolaDuquesne UniversityResearch</PERSON> and ScholarshipHelping to decipher history and improve computer security.<PERSON>Tracy FullertonUniversity</PERSON> of Southern CaliforniaTeachingCreating games that make a measurable difference in attracting and retaining college students.Dr. <PERSON>Pam Northrup</PERSON>, Dr. <PERSON>Dave Dawson</PERSON>, Vice Admiral <PERSON>Gerry Hoewing</PERSON>, <PERSON>Marc WatsonUniversity</PERSON> of <LOCATION>West Florida</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>The National Flight Academy</ORGANIZATION>, TEQGames at Universal StudiosTeachingWorking to change the way we educate children and lead students to choose STEM careers.eTutoring.orgeTutoring.orgOtherCurrently meeting the online tutoring needs of over 120 institutions.Dr. Macello MedeirosUNEB / BrazilResearch and ScholarshipDeveloped a Sound Console Simulator Training (in project), the Virtual Console.<PERSON>Randy BestAcademic</PERSON> PartnershipsBusiness ModelsFounded three progressive organizations actively advancing the mission of democratizing education.<PERSON>Hernan JaramilloTareasplusOtherFounder</PERSON> and CEO of  a company specializing in web design, Internet consulting and launching Internet ideas.<PERSON>Beth DavisWCETOtherHelping</PERSON> higher education think about student success in new ways.<PERSON>Robbie MeltonTennessee Board</PERSON> of RegentsOtherExploring the applicability of mobile apps for education.<PERSON>J.J. AllaireRStudioTeachingDedicated</PERSON> to providing software, education, and services for the R statistical computing environment.<PERSON>Ali JafariIndiana UniversityOtherInventor</PERSON> of On Course, ANGEL Learning, <PERSON>Epsilen</PERSON>, and now Course Networking.<PERSON>Herminia DinTeachingResearches</PERSON> how the use of new technologies offers the potential to transform teaching and learning in art.<PERSON>Shai ReshefUniversity</PERSON> of the PeopleBusiness <ORGANIZATION>ModelsCreated University of the People</ORGANIZATION>, a non-profit, online, tuition-free University.<PERSON>Philip C. ReppBall</PERSON> State UniversityAdministrationPioneered a student-centered approach to information technology at <ORGANIZATION>Ball State University</ORGANIZATION>.<PERSON>Brian SowardsUSEEDBusiness</PERSON> ModelsCreating system that is on the forefront of education theories.Dr. <PERSON>George VeletsianosUniversity</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> at AustinResearch and ScholarshipStudies the design of emerging technologies and pedagogies in online and hybrid education settings.<PERSON>Bobby HollemanUniversity</PERSON> of ArkansasAccessDeveloping the statewide <ORGANIZATION>KENEX</ORGANIZATION> Cloud, which re-envisions how colleges and universities in <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> work collaboratively to meet technological needsGregory <ORGANIZATION>McNealPepperdine University School of LawTeachingSetting</ORGANIZATION> a powerful example of how modern technology can be used to instruct subject matters with even the oldest of roots.<PERSON>Ryan FiskManhattanville</PERSON> CollegeTeaching'Flipped' his own classroom, providing instructional videos, screenshots, and step-by-step tutorials on a <ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> Drive account.<PERSON>Kane</PERSON> SarhanEnstituteBusiness ModelsCreating a new model of higher education through startup or business apprenticeships.<PERSON>Magí AlmirallUniversitat Oberta de CatalunyaOtherResponsible</PERSON> for what has been the first truly interoperable higher ed online campus.<ORGANIZATION>Kiran KodithalaN2N Services Inc.</ORGANIZATION>AdministrationWorked to develop solutions to address technology gaps with <ORGANIZATION>Student Information Systems</ORGANIZATION> and third-party product for education.<PERSON>Rifka CookNorthwestern UniversityTeachingUses</PERSON> “clickers” to engage her students and increase their learning motivation.<PERSON>Kenneth C. GreenCampus</PERSON> Computing ProjectResearch and ScholarshipResearch on campus IT planning and policy issues has helped to shape, inform, and advance the role of information technology.<PERSON>Shaila IttycheriaEnstituteBusiness ModelsNew</PERSON> low-cost model of higher education with an apprenticeship-based “Learn by Doing” approach.BoundlessBusiness ModelsRevolutionizing textbooks and providing students with free alternatives.<PERSON>Eric StortzColorado</PERSON> Technical UniversityStudent LifeSought to motivate and inspire students toward the completion of their academic goals.<PERSON>Hannah ChoiUniversity</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> at Urbana-ChampaignOtherChallenges her Instructional Design team to use cutting-edge learning theories and instructional design models.<PERSON>Ray HendersonBlackboard</PERSON> <ORGANIZATION>Inc.</ORGANIZATION>OtherOne of the first in industry to champion open education standards.<PERSON>Judd RattnerIntellidemiaAdministrationProvides</PERSON> much needed administrative efficiencies and ensures students are receiving the best possible communication.<PERSON>Kyle JudahRecoVendAdministrationFocused</PERSON> on helping schools save money.<PERSON>David K. MoldoffAcademyOne</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Inc.</ORGANIZATION>AccessDeveloped methods, workflows, and tools that help advance the full spectrum of today’s college learners.Lev GonickCase <ORGANIZATION>Western Reserve University</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland</ORGANIZATION> OHAdministrationFounded OneCommunity to create a connected community throughout <LOCATION>Northeast Ohio</LOCATION> through ultra broadband wired and wireless networks.Prof. <PERSON>Jin Kim Montclare</PERSON> and student <ORGANIZATION>Carlo YuviencoPolytechnic Institute of New York UniversityAccessDeveloped</ORGANIZATION> an app for <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> schools that is an educational tool about chemistry.<PERSON>Mickey LevitanCourseloadTeachingTransforming</PERSON> the way students access digital texts and classroom materials.Prof. <ORGANIZATION>Nasir MemonPolytechnic Institute of New York UniversityTeachingEnergized</ORGANIZATION> and empowered a virtual army of youthful cyber ninjas to address a severe shortage of cybersecurity experts.<PERSON>Andrew GossenCornell UniversityStudent LifeInsightful</PERSON> leadership in using new technology to engage alumni through their social networks.<PERSON>Fred HurstNorthern Arizona UniversityBusiness ModelsHelps</PERSON> students pursue higher education through alternative learning environments.<PERSON>Tyce MillerAirWatchAccessHelping</PERSON> both students and staff at higher education institutions better use technology.<PERSON>Mike SweetCredoBusiness ModelsPartners</PERSON> with libraries to improve retention and support transferability of critical thinking and other information literacy skills beyond campus.<PERSON>Mehdi MaghsoodniaRafter</PERSON>, Inc.Business ModelsThe driving force behind founding <PERSON>Rafter</PERSON>, which addresses issues around course materials to lower the overall cost of education nationwide.<PERSON>Jared CejaChaffey CollegeBusiness ModelsUnder</PERSON> his guidance, the <ORGANIZATION>Chaffey College Bookstore</ORGANIZATION> has seen its market share increase over 50 percent this fall.<PERSON>Chris NixonUniversity</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> - FayettevilleAdministrationProduced several innovations this year that enhance services for students and the larger educational community.<PERSON>Sam Gustman</PERSON>, Chief Technology Officer for ITS <ORGANIZATION>Shoah Foundation Institute for Visual History and Education</ORGANIZATION>, Associate Dean, <ORGANIZATION>USC LibrariesUniversity of Southern</ORGANIZATION> CaliforniaLibrariesCreated a digital repository that allows the preservation and distribution of testimonials of survivors of the Holocaust and genocides around the world.<PERSON>Chris GamstCCS Presentation SystemsOtherHelps</PERSON> both students and administrations save time and money.<PERSON>Karen Symms</PERSON> GallagherUniversity of <ORGANIZATION>Southern California Rossier School of EducationAdministrationLaunched</ORGANIZATION> an online Master of Arts in Teaching degree that has since graduated nearly 1,200 teachers in every state and in 40 countries.<PERSON>Joseph CevetelloUniversity</PERSON> of Southern CaliforniaAdministrationManaging a program to update every  learning space on campus and more effectively connect students and faculty with the learning environment best suited to their needs.<PERSON>Stephen LuUniversity</PERSON> of Southern CaliforniaTeachingThe driving force behind an international education partnership that allows students from around the world to interact and collaborate in a virtual “classroom without borders.”<PERSON>Michael Gosz</PERSON>, Ph.D.<ORGANIZATION>Illinois Institute of TechnologyAdministrationLeads</ORGANIZATION> one of <ORGANIZATION>IIT</ORGANIZATION>'s newest signature initiatives: The Idea Shop, a 13,000 square foot facility composed of a rapid prototyping lab, collaborative teaming areas, and formal classroom space.<PERSON>Richard A. DeMilloGeorgia</PERSON> <ORGANIZATION>Institute of TechnologyAdministrationLeader</ORGANIZATION> in defining the next generation of educational practices and technologies for higher education.<ORGANIZATION>Kayvon BeykpourBlackboard Inc.</ORGANIZATION>OtherLeads the <ORGANIZATION>Blackboard Mobile</ORGANIZATION> team in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.<PERSON>Allison GageSOPHIAOtherClosing</PERSON> the achievement and affordability gap by addressing the urgent social issues of academic disparity.<PERSON>Jeff GrannCapella</PERSON> UniversityOtherImplementing near real-time reporting that contains information on each student’s demonstration of course competencies.<PERSON>Ryen Borden</PERSON>, Executive Director of the <ORGANIZATION>Sanford Inspire ProgramMary Lou Fulton Teachers College</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Arizona State</ORGANIZATION> UniversityTeachingCreating a series of interactive video games to help novice teachers develop knowledge and skills.<PERSON>Jon KolkoMyEduStudent LifeFocuses</PERSON> on bringing the power of design to social enterprises, with an emphasis on entrepreneurship and large-scale industry disruption.<PERSON>Michael CrosnoMyEduAccessHas</PERSON> dedicated himself to improving what he calls the “return on education” for college students of all kinds.<PERSON>Troy WilliamsPublishingResponsible</PERSON> for managing a portfolio of innovative ed-tech companies that will directly impact students’ learning outcomes and behaviors.Chip Paucek2U (formerly 2tor)Business ModelsCo-founded 2U, which has impacted over 6,000 teachers, social workers, nurses, and public administrations.<PERSON>K. Derek WeberRaritan</PERSON> <ORGANIZATION>Valley Community</ORGANIZATION> CollegeTeachingBrings his classes to life through the intentional use of technology to incite inquiry based active learning.<PERSON>Rebecca JoffreyTuck</PERSON> School of BusinessAdministrationResponsible for leading the charge in transforming the way career conversations happen at <ORGANIZATION>Tuck School of Business</ORGANIZATION>.<PERSON>Andrew Smith</PERSON> LewisCeregoBusiness ModelsDemocratizing adaptive learning platforms by making it possible for anyone to put brain science to use.<PERSON>Gregory Möller</PERSON>, Ph.DUniversity of IdahoTeachingWorks at the bleeding edge of technology in the teaching and learning environment.Dr. <PERSON>Stephen C-Y LuUniversity</PERSON> of Southern CaliforniaTeachingFounder of the <ORGANIZATION>Viterbi iPodia Alliance</ORGANIZATION>, which allows students from countries across the globe to take the same class at the same time.<PERSON>Joe MoxleyUniversity</PERSON> of South FloridaPublishingMade significant arguments for the value of digital theses and dissertations and open source projects.<LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> BeckmanLincoln Memorial UniversityAdministrationUsing interactive technology in each and every class session (with a very few exceptions).Sallie SevernsAnswer UndergroundOtherHelping students learn by connecting them with study groups across the country.TaskstreamTaskstreamAdministrationManage assessment data in a way that streamlines workflow and improves processes, engagement and utilization of data.<PERSON>Robert BeichnerNorth</PERSON> <ORGANIZATION>Carolina State</ORGANIZATION> UniversityTeachingTreating the classroom and its furnishings as technology.<ORGANIZATION>Scott HinesWorld Education University</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>WEU</ORGANIZATION>)<ORGANIZATION>Business ModelsCo-founded World Education University</ORGANIZATION>, the world’s first tuition-free, online, global higher education institution.The InnovationSpace/Jennifer SparrowVirginia TechTeachingSupporting students through a variety of digital fluency trainings.<PERSON>Sebastian</PERSON> ThrunStanford/UdacityBusiness ModelsStruck a new deal to provide for-credit education on <LOCATION>Udacity</LOCATION>.<PERSON>Todd A. Hitchcock</PERSON>, Senior Vice President, Online Solutions andamp; <ORGANIZATION>Business Development for PearsonPearson Learning</ORGANIZATION> SolutionsAccessDriving force in creating student-centered online courseware that provides rich and engaging learning experiences.<PERSON>Andrew TongeKent</PERSON> State UniversityTeachingUsing a completely online computer learning model since 2011 for math courses.