<PERSON>NewsEboo Patel</PERSON> Has a DreamCollege Confidential: A Field GuideWhat began as an admissions Web site for the anxious has become a culture with its own ethos, language, and rituals.
48 Hours of Worry and Waiting at Suspect's CampusThe discovery that one of the suspects in the <LOCATION>Boston Marathon</LOCATION> bombings was a student at <ORGANIZATION>UMass-Dartmouth</ORGANIZATION> led to an unnerving ordeal for the campus.
International Students Ask: Is It Safe to Study in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>?The death of a Chinese graduate student in the <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> bombings focuses new attention on what has become a mounting concern.
<ORGANIZATION>Illinois College Find</ORGANIZATION> a Way to Help Low-Income Students Go AbroadThe small college gives $2,000 to each one of its students, many of them low-income, for international study.
Adjuncts' Advocates Call for Fair Treatment on Work-Hour CalculationsProposed guidance for employers under the new health law takes note of special concerns for adjuncts. Their advocates spoke up at a hearing.
Why Some Colleges Are Saying No to MOOCs, at Least for NowAmherst's rejection of edX could signal the end of the honeymoon phase for massive open online courses.
U. of <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Urbana-Champaign</ORGANIZATION> Plans to Add 500 Full-Time ProfessorsThe hiring over the next five to seven years will attempt to restore the size of the university's faculty to its level in 2007, before the recession hit.
<ORGANIZATION>New College Chiefs Must Meet Revenue and Innovation</ORGANIZATION> ChallengesAs a wave of community-college presidents retires, their successors confront a day of reckoning, said speakers at the sector's annual meeting.
Groups Describe Efforts to Push More Students Toward Degree CompletionGetting students past remedial courses and helping them focus their academic goals were among strategies discussed at a meeting of college leaders.
Helping Black Men Succeed as Students Is Focus of Community-College MeetingSeveral sessions at the annual conference were devoted to how colleges are working to raise the proportion of black men who earn postsecondary credentials.
A Trove of <PERSON>Darwin</PERSON>'s Correspondence Is Published OnlineCharles <PERSON>Darwin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Joseph Dalton Hooker</PERSON> exchanged some 1,200 letters over the course of 40 years. Now the correspondence is available online.
Oregon Considers Big Changes in Governance of Higher EducationLegislation would redistribute authority, and control of funds, among old and new boards.
An Entrepreneur Reaches for the 'Holy Grail' of Online EducationThe push for academic integrity bedevils efforts to fill online vacancies with students who can't get into the classes at their own colleges.
2 Years of For-Profit College? Earnings No Better Than After High SchoolA study has found that graduates of for-profit institutions' two-year programs earn about the same as students who finish only secondary school.
UMass Graduate Student Talks About Economists' Mistake That Made Austerity a PolicyThomas <PERSON>Herndon</PERSON> is the talk of economics after demonstrating flaws in a hugely influential 2010 journal article.
Parents' Education Level Is Weak Predictor of Students' Learning Habits, Study FindsStudents whose parents earned baccalaureate degrees were the least likely to engage in deep learning.
Looking Back, <LOCATION>Departing City U. of New York</LOCATION> Chief Says He Has No RegretsMatthew <PERSON>Goldstein</PERSON> has earned praise for his work leading the 24-institution system, although there remain conflicts with faculty groups over policy.
<ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION> Names Its Provost as Its Next PresidentChristopher <PERSON>L. Eisgruber</PERSON>, a constitutional scholar, will replace <PERSON>Shirley M. Tilghman</PERSON>, who announced last fall that she would step down this year.
Former <ORGANIZATION>Dowling College</ORGANIZATION> President to <ORGANIZATION>Lead Portland Community College</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Penn State</ORGANIZATION> Gets New ProvostJeremy <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> will replace the current community-college leader, <PERSON>Preston Pulliams</PERSON>, who is retiring. Read about that and other job-related news.
<ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> Professor Guides Students Who Write Textbooks on Afghan LawErik <PERSON>G. Jensen</PERSON> works with law students at the university who are writing law textbooks for their counterparts in <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> and other developing countries.
THe Digital Campus 2013The Idea Makers: Tech Innovators 2013These thinkers are shaking up campuses with some of the biggest ideas in education technology.
Software to Enhance Diversity in AdmissionsJuan <PERSON>E. Gilbert</PERSON> has developed a computer program that provides a true and fair "holistic review," he says.
Making His MOOC an 'Outreach for Poetry'The professor is not interested in the class's completion rate but in the fact that more people are reading the poems than ever before.
Fighting to Reinvent Teaching and Keep Costs DownThe leader of the <ORGANIZATION>National Center for Academic Transformation</ORGANIZATION> has been in the forefront of technology in higher education since 1980.
Listening to Online Education's OmbudsmanThe economist and former <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION> president wants to apply rigorous experiments to massive open courses.
Helping Colleges Move Beyond the Credit HourA deputy director of the <ORGANIZATION>New America Foundation</ORGANIZATION> works to increase acceptance of competency-based education.
Learning From Big BusinessThose who stubbornly clung to the railroad business failed, says one college president, while those who diversified, considering their mission as transportation, thrived.
Pushing a Data-Driven Culture on One CampusA veteran community-college leader sees value in knowing the numbers.
Devising New Roles for Scholars Who Can CodeA digital researcher pushes the field to ensure that gender, race, ethnicity, and economic status aren't left out.
Asking Authors to Buy 'Memberships' for Open AccessA geneticist started PeerJ to show that academic publishing can be faster and cheaper.
From Textbook Rentals to 'Student Hub'The chief executive of <LOCATION>Chegg</LOCATION> wants to help students with more than just textbook rentals.
The Major Players in the MOOC UniverseExplore connections among the major players.
My Modern MOOC ExperienceA college president is enchanted by the diversity and drive of his online students.
2013: Year of the SeminarNo MOOC can give young minds the in-person experience of working directly with older experts to create, deepen, and connect ideas.
MOOCs and the Material WorldWhat brick-and-mortar classrooms still provide is that moment when people confront a problem hands-on in the same local space.
Massive Open Online AdventureTeaching a MOOC is not for the faint-hearted (or the untenured).
Using Social Networking to Control First-Year StressAn adult student finds new ways of studying and supporting her fellow freshmen.
Go Where the Students Are: FacebookBy using the social-media site for class, a professor sees online discussions that are both student-driven and multidirectional.
Twitter Meets PoloniusA theater instructor at <ORGANIZATION>George State University</ORGANIZATION> puts on "Hamlet 2.0."
ViewsCommunication and Counseling Are Keys to a Safer CampusEmpowered faculty members can play a vital role in preventing violence. Making sure they can do so more effectively is among colleges' greatest challenges.
Self-Sabotage in the Academic CareerFifteen ways in which faculty members harm their own futures, often without knowing it.
I'd Like to Thank the AcademyThe place where a writer's personality is revealed clearly, if unintentionally, is in the acknowledgments.
How a President Can Rescue—or Ruin—a College's ReputationChief executives' actions and behavior have a crucial impact, for better or worse, on how their institutions are perceived.
College Graduates Deserve Much More Than TranscriptsIf students can't present information about their actual learning, then that learning is devalued. And devalued things don't get the support they warrant.
On Hiring: Dealing With the UnexpectedThe worst things often happen at the most inconvenient times in the job-search process, writes <PERSON>Gene C. Fant Jr</PERSON>.
On Hiring: Know Your Worth and Ask for ItA scientist offers advice on negotiating a higher nonacademic salary.
