As colleges scramble to offer so-called massive open online courses, or <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>'s, faculty members have found themselves struggling to keep up with those plans and to make sure their views are heard.
A dozen colleges, including <ORGANIZATION>Duke University</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>, announced partnerships with the MOOC-platform company <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON> in July, and 17 more signed up this month. In some of those cases, faculty members had little input in the fast-moving negotiations, which took place over the summer. Many professors are now asking questions about what free online courses mean for their institution's future.
Meanwhile, other universities are taking a slower road, and are involving faculty leaders more closely as they consider whether to pursue <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>'s.
<ORGANIZATION>Yale University</ORGANIZATION>, for instance, announced last week that a committee had been formed to consider the future of online courses, "given what is happening around the country," said <PERSON>Mary Miller</PERSON>, dean of <ORGANIZATION>Yale College</ORGANIZATION>. The committee's co-chairs, <PERSON>Paul Bloom</PERSON> and <PERSON>Craig M. Wright</PERSON>, declined to discuss it withThe Chronicle,saying by e-mail that they did not yet have "anything substantive to say about these issues" because the panel had been formed so recently.
The <ORGANIZATION>University of Illinois</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Urbana-Champaign</ORGANIZATION> is an example of a campus that moved swiftly. As soon as <PERSON>Phyllis M. Wise</PERSON>, the university's chancellor, heard about <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON> from other administrators who had signed on, she wanted to follow suit. She asked the executive committee of the university's Academic Senate for a recommendation on whether to work toward a Coursera deal, and a faculty task force quickly issued a report giving a green light for such a partnership.
The task force devised a list of questions about how a Coursera partnership would work, said <PERSON>Nicholas C. Burbules</PERSON>, a former chair of the Academic <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> and a professor of educational-policy studies. For example, how would potential revenues from <LOCATION>Coursera</LOCATION> be divided within the university, and how would faculty members be compensated for teaching Coursera courses?
"I don't think anyone knows exactly where this is going," Mr. <PERSON>Burbules</PERSON> said. "We're on a very fast train right now, and we're jumping on board and seeing where it ends up."
'Continued Surprise'At anAcademic <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> meetingthis month, several faculty members voiced concern over the quick decision to team up with <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON> without consulting the full <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>.
"I'd like to express some continued surprise that the initiative got as far as we've heard today with the <ORGANIZATION>Academic Senate</ORGANIZATION> as a body not having discussed its implications so far," said <PERSON>Kathryn J. Oberdeck</PERSON>, an associate professor of history. "I'd like to have some idea of what plans are going forward for consultation regarding the implications of Coursera for shared-governance issues, and why there haven't been efforts to engage Academic <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> members in the discussions leading up to a partnership with such broad implications for education at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Illinois</ORGANIZATION>."
Ms. <PERSON>Wise</PERSON> said at the meeting that striking a deal at the same time as institutions like <ORGANIZATION>Caltech</ORGANIZATION> would give a greater boost to the university's recognition. "I believe these are the kinds of universities we want to be associated with—I pushed being in this cohort more than anyone else," she said.
Like the <ORGANIZATION>University of Illinois</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Urbana-Champaign</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Rice University</ORGANIZATION> signed a deal with <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON> over the summer. An ad hoc faculty group on online education formed within a week of the deal's announcement in order to recommend how <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>'s would work, said <PERSON>Peter C. Caldwell</PERSON>, a history professor at <PERSON>Rice</PERSON> and speaker of the Faculty Senate.
"A bunch of issues are going to hit us—we have a number of professors doing things related to online education across the university, with our own little modules here and there," he said. "We need to ask hard questions about how that works with what the university is doing." Mr. <PERSON>Caldwell</PERSON> said the university had felt pressure to follow the lead of universities like <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>, which was one of the first to offer <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>'s, but did take the time to discuss whether to work with <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON>. The decision "wasn't a leap," he said.
At many colleges, the faculty itself is divided over whether to embrace <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>'s. "You have a division between some faculty members who are very excited about the potential of technology and really running with this, and people who are just trying to explore it" more cautiously, said <PERSON>Mark F. Smith</PERSON>, a senior higher-education policy analyst at the <ORGANIZATION>National Education Association</ORGANIZATION>.
The U. of <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>ExampleThe University of Virginia</ORGANIZATION> board's decision to dismiss <PERSON>Teresa A. Sullivan</PERSON> as president in June illustrated the pressure on universities to strike MOOC deals quickly to keep up with peer institutions, said <PERSON>Martin D. Snyder</PERSON>, senior associate general secretary and director of the department of external relations for the <ORGANIZATION>American Association of University Professors</ORGANIZATION>.
"She was perceived to not be on the cutting edge and going where <LOCATION>Stanford</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> were going," he said of Ms. <PERSON>Sullivan</PERSON>, who was later reinstated as president. "There's a lot of pressure from boards and politicians, and some overlap between those two, particularly at public universities, to do that."
But even faculty members at <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> haven't had much formal discussion of the future of <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>'s. The free online courses will be one of the first topics the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>Academic Council</ORGANIZATION> will tackle this fall, said <PERSON>Raymond E. Levitt</PERSON>, a professor of civil engineering and chair of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>. He said he expects the faculty to "weigh in very strongly" on the issue.
<ORGANIZATION>Purdue University</ORGANIZATION>'s administration is among those that are taking a more-cautious route as the campus awaits a new president, Gov. <PERSON>Mitch Daniels</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, who will take office in January 2013.
The Republican governor has expressed interest in <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>'s, but the campus has not solidified its plans, said <PERSON>Michael Eddy</PERSON>, assistant dean for administration and planning at the <ORGANIZATION>Purdue</ORGANIZATION> Extended Campus.
<PERSON>J. Paul Robinson</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Purdue's University Senate</ORGANIZATION> and a professor of biomedical engineering, said faculty members preferred to be cautious before signing a deal with a company that offers <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>'s. "We know that leading institutions want to be seen at the leading edge of everything, but it's very unclear to me and many other faculty how this is going to translate into something valuable and useful," he said. "There's very little evidence that what they're doing is delivering quality learning."
Some administrators are not interested in jumping onto the MOOC bandwagon at all. On August 27, the <ORGANIZATION>University of Southern California</ORGANIZATION>'s president, <PERSON>C.L. Max Nikias</PERSON>, outlined the university's goals for online education in amessage to the campus.It noted that <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>'s were off the table.
"Other universities are increasingly offering online courses for free, with scant concern for whether enrollees ever complete a course," he wrote. "Our goal, by contrast, is to ensure that the educational experience is reserved for only those students with the requisite interest and ability to meet our faculty's high expectations." He added that Southern Cal "does not intend to join the growing ranks of institutions that seek to franchise undergraduate education through the Internet or through smaller satellite campuses abroad."
The university hopes to continue expanding its online graduate programs instead of focusing on <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>'s, said <PERSON>Patricia Riley</PERSON>, president of the university's <ORGANIZATION>Academic Senate</ORGANIZATION> and a professor at the <ORGANIZATION>Annenberg School for Communication</ORGANIZATION> and Journalism. "It was a fire-starter at some places," she said, "and it just didn't have a reaction at a place with such a strong online presence."
<PERSON>Alisha Azevedo</PERSON>