<ORGANIZATION>Antioch University</ORGANIZATION> announced on Monday that it had reached an agreement with the <LOCATION>Silicon Valley</LOCATION> start-up company <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON> to offer students college credit forMOOCÕs,the free online courses that have recently captured the attention of elite universities across the country. In anews release,the university, which has five campuses in four states, said its <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> location would offer the Coursera courses Òfor less than the per-course cost of tuition and fees at either of the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> public four-year university systems.Ó The <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> campus created a pilot program this fall in which its students could enroll in two Coursera courses created by the <ORGANIZATION>University of Pennsylvania</ORGANIZATION>; three additional courses will be offered this winter, and the university hopes to introduce an expanded program nationwide next year.
Filed under:<PERSON>TechnologyNick DeSantis</PERSON>