The Bill andamp; <ORGANIZATION>Melinda Gates Foundation</ORGANIZATION> on Wednesdayannouncedthat it had awarded $5.4-million in new grants to support 13 models of personalized technologies for improving college readiness and completion. Six grants will support postsecondary-degree programs. The winners include the <ORGANIZATION>University System of Georgia’s Board of Regents</ORGANIZATION>, the start-up companyAltius Education,and the <ORGANIZATION>University of Washington</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> will work withCoursera,a high-profile provider of online courses known asMOOC’s,to build a program for students who have earned some college credits but need to complete their degrees online, according to a news release.
Filed under:<PERSON>TechnologyNick DeSantis</PERSON>