NewsThe Dissertation Can No Longer Be Defended3 Ph.D.'s <ORGANIZATION>Doing Digital</ORGANIZATION> DissertationsInformation technology contributes to studies of prison newspapers, frontier post offices, and medieval fortresses.
Great Possibilities, Thwarted HopesAmerican colleges seek to build campuses, partnerships, and research opportunities in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, but red tape, poor facilities, and other problems keep getting in the way.
Americans Value Higher Education but Question Its Quality, National Survey FindsThey also worry about cost and favor making it easier for working adults to earn degrees, including the awarding of credit for prior learning.
Tough Times Push More Small Colleges to Join ForcesWorking together can help save money and provide more options to students, but colleges are still concerned about preserving their identities.
<ORGANIZATION>Colleges Ask Education Dept.</ORGANIZATION> to Clarify Rules on Competency and CreditPrograms that award credit for prior learning have been around for a while, but they haven't been using federal student aid. That may be about to change.
Digital Devices Invade Campus, and Networks Feel the StrainOne hundred students in the library with their smartphones and iPads can mean more than 200 bandwidth-guzzling Wi-Fi connections.
Flap Over Study Linking Poverty to Biology Exposes Gulfs Among DisciplinesA study by two economists that used genetic diversity as a proxy for ethnic and cultural diversity has drawn fierce rebuttals from anthropologists and geneticists.
Common Application Adopts New Essay Prompts and a Longer Word CountThe changes seek to offer applicants flexibility while encouraging them to focus on what they want others to know about themselves.
Work-Force Demand for STEM Students Spurs Efforts at Community CollegesAs concerns grow over work-force shortages in science, technology, engineering, and math fields, the colleges ready students for jobs or more education.
College Presidents and Education Secretary Push for Stricter Gun ControlOfficials at the <ORGANIZATION>National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities</ORGANIZATION>' annual meeting spoke out in favor of "common sense" gun-reform legislation.
<ORGANIZATION>American Council on Education Recommends</ORGANIZATION> 5 MOOCs for CreditApproval of the Coursera-provided classses could be a major step toward bridging the gap between massive open online courses and traditional higher education.
<ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION> and Coursera Try to Recover From MOOC StumbleWhen <PERSON>Fatimah Wirth</PERSON> decided to teach a massive open online course about how to run a virtual classroom successfully, she did not expect it to turn into a case study for the...
Bridge Program Offers Another Chance to Students Who Have <ORGANIZATION>FounderedLandmark College</ORGANIZATION>'s Bridge Semester is designed to help learning-disabled students get back on track at the colleges they previously attended.
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> Is Urged to Rule on <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> Affirmative-Action CaseSupporters of the state's ban on race-conscious college admissions are challenging an appeals court's ruling that found the ban to be unconstitutional.
Researcher Is Lauded for Discovering How Students Spend Their TimeGeorge <PERSON>D. Kuh</PERSON>, who developed an oft-used and sometimes-criticized study of student engagement, was honored by alumni at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Pennsylvania</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>NSF</ORGANIZATION>'s Director Is Leaving to Become Head of <PERSON>Carnegie Mellon U.Subra Suresh</PERSON>, who has led the federal agency since late 2010, says the unexpected offer from <PERSON>Carnegie Mellon</PERSON> was an opportunity he could not turn down.
Transitions: Chief Economist at <ORGANIZATION>Regulatory Agency Joins MIT</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Xavier U.</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> Hires Its First <PERSON>ProvostAndrei Kirilenko</PERSON> is now a professor of the practice of finance at <ORGANIZATION>MIT</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Sloan School of Management</ORGANIZATION>. Read about that and other job-related news.
Slide Show: <ORGANIZATION>Faces of Research</ORGANIZATION>, Faces of ResistanceGlimpses of life in academe from around the world.
The Chronicle ReviewHow Much  Do You Pay for College?Students are talking more openly about their socioeconomic status. The rest of us should, too.
Better Sound Than SafeIn debating gun policies, we must consider not just our vulnerability but also our humanity.
The Quest for Permanent NoveltyArtists have created some of their most powerful works by exploring our yearning for ever-fresh sensation.
Why Narnia?Strange, lovely, and symbolically untidy, <PERSON>C.S. Lewis</PERSON>’s fictional kingdom remains a narrative tonic for our spiritual renewal.
Teaching Ethics in a Dark WorldAn ethicist is painfully reminded of demagoguery’s brute power. Is that a lesson he should share with his idealistic students?
A Leviathan Task of BiographyMore than a decade after the publication of his career-defining <ORGANIZATION>Melville</ORGANIZATION> volumes, <PERSON>Hershel Parker</PERSON> strikes back at his critics in a genre-bending new work.
ViewsEnough With the Talk. Let's Start Fixing It.Faculty members and administrators need to get together and start testing solutions to make higher education work for students.
The Reality of Writing a Good Book ProposalOnce the crazy submissions are shooed away, publishers are left with a bunch of equally viable candidates.
Stop the Courts From Weakening Student <ORGANIZATION>JournalismA Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> ruling in a 1988 case involving children is now being applied to college and graduate-school students.
On Being A Rookie ChairEveryone assumes my life is now extraordinarily difficult and stressful. Should I let them?
College Presidents: Bruised, Battered, and Loving ItThey can change the world: Who wouldn't want a job like that?
