<PERSON>John C. Mitchell</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION>’s new vice provost for online learning, will oversee its new MOOC program. He has16 coursesslated for the fall, a seed-grant program to encourage course development, ahandfulofplatforms,and no long-term plan. That is, no fixed long-term plan: In an interview withThe <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>,he tells <PERSON>Jordan Weissmann</PERSON> that flexibility will be key:
It remains to be seen what really works best. But I think we’re entering a period, and we’ve been in a period, of experimentation where we have the scientific method. You know, hypothesis: if we put video online, people will be happier. Then we’ll try that and see how it goes and we’ll try different ways of doing that. And it will vary by school.
The computer-science professor has also toldThe Chroniclethat in thinking about outcomes, he’ll be especially focused on the students who will be taking the courses:
If I could reduce the number of hours per year I spend at a large lecture and have more time that I spend at a cafe with small groups of students, that would be more fun for me, and on balance it’d probably be more fun for the students, and everybody would be happier.
Read more on <PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s:
‘There’s Something Very Exciting Going On Here’—<ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>’s new head of online learning explains his vision for how the Internet can remake college classrooms.
What’s Next in Online Learning? <ORGANIZATION>Stanford Names Mitchell</ORGANIZATION> to Lead the Way—How extensive the offerings are—for example, whether the courses are videotaped in their entirety and put online—is up to individual instructors.
What You Need to Know About <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s—Struggling to make sense of it all? What <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s are, which universities have them, and how the technology landscape in higher education is changing.
Filed under:Teaching,Technology,<PERSON>John Mitchell</PERSON>,MOOCs,<ORGANIZATION>Stanford UniversityXarissa Holdaway</ORGANIZATION>