NewsA Women's College Tries a TransformationFor Parents, Straight Answers on Paying for College Are Still Too Little, Too LateFamilies have more information than ever before, but no more clarity about the eventual cost of a diploma.
For-Profit Colleges Take a Step Back to RegroupThe sector's former "swagger" is gone, one expert says, since economic and reputation problems have damaged enrollments.
In a Volatile Economy, Colleges' Endowment Returns Fall FlatColleges should keep their portfolios diversified to survive the roller-coaster ride, say the leaders of <LOCATION>Nacubo</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Commonfund Institute</ORGANIZATION> about the results of their latest...
College and <ORGANIZATION>University Endowments</ORGANIZATION>, 2011-12Year-by-Year <ORGANIZATION>Comparison of College and University Endowments</ORGANIZATION>, 2007-12Explore the market values of hundreds of funds at institutions in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>.
Immigration-Reform Plans Offer a Path for StudentsPresident <PERSON>Obama</PERSON> and a bipartisan group of senators have announced proposals that would provide a route to citizenship.
<ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> Money for Student Assistance Lands in Many Pockets, Big Ten Document ShowsThe $75-million fund has helped athletes pay for utilities, health insurance, and emergency travel. Some of the money also ends up in institutional coffers.
Visiting Professorships: How Many Is Too Many?One historian didn't realize until too late that he was doomed to be a perpetual visitor. Others, however, still see the role as a steppingstone.
Hot Off the (Library) PressScholarly publishing by college libraries takes wildly different forms at different institutions. A new coalition is trying to make connections and share expertise.
The <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> Could Teach Colleges a Lot About Competition—and CooperationBy forming a "league" of member institutions that agree to share resources and admission practices, a paper says, colleges might better serve the public.
Head Count: 'More Than Narrow Measures'The author of a new paper calling for collaboration among colleges discusses his vision of an admissions “league.”
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Said to Have Wasted Billions in Duplicative Spending on Research GrantsAnalysis by <ORGANIZATION>Virginia Tech</ORGANIZATION> researchers identified at least 167 pairs of grants so similar that they appeared to be essentially the same project.
Buildings andamp; Grounds: What's the Payoff for the 'Country Club' College?Researchers at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Michigan</ORGANIZATION> at <PERSON>Ann Arbor</PERSON> found that some colleges might be better off spending money on amenities than on instruction.
<PERSON>Stanley Karnow</PERSON>, Journalist and Historian of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, Dies at 87Mr. <PERSON>Karnow</PERSON>'s popular book on <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> was set apart from those of many other historians by his knack for storytelling.
Dorm Residents at a <ORGANIZATION>Kentucky College</ORGANIZATION> Get Used to Seeing the Dean Next DoorDrawing on her training as an anthropologist, <PERSON>Barbara LoMonaco</PERSON> immersed herself in student life when she became <ORGANIZATION>Transylvania University</ORGANIZATION>'s dean of students.
Provost to Step Up to <ORGANIZATION>U. of Georgia Presidency</ORGANIZATION>; Former Astronaut to Lead Center at <ORGANIZATION>U. of HoustonJere W. Morehead</ORGANIZATION> is the sole finalist for the leadership position at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Georgia</ORGANIZATION>. Read about that and other job-related news.
For Making the Most of College, It's Still Location, Location, LocationThe importance of place in learning, and in the value of higher education, can't easily be replicated in online courses.
The Chronicle ReviewPower of SuggestionExperiments by social psychologists that showed the influence of unconscious cues over our behavior are now getting a skeptical second look.
A More Radical Online Revolution"Generative scholarship" spurs new questions, evidence, conclusions, and audiences. The Web could be a particularly fertile home for it.
<LOCATION>Academe</LOCATION>'s Still-Precarious FreedomProfessors' free-speech rights are no greater than everybody else's. But their special task in furthering democracy requires protections.
Written on the Classroom WallsWhen a crumbling humanities building was finally closed for renovation, its loyal denizens celebrated with indelible markers.
The Skinny on FatThe sociologist who wrote "What's Wrong With Fat?" is more interested in the question than in the answer.
CommentaryRequire Business 101 for Every StudentMost liberal-arts majors will end up working for organizations concerned with at least breaking even at the end of the day. Let's educate them accordingly.
The End Is Not Nigh for CollegesDoomsayers are predicting that MOOCs, for-profit colleges, or other forces will soon put many colleges out of business. Here's why they're wrong.
AdviceIn Search of a Good CritiqueIt's possible to get useful evaluations of your work, but you have to help the process along.
Life as a Job-Market CaptiveA Ph.D. in history is learning the rules of the game, and finding that search committees could do with a few lessons, too.
