The IU Online project will be seeded with an initial investment of $8-million over the next three years, and will include both traditional online classes and the potential development of <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s, or massive open online courses.
Source:<ORGANIZATION>IuIndiana University</ORGANIZATION> announces <ORGANIZATION>IU Online</ORGANIZATION>, a major new online education initiative FOR IMMEDIATE RELEASE Sept. 5, 2012 <LOCATION>BLOOMINGTON</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION> — <ORGANIZATION>Indiana University</ORGANIZATION> has announced IU Online — a major strategic investment in online education that will accelerate the development and delivery of quality online courses and programs at IU’s campuses statewide, address <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>’s economic and professional development needs, and extend the university’s global reach.
Read more at:newsinfo.iu.edu
Xarissa Holdaway