<PERSON>Coursera</PERSON> offers free, online courses to people around the world, but if you live in <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, company officials are urging you to log off or head for the border.
The state’s <ORGANIZATION>Office of Higher Education</ORGANIZATION> has informed the popular provider ofmassive open online courses,or <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s, that <LOCATION>Coursera</LOCATION> is unwelcome in the state because it never got permission to operate there. It’s unclear how the law could be enforced when the content is freely available on the Web, but <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON> updated its <ORGANIZATION>Terms of Service</ORGANIZATION> to includethe following caution:
Notice for <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> Users:
<PERSON>Coursera</PERSON> has been informed by the <ORGANIZATION>Minnesota Office of Higher Education</ORGANIZATION> that under <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> Statutes (136A.61 to 136A.71), a university cannot offer online courses to <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> residents unless the university has received authorization from the State of <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> to do so. If you are a resident of <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, you agree that either (1) you will not take courses on Coursera, or (2) for each class that you take, the majority of work you do for the class will be done from outside the State of <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Tricia Grimes</PERSON>, a policy analyst for the <ORGANIZATION>state’s Office of Higher Education</ORGANIZATION>, said letters had been sent to all postsecondary institutions known to be offering courses in <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>. She said she did not know specifically whether letters had been sent to other MOOC providers like edX and Udacity, and officials there did not immediately respond to questions fromThe Chronicle.
But Ms. <PERSON>Grimes</PERSON> said the law the letters refer to isn’t new. “This has been a longtime requirement in <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> (at least 20 years) and applies to online and brick-and-mortar postsecondary institutions that offer instruction to <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> residents as part of our overall responsibility to provide consumer protection for students,” she wrote in an e-mail.
<PERSON>Daphne Koller</PERSON>, a co-founder of <LOCATION>Coursera</LOCATION>, said she was surprised to receive the letter from <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> in July. “The law’s focus is on degree-granting programs as opposed to free, open courseware,” she said in an interview on Wednesday. “It’s not clear why they extended it to us.”
Ms. <PERSON>Koller</PERSON>, who is on leave from her position as a professor of computer science at <LOCATION>Stanford</LOCATION>, said she wasn’t aware of any other states with similar restrictions. “We’re providing  tremendous, high-quality education for free to students around the country,” she said. Most of the enrolled students, many of whom are in high school or brushing up on professional credentials, wouldn’t be signing up for traditional degree courses, so Coursera shouldn’t pose any threat to them, she added.
Referring to <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON>’s caution that Minnesotans who do enroll study outside the state, <PERSON>Robert Talbert</PERSON>, an associate professor of mathematics at <ORGANIZATION>Grand Valley State University</ORGANIZATION>, in <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, had a suggestion.
Writing inhis blogonThe Chronicle’s Web site, he said he sees “a strong potential for a cottage industry: Set up a chain of coffee shops with free Internet access and on-site tutors just across <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>’s borders for Minnesotans to cross over and take their <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s.”
andgt;andgt; What You Need to Know About <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s
This entry was posted inCompany Watch,<ORGANIZATION>Distance Education</ORGANIZATION>,Offbeat,Startups. Bookmark thepermalink.<PERSON>Katherine Mangan</PERSON>