NewsA College Degree Sorts Job Applicants, but Employers Wish It Meant <ORGANIZATION>MoreNational Association of Scholars</ORGANIZATION>, at 25, Shows Signs of AgeThe group that seeks to maintain traditionalism in higher learning struggles to attract members and money.
U. of <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> Is in Search of a <ORGANIZATION>Scholar of Conservative</ORGANIZATION> ThoughtThe visiting scholar's position, supported by private donations, was created in part to counter public perceptions of ideological bias at the flagship.
White House Delivers New Open-Access Policy That Has Activists CheeringThe <PERSON>Obama</PERSON> administration says federally financed research should be made freely available within 12 months of publication in a peer-reviewed journal.
<ORGANIZATION>NSF</ORGANIZATION> Anticipates Pushing Boundaries on Open-Access PlanThe science foundation is among the agencies that were asked to set policies on how long publishers can restrict access to federally sponsored research.
Getting Down to the Reality of a $10,000 Bachelor's DegreeWith a <ORGANIZATION>YouTube</ORGANIZATION> comment and a governor's challenge, the idea has grown into a kind of Rorschach test for how Americans view higher education.
In Helping Immigrant Students, Jesuit Colleges Hope to Lead the WayMore than two dozen of the colleges pledge to assist students who are in the country illegally, and three colleges issue a paper on what needs to be done.
To Foster Financial Literacy, Students Need More Than Information, Report SaysFor financial-literacy training at colleges to work, it must also tackle students' attitudes and behaviors, according to an analysis of survey results.
The Bandwith DivideA new kind of digital divide means that online courses might not be available for everyone.
Wired Campus: Online Courses Could Widen Achievement Gaps Among StudentsIn a study of students who took more classes online, those in underrepresented groups fell further behind than if they were taking face-to-face courses.
U. of <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> Expects Probation From Its AccreditorA review team has recommended probation, saying the institution lacks sufficient autonomy from its corporate owner. The company plans to appeal.
Adjunct Orientations Take Hold, With a Variety of ApproachesUnheard of in years past, formal introductory programs for part-timers are becoming more common.
Canceled Conference Revives Concerns About Academic Freedom in the Persian <ORGANIZATION>GulfThe London School of Economics</ORGANIZATION> has shut down an event in the <LOCATION>United Arab Emirates</LOCATION> over "restrictions imposed on the intellectual content."
High Debt Loads May Deter Men From Graduating, Research FindsWomen may tolerate student-loan debt more than men do because they have more to gain in earnings potential by completing a college degree.
Energy Makeovers for Labs Create Breathing Room in the Bottom LineChanges in ventilation systems have added up to big savings at campuses in <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>For-Profit Group Suggests Best Practices for Serving Military</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Veteran StudentsThe Association of Private Sector Colleges</ORGANIZATION> and Universities assembled a panel of experts to produce the guidelines, which are intended for all colleges.
<ORGANIZATION>Georgia State U. Scholar Leads Strengthened Oral-History GroupThe Oral History Association</ORGANIZATION>'s first-ever executive director, <PERSON>Clifford M. Kuhn</PERSON>, must lead it through the rocky terrain of legal challenges and digital advances.
A Dean Seeks Ways to Recruit Minority Scholars to Liberal-Arts CollegesShirley <PERSON>M. Collado</PERSON>, of <ORGANIZATION>Middlebury College</ORGANIZATION>, is one of the leaders of an effort to persuade certain doctoral students to consider teaching at small, rural colleges.
U. of <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> Names New President; <ORGANIZATION>Amherst College Hires Dean of Students From Gates FoundationThe</ORGANIZATION> university's next leader will be <PERSON>Robert J. Sternberg</PERSON>, provost at <ORGANIZATION>Oklahoma State University</ORGANIZATION>. Read about that and other job-related news.
Engineer Brought a Passion for Teaching to the Presidency of a <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> UniversityBeheruz <PERSON>N. Sethna</PERSON>, who is retiring as president of the <ORGANIZATION>University of West Georgia</ORGANIZATION>, wanted to raise the institution's status, and he did.
'Dr. Garbage' Studies Local Tribe Many Prefer to IgnoreThe tribe examined by an anthropologist at <ORGANIZATION>NYU</ORGANIZATION> works in plain sight in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>, with lingo, rules, and customs all its own.
The Chronicle ReviewFixing Financial AidFor 40 years, federal money has sustained higher education while enabling its worst tendencies. That's about to change.
Synthetic Biology Comes Down to <PERSON>EarthJim Collins</PERSON> was there when the promise of engineered life generated waves of press. It's quieted down since then, and that's not all bad.
The Real Digital Change AgentMOOCs get the marquee billing. But open access has far greater potential to transform society, and to save colleges money in the process.
Fear and the Legacy of the New DealThe program was forged under the distinctive political pressures of its anxious times, but its imperfections continue to influence our own era.
Comedy ClubWhich do you think is harder: getting tenure or getting into the Friars Club?
In Pursuit of the Impossible EquationA new book explores the challenges of reducing the computationally confounding to the conceivably calculable.
ViewsAs Colleges Evolve, So Must Their PresidentsAcademe is in a period of profound change, and a new generation of leaders will have to change with it.
Let's Help Computer-Science Students Crack the CodeSuccessful professional programmers grab code from the Web, work in teams, and critique one another. Our students should be doing the same.
Avoiding Bad Advice From Your ColleaguesTips on how to ignore, reject, or only pretend to follow terrible guidance.
The Bittersweet Task of Running a Grant ProgramFrom drafting the call for proposals to announcing the results, here's what you need to know.
Caps on Data Use Dim Online Learning's Bright FutureEducators believe new online courses could make higher education more available and affordable for all. But what about people who can't afford the Internet?
