<PERSON>Tyler Cowen</PERSON> and <PERSON>Alex Tabarrok</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>George Mason University</ORGANIZATION> economists who write the economics blog Marginal Revolution, on Wednesday announced that they were introducing a platform for free online courses dubbed “MRUniversity.” Mr. <PERSON>Cowendescribed</PERSON> the effortas a “flexible learning module” that can be used to create one of the massive open online courses, or <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s, that have lately been ahot topicin higher-education circles.
“We think education should be better, cheaper, and easier to access,” Mr. <PERSON>Cowen</PERSON> wrote. “So we decided to take matters into our own hands and create a new online-education platform toward those ends. We have decided to do more to communicate our personal vision of economics to you and to the broader world.”
The courses will be free and will feature quizzes, tests, and videos that average roughly five minutes in length. The first course, ondevelopment economics,will begin in October. It’s not clear if the new effort will have any formal relationship with <PERSON>George Mason</PERSON>, though Mr. <PERSON>Cowen</PERSON> noted that MRUniversity’s international reach will be “building upon the global emphasis” of the professors’ home institution.
Filed under:Teaching,Technology,Massive Open Online CoursesNick DeSantis