To the Editor:
Recently, a student of ours shared with us the unsolicited contact by a <PERSON>Vashisth Seth</PERSON>, who claimed to hold a doctorate and professor designation at a reputable university in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. He claims he will “help students of Management, who are taking online courses from Universities like <ORGANIZATION>University of Phoenix</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Lawrence Technical University</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>University of Waterloo</ORGANIZATION>, etc.”
“I help students with their Assignments, Case Studies, and some of them even want me to take care of their Discussion Forums through out week, as they were busy with their jobs,” he says. “I had an experience of over 5 years and loves helping students globally. I am working as a Head of Department (Management) at a University.”
We are investigating the claims he is making in this statement above. A linked in profile for this individual suggests he may be affiliated with <ORGANIZATION>Uttar Pradesh Technical University</ORGANIZATION>, in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
This is a problem for all of us to keep in mind. It is bad enough to worry about it from an online-degree-program perspective, but what about <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s? If someday <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s are accepted at institutions for credit towards degrees, on-ground and online, it could topple higher education as we know it and set the stage for more government and regional oversight—something none of us will ever want to see happen.
<PERSON>Richard G. BushDirectoreLearning ServicesLawrence Technological UniversitySouthfield</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mich</LOCATION>.
This entry was posted inUncategorized. Bookmark thepermalink.