Major Players in the MOOC Universe
CourseraKhan AcademyUdacityedXThis for-profit MOOC founded by <PERSON>Andrew Ng</PERSON> and <PERSON>Daphne Koller</PERSON> has teamed up with 62 colleges (and counting) for its classes. The company is experimenting with a career service that makes money by connecting employers to its students, and attracted $22-million in venture capital in its first year.
<PERSON>Salman Khan</PERSON> made waves when he quit his job as a hedge-fund analyst to record short video lectures on everything from embryonic stem cells to—you guessed it—hedge funds and venture capital.
This for-profit MOOC, started by the <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> professor <PERSON>Sebastian Thrun</PERSON>, works with individual professors to offer courses. By March 2013, <ORGANIZATION>Udacity</ORGANIZATION> had raised more than $21-million in venture capital.
<ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>MIT</ORGANIZATION> put up the original $60-million to start this nonprofit MOOC. So far, students can take classes only from <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>MIT</ORGANIZATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>UC Berkeley</ORGANIZATION>, but classes from nine more universities are coming soon.
Companies to watch:MOOC2Degree:This upstart’s main selling point is real, transferable credit, as long as students can get admitted to the college, that is. At least nine colleges are planning to participate, and <PERSON>Jeb Bush</PERSON>, the former <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> governor, has spoken favorably of the venture.
Canvas Network:Network's owner, Instructure, is one of Blackboard’s biggest competitors. <PERSON>David Wiley</PERSON>, an early MOOC teacher and promoter, has gotten behind the project, and more than a dozen colleges have signed up. The company has received more than $9-million in investments.
CourseSites:Blackboard is only just starting to compete in the MOOC universe with its CourseSite platform. So far, only a handful of universities have tested it out.
Udemy:Professors, authors, professionals, and celebrities create and sell courses about pretty much anything at <LOCATION>Udemy</LOCATION>, which has raised more than $16-million in venture capital.
Thinkful:One of the billionaire <PERSON>Peter Thiel</PERSON>’s 20 Under 20 fellows started this career-development-oriented company, into which Mr. <PERSON>Thiel</PERSON> has invested $1-million.
Graphic by <PERSON>XARISSA HOLDAWAY</PERSON>; illustration by <PERSON>NIGEL HAWTIN</PERSON>
Sources: THE CHRONICLE OF HIGHER EDUCATION, FINANCIAL TIMES, NATIONAL SCIENCE FOUNDATION, THE <LOCATION>NEW YORK</LOCATION> TIMES, TECHCRUNCH, <ORGANIZATION>CNN</ORGANIZATION>, WIRED, AND <ORGANIZATION>YAHOO</ORGANIZATION> FINANCE
