From the <ORGANIZATION>John Hope Franklin Humanities Institute</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Duke University</ORGANIZATION> comesthis announcementof an event this afternoon from 1:30-3:00pm Eastern time, featuring ProfHacker’s own <PERSON>Adeline Koh</PERSON>:
Please join us for an event on MOOCs (Massively Open Online Courses) and play in education withPete <PERSON>Rorabaugh</PERSON>(English, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> State University;@allistelling) andJesse <PERSON>Stommel</PERSON>(English andamp; <ORGANIZATION>Digital Humanities</ORGANIZATION>, Marylhurst University;@jessifer), editors of the journalHybrid Pedagogy.<PERSON>Adeline Koh</PERSON>(Literature, <ORGANIZATION>Richard Stockton College</ORGANIZATION> andamp; 2012-13 Humanities Writ Large Visiting Faculty Fellow) will moderate.
We’ll be livestreaming the event on theFHI Youtube channel, and everyone is encouraged to watch and take part via the Twitterstream: hashtag#dukehp.
For more information,read the entire announcement.
Update at 5:00pmHere is the video from today’s event:
[Creative Commons-licensed image fromLight Cue 23]
This entry was posted inTeachingand taggedcollaboration,moocs,play. Bookmark thepermalink.<PERSON>George Williams</PERSON>