NewsBitter Fruit of Arab Spring: Islamic Fundamentalists Challenge AcademeThe Creativity CureA growing appreciation of the practical and societal value of creative thinking has prompted colleges to make it compulsory.
Everyone Wants to Fix Student AidBut do they even understand it? Recipients of grants from the Bill andamp; <ORGANIZATION>Melinda Gates Foundation</ORGANIZATION>'s "Reimagining Aid" program propose varied strategies.
Handicapping the 'Reimagining Aid' RecommendationsMany of the proposals financed by the Gates foundation would save taxpayers and students money, but are they politically viable? The Chronicle offers its forecast.
A Faculty Refuge Becomes an Accreditor's TargetAt the <ORGANIZATION>City College</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, the administration is lean, and faculty members have a lot of say. Now that ethos is threatening its future.
Coalition Steps Up to Advocate for Needy Students—and Their CollegesSmaller private colleges with many <PERSON>Pell Grant-eligible</PERSON> students want more help for those students and better measures of what the institutions are achieving.
HeadCount: Going to See 'Admission' With an Admissions OfficerA real-life admissions director reflects on the fictional rendering of higher education’s gatekeepers in <PERSON>Tina Fey</PERSON>’s new movie.
Education Advocacy Group Objects to Government's Demand for Its E-mailsInvestigators have subpoenaed the records to help determine if a key former <ORGANIZATION>Education Department</ORGANIZATION> official, <PERSON>Robert Shireman</PERSON>, broke federal ethics laws.
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> Lawmakers Accuse Regents of Vendetta Against Flagship's PresidentDuplicative probes are part of an effort by the board to oust <PERSON>William Powers</PERSON>, his supporters maintain.
<PERSON>Brown</PERSON> U. Program Helps Minority Science Ph.D.'s to ThriveThe program has enabled the university to attract more black and Hispanic graduate students, and has helped them succeed.
<ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> to Review <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s Ban on Race-Conscious AdmissionsThe case is the second before the court involving affirmative action in higher education. The other challenges a race-conscious admissions policy in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
Behind <ORGANIZATION>Rollins College</ORGANIZATION> Chief's Battle, a Broader Liberal-Arts DebateA vote of no confidence in the president highlights a simmering controversy about the future of the liberal arts in a competitive higher-education marketplace.
New Legal Mandate in Hand, Data-Sharing Advocates Tackle Cultural ObstaclesMore than 200 representatives of universities, companies, and government agencies gathered in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> for the first meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>Research Data Alliance</ORGANIZATION>.
Independent Study-Abroad Companies to Get Permits for Programs in CubaThe <PERSON>Obama</PERSON> administration lifted a ban on educational travel to <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> two years ago but had not given licenses for study-abroad groups.
Lighter Teaching Loads Contribute to Rising College Costs, Report SaysA decline in full-time professors' teaching loads accounted for more than half of the tuition increase seen over a seven-year period, an analysis found.
Wired Campus: Journal's Editorial Board Resigns in Protest of Publisher's Policy Toward AuthorsThe editor of the “Journal of Library Administration” says he and the board felt that under the publisher’s terms, the “math just didn’t add up” for authors.
Wired Campus: For Libraries, MOOCs Bring Uncertainty and OpportunityAcademic librarians discuss what roles they might play in the massive online phenomenon.
<PERSON>Chinua Achebe</PERSON>, Author and Professor of Africana Studies at <LOCATION>Brown U.</LOCATION>, Died at 82The Nigerian-born author wrote the novel "Things Fall Apart," widely read in college classrooms around the world. Read about his career and about other deaths in academe.
President Emerita of <ORGANIZATION>Barnard College</ORGANIZATION> to Lead <PERSON>Teagle FoundationBefore</PERSON> she became a candidate, <PERSON>Judith R. Shapiro</PERSON> was on the search committee to find a new leader for the foundation, which supports education in the liberal arts.
Student Filmmaker Turns 'Blame the (Rape) Victim' Ethos Into a Positive VideoA student at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Oregon</ORGANIZATION> talks about her provocative video inspired by a rape conviction in <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>.
Former Lieutenant Governor to <ORGANIZATION>Lead Babson College</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Columbia U. Names New Engineering</ORGANIZATION> <PERSON>DeanKerry Healey</PERSON>, who served under <PERSON>Mitt Romney</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, will be the business college's first female leader. Read about that and other job-related news.
The Chronicle ReviewThe Case for RevengeWithout the debt-canceling, equalizing, restorative dimensions of revenge, faith in humankind is lost and the world makes less sense.
Hacking the WorldGabriella <PERSON>Coleman</PERSON> is an anthropologist in the midst of a geek insurgency.
The Paradox of IndividualismSmall government and liberty might not actually be as compatible as some think.
<PERSON>Willa Cather</PERSON> in Her Own Words, at LastHer literary estate's release of her letters sheds light on a writer who protected her privacy and provides vast opportunity for scholarship.
Ivory Tower Fiber FreakIt was a new, unsupported field for one professor. Her passion for the subject was crucial. But so was a strategic, considered approach.
The Human Art of Way-FindingA physicist composes an ode to the lost skills of navigation.
ViewsWhy Republicans and Academics Need Each OtherColleges should see political diversification as a matter of self-preservation as well as a genuine public good.
Giving Students a Voice in the College BudgetAt <ORGANIZATION>Northwestern University</ORGANIZATION>, they have an active, official role in deciding how the money is spent. Here's how it works.
A Simple Fix for the <ORGANIZATION>Broken College</ORGANIZATION> ScorecardWith one simple change, the government could make the guide more relevant to students while also eliminating incentives for colleges to game the system.
The Etiquette of Accepting a Job OfferHow to get to "yes" efficiently and amicably.
