<ORGANIZATION>NewsPepperdine U.</ORGANIZATION>'s President Faces One Problem He Can't SolveHigh-Profile Plagiarism Prompts Soul-Searching in German UniversitiesThe esteemed academic home of <LOCATION>Humboldt</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Hegel</PERSON> struggles to root out scholarly fraud
Threat of Sequester Has Researchers, Aid Officers ScramblingUnless <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> acts, thousands of scientists will lose their jobs and thousands of students will lose their financial aid.
Uncle <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>'s Gift to Military ChildrenFederal education benefits and related programs make college possible not only for veterans but for military families, too.
The Jury Is Out on <ORGANIZATION>New College</ORGANIZATION> ScorecardThe Chronicleasked five higher-education and student-aid experts to weigh in on the White House's new tool for families to use to compare colleges.
Pay Increase for Top Administrators Barely Outpaces InflationTheir median base pay rose by 2.3 percent last year, an improvement over the previous year, an annual survey found.
High-School Dropouts Get a <ORGANIZATION>Taste of College</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> AcademyThe program has helped an impoverished school district graduate more than 1,000 off-track students since 2007.
For Adviser to Historically Black Colleges, Good Governance Is <PERSON>KeyJohn W. Garland</PERSON> is the first president in residence of the <ORGANIZATION>Thurgood Marshall College Fund</ORGANIZATION>. He hopes to help member colleges harness their "transformative power."
<ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION> Theologian Is Drawn to Lead a Divinity School With a Progressive <PERSON>EdgeEmilie M. Townes</PERSON> at first didn't want the pressure of being dean at <ORGANIZATION>Vanderbilt Divinity School</ORGANIZATION>. But she was taken by what it stood for.
Transitions: President of <LOCATION>Caltech</LOCATION> to Lead Saudi University; Math Professor to Take Helm at Southwestern U.Jean-Lou Chameau will become the second president of <ORGANIZATION>King Abdullah University of Science and Technology</ORGANIZATION>. Read about that and other job-related news.
How EdX Plans to Earn, and Share, Revenue From Free Online CoursesThe nonprofit is giving university partners two options for sharing in the money its MOOCs bring in. But first, they have to bring it in.
Emory Faculty Seek More Contrition From Their PresidentThe president has apologized for using a racially sensitive episode in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> history to make a point, but critics say the way he apologized was confusing.
Gifts to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Colleges Rose 2.3% in 2012, Narrowly Outpacing InflationThe growth was well below 2011's 8.2-percent rise and, when adjusted for inflation, came to an increase of just 0.2 percent, says the Council for Aid to Education.
Planned Military Research at <ORGANIZATION>Yale Medical School Draws CriticismCritics</ORGANIZATION> say the center would train interrogators using immigrants as subjects. The psychiatrist who would lead the project says its purpose is misunderstood.
Ranking Colleges by 'Desirability'A new paper proposes a model based on students’ “revealed preferences”: the colleges they choose from among all those that accept them.
In Rare Second Act, Chapel Hill Chancellor Will Be Provost at <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> U.H. <PERSON>Holden Thorp</PERSON> will take an unusual step down the administrative ladder in moving from <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>.
The Chronicle ReviewIn <PERSON>Ian Morris</PERSON>'s Big History, the Future Looms LargeHis latest book analyzed 15,000 years of data to explain why the West is dominant. Now the intelligence community wants to know what will happen next.
A Battered Bag of MemoriesYears ago, a writer lost a satchel full of student humiliation. Then one night a stranger calls …
Closer to God: Religion and the American Space ProgramAstronauts' experiences, theologians' pronouncements, and churches in space-enclave communities all factor in to a new cultural history.
The Myths Behind the Age of MartyrsThe documentary record does not support the ideologically charged narrative of early Christian martyrdom.
<PERSON>Aaron Swartz</PERSON> Was RightThe current academic publishing system is prettied-up extortion. He defied it, and the rest of us should too.
ViewsGive <ORGANIZATION>AP Credit Where Credit Is DueColleges</ORGANIZATION> have the right to choose which high-school-level work to credit. But they should think about what their decisions mean for high schoolers.
Ph.D. Student in the Sciences? Time to Get RealThe number of Ph.D.'s produced outweighs the number of jobs for them in academe. Departments should tell students more about alternative careers.
A Liberal-Arts Home for the MilitaryIf we are to remain a <ORGANIZATION>democratic republic</ORGANIZATION>, we must reacquaint academic <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> with the military.
We're Not a Hierarchy, We're an EcosystemGraduate programs should ignore the rankings and find their niche.
Bloopers to Avoid in Job InterviewsHere are 12 things you should never say or do as a job candidate.
