More than 900,000 students have signed up for the so-called massively open online courses offered by major universities through <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON>. The upstart company, which began operating earlier this year, held its first official meet-up on Saturday, in a park near its headquarters in <LOCATION>Mountain View</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. Some 650 students attended.The Chronicleasked a sample of students at the event to explain their motivation for working through the courses, which carry no official credit. |Related Story
<PERSON>Kimberly Spillman</PERSON>
38, <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>
"I was socializing with students way more than I ever had. We'd hang out in the pub."
This audio feature is not available.<PERSON>Charles Clark59</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>"I could have bought a book, but I think having a fixed deadline has a lot of value."This audio feature is not available.Yichuan Cao23, <LOCATION>Mountain View</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>"I probably wouldn't put that on my resumé, but I would say I know how to do it."This audio feature is not available.<PERSON>Amy Tam42</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Sunnyvale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>"What I am hoping for is, if there are questions, the local study group will help."This audio feature is not available.Interviews: <PERSON>Jeffrey R. Young</PERSON>; Photos: <PERSON>Noah Berger</PERSON>; Design: <PERSON>Brock Read</PERSON>