<PERSON>Michael Sandel</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> government professor, sent the following statement to aChroniclereporter in response to anopen letterfrom <ORGANIZATION>San Jose State University</ORGANIZATION>'s philosophy department suggesting that professors who develop MOOCs are complicit in how public universities might use them.(See arelated article.)
<PERSON>Sandel</PERSON> Response to Chronicle of Higher Ed (PDF)<PERSON>Sandel</PERSON> Response to Chronicle of Higher Ed (Text)