NewsStudents Get Savvier About Textbook Buying, When They Buy at AllDon't Call Them TextbooksPublishers' latest digital products may deserve a category of their own.
For Many Students, Print Is Still KingThey still want real books, publishers and professors say, even as digital products proliferate.
Can Textbooks Ever Really Be Free?Many agree that making books free for college students is a good idea. But nobody's found a great way to do it.
Required Texts? Really?Some students will go to great lengths to avoid shelling out for a new textbook.
Freshman Survey: This Year, Even More Focused on JobsA greater percentage of freshmen than ever before said a prospective career was a crucial reason to go to college, according to an annual survey by <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>'s Higher Education...
'Bill of Rights' Seeks to Protect Students' Interests as Online Learning ExpandsThe document's authors want to make sure that the rapid rise of MOOCs and other digital tools does not obscure traditional obligations to students.
The Document: 'A Bill of Rights and Principles for Learning in the Digital Age'In an <LOCATION>Israeli Desert</LOCATION>, a Modest Effort to Build an Environment for <ORGANIZATION>PeaceThe Arava Institute for Environmental Studies</ORGANIZATION> is a small place with big ambitions.
As Temperatures Keep Rising, 'Plan B' Gets a Harder LookSome scientists say we shouldn't try to geoengineer the earth's climate; others say we can't afford not to.
Challenges Ahead for the U. of <PERSON>CaliforniaMark Yudof</PERSON> is stepping down in August. His successor may face no less than a major rethinking of the breadth and scope of the 10-campus system.
Report Calls for Renewed Focus on Raising College-Completion RatesA yearlong effort by the <ORGANIZATION>National Commission on Higher Education Attainment</ORGANIZATION> identifies innovative repairs for colleges' leaky pipelines.
A Historian Bids Farewell to Her PastNell <PERSON>Irvin Painter</PERSON> wrote seven groundbreaking books about African-American history and taught at <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION> for 17 years. Now she's pursuing a different passion.
Expert in Diplomacy to Take On Task of Being a College's First ProvostPeter Uvin will assume the new role at <ORGANIZATION>Amherst College</ORGANIZATION>, and one of his responsibilities will be defining just what a provost at such a liberal-arts institution does.
Longtime Dean Sees Ever-Expanding Role for Nurses With Advanced DegreesColleen Conway-Welch, who is retiring from <ORGANIZATION>Vanderbilt's School of Nursing</ORGANIZATION>, predicts that nurses will soon take over much of the work of primary-care doctors.
U. of <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Get New Dean of Arts and Sciences</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Lorrie Moore</PERSON> to Move to VanderbiltThe new dean is <PERSON>Steven J. Fluharty</PERSON>, senior vice provost for research and a professor at Penn. Read about that and other job-related news.
A Rice U. Student Battles the Teaching of <PERSON>CreationismZack Kopplin</PERSON> started his fight in high school, after passage of the <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> Science Education Act.
U. of <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> Master's Student Becomes First 'Wikipedian in Residence' at Presidential <PERSON>LibraryMichael Barera</PERSON> parlayed his volunteer editing of <LOCATION>Wkipedia</LOCATION> into an internship.
<ORGANIZATION>Rocker/Academic Leads New Institute for Popular Music</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>U. of RochesterJohn Covach</ORGANIZATION>, the institute's founding director, has worked hard to give the study of popular music the same prestige as the study of classical music.
<PERSON>Steven Muller</PERSON>, Former President of <PERSON>Johns Hopkins</PERSON>, Dies at 85; Other DeathsSteven <PERSON>Muller</PERSON> led the university from 1972 to 1990, during which time he expanded its scope and raised hundreds of millions of dollars.
The Chronicle ReviewThe End of Feminism?New works on women lack the fire of <PERSON>Betty Friedan</PERSON>. They don't rage, they fizzle.
All Guns Are Not Created EqualThe writers of the Second Amendment didn't think so, and neither should we.
Anti-Judaism as a Critical TheoryHostility to <ORGANIZATION>Judaism</ORGANIZATION> is not just a product of extreme ideologies. It’s rooted in the power and politics of Western tradition.
When Beauty Is Not TruthPhysicists are drawn to elegant, symmetrical theories, and many have turned out to be true. But the gleam of the beautiful can blind scientists, a critic argues.
Remembrance of MLA Conventions PastAnother year, another paper, another interview suite. Until the last one.
Too Old to Rock and Roll?An ethnography of former rock fans explores how they've aged.
The Pre-Digital Art of Crafting NotesCommentaryWhat Are Low-Ranked Graduate Programs Good For?Too many Ph.D. programs are too focused on what's going on above them.
Don't Reform Graduate Education in a VacuumProposals to rethink the doctoral curriculum must involve Ph.D.'s who have left academe.
An Undisciplined Report on the Teaching of <ORGANIZATION>HistoryThe National Association of Scholars</ORGANIZATION>' take on current historiography does not contribute to an informed debate.
The Obsession With Social HistoryThe report's main arguments are largely true, says a historian who taught for 40 years at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION>.
College Rankings: a Guide to NowhereOrganizations that rank colleges need more-meaningful measures that show diversity, job placement, faculty membership in national academies, and student engagement.
AdviceWe Know You Can Read. So Can We.In which I sit through a conference panel and do not obtain enlightenment.
