The social-news site <LOCATION>Reddit</LOCATION> has slowly grown a spin-off ”university” where anyone can offer free courses, and two professors at <ORGANIZATION>University of South Florida’s Honors College</ORGANIZATION> are trying the system to turn courses they’re teaching this fall into Massive Open Online Courses, or <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s.
The instructors, <PERSON>Philip S. Bishop</PERSON>, a visiting assistant professor, and <PERSON>K. Edward Renner</PERSON>, an adjunct professor, are offering courses simultaneously in-person, to registered students, and online, to anyone who wants to join in.
The two professors say they have been trying to encourage the <ORGANIZATION>University of South Florida</ORGANIZATION> to create <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s for several years, but were frustrated by what they saw as the slow pace of academic administration that prevented them from moving forward.
When they finally received the go-ahead to put their courses online earlier this year, Mr. <PERSON>Bishop</PERSON> and Mr. <PERSON>Renner</PERSON> did not have the resources to establish a platform through the <ORGANIZATION>University of South Florida</ORGANIZATION> to deliver them. So they decided to try the site that has become known as the <ORGANIZATION>University of Reddit</ORGANIZATION>. That platform has no formal relationship with <LOCATION>Reddit</LOCATION> itself, but it uses the larger <LOCATION>Reddit</LOCATION> system informally. It was created two years ago by <PERSON>Anastas D. Stoyanovsky</PERSON>, and allows anyone to offer a course on any subject they choose.
The site offers Web space for instructors to post a syllabus and other course information. Students will also have access to a message board on <LOCATION>Reddit</LOCATION>, which will serve as a discussion board, allowing virtual and in-person students to interact for weekly assignments.
Both of the <LOCATION>South Florida</LOCATION> professors have written textbooks to accompany their courses, which will be available free from iTunes University.
Mr. <PERSON>Bishop</PERSON> is teaching a philosophy course called “Arts and Humanities: What Does It Mean to Live Well?” and Mr. <PERSON>Renner</PERSON> is leading “Forums for a Future,” which directly tackles some of challenges facing today’s students.
The platform has its drawbacks, the professors concede. “One of the downfalls of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Reddit</ORGANIZATION> is that I can’t track where the students are coming from, how much time they’re looking at the material,” Mr. <PERSON>Bishop</PERSON> said. The <ORGANIZATION>University of Reddit</ORGANIZATION> also lacks credibility. “The greatest difficulty is getting people to take it seriously,” Mr. <PERSON>Bishop</PERSON> said, noting that the site also offers a course on StarCraft, a popular video game.
Both professors feel, however,that running their courses on a freely available platform provides opportunities for their students on the campus as well as for those participating online. “What my students get is a global perspective on this material,” Mr. <PERSON>Bishop</PERSON> said. And the online students, he added, “are going to get the benefits of the honors students posting and creating content on the bulletin boards.”
Although the <ORGANIZATION>University of Reddit</ORGANIZATION> is the platform they’re using to get started, both professors envision creating their own platform through the <ORGANIZATION>University of South Florida</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Stuart H. Silverman</PERSON>, dean of the Honor’s College, says that he expects this type of program to continue after this semester.
This entry was posted inPublishing,Teaching. Bookmark thepermalink.<PERSON>Ben Pokross</PERSON>