Just days before his long-simmering conflict with professors came to a head last week at <ORGANIZATION>Rollins College</ORGANIZATION>, its president, <PERSON>Lewis M. Duncan</PERSON>, gave a sobering speech about the future of higher education.
Speaking at a March 15 faculty meeting, Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> appeared to cast online learning as a viable replacement for traditional liberal-arts institutions like <PERSON>Rollins</PERSON>, which serves about 3,200 students in Winter Park, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. Over the course of 49 PowerPoint slides, Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> cited dozens of news articles and opinion pieces about the need to radically disrupt the higher-education business model and about the promise of massive open online courses, or MOOCs.
"Even if the budget model could be maintained for another generation of students, we are experiencing a 'Copernican moment,'" one of Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON>'s slides said. "The college campus is no longer at the center of the education universe."
Six days after that presentation, faculty members in the <ORGANIZATION>College of Arts</ORGANIZATION> andamp; Sciences voted, 67 to 10, to expressno confidence in Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON>'s leadership.
The story behind the faculty vote reflects a broader debate about whether private liberal-arts colleges with relatively small endowments can maintain their character and mission while remaining competitive in an ever-more-crowded higher-education marketplace. <PERSON>Rollins</PERSON>'s residential undergraduate program remains its bread and butter, but Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> and the board have signaled that the college's growth will come from preprofessional programs for nontraditional students, in online and evening courses.
That is quite a shift for an institution that, just two decades ago, killed off its business major because it was perceived by some professors as anathema to the liberal arts. (A separate international-business major, created in the 1990s, was thought to be more palatable in part because it included foreign-language requirements.)
A 'Continuing Strain'To some professors at the March 15 meeting, and even those who only later viewed Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON>'s PowerPoint slides, the president's presentation sounded like a dreary surrender to market forces rather than a plan for preserving the intimacy of small classes and Socratic dialogue that many argue are central to the Rollins experience. To Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON>'s harshest critics, the speech sounded like high-minded cover for a series of unilateral administrative changes they say he has made in the college's structure and curriculum.
<PERSON>Jill C. Jones</PERSON>, president of the Arts andamp; Sciences faculty, said the vote "signals a desire to see a change in leadership."
"The first thing the faculty is really clear about is there is no communication, no collaboration, no buy-in, no attempt to win over the faculty to his vision for the college," said Ms. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, an English professor. "In fact, we are unclear about what his vision for the college is, and that makes a lot of decisions seem arbitrary and out of the blue."
Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> declined an interview request but did provide a written statement, and he responded to several questions by e-mail. In the statement, Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> said the no-confidence vote reflected a "continuing strain over the past several years" about faculty involvement in strategic decisions. He added, however, that he "must respectfully disagree" that professors have not been adequately consulted.
"I do believe change is inevitable, that decisions and actions frequently must be undertaken more quickly than the deliberative pace at which faculty bodies are inclined to act, that change evokes resistance, and that broad consensus for change is often unrealizable," Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> added.
Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON>, who earned a Ph.D. in space physics at <ORGANIZATION>Rice University</ORGANIZATION>, came to <PERSON>Rollins</PERSON> in 2004 from <ORGANIZATION>Dartmouth College</ORGANIZATION>, where he was dean of the College of Engineering. He is a vocal champion of the "applied liberal arts" ethos at <LOCATION>Rollins</LOCATION>, arguing that rocket scientists like himself are better at their jobs for having read a little Plato.
Quality ConcernsThe decision that really set off the <PERSON>Rollins</PERSON> faculty occurred in 2011, when the departments of communications, international business, and education were moved out of Arts andamp; Sciences to create a new College of Professional Studies.
"It was presented as something that was going to happen," Ms. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON> said. "There was no point in discussing."
That action prompted Arts andamp; Sciences faculty members to censure Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON>, and his critics say that he has only become less engaged with the faculty since then.
Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> does not dispute that before the new college's creation, administrators consulted principally with the three departments that would be moved, rather than with the full college. A 10-page unsigned memorandum—which the president provided toThe <PERSON>Chronicleand</PERSON> described as a thorough background of his version of the events of 2011—says the decision to create the new college was necessary because "small controlling groups of faculty" within Arts andamp; Sciences repeatedly opposed necessary curricular changes in communications, international business, and education.
That opposition, the memo continues, was particularly problematic for international-business professors, who said curricular changes were critical to a renewal of accreditation from AACSB International: the Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business.
The memo further states that professors in professional programs felt prejudice from other faculty members who "do not regard them as being from true liberal-arts disciplines." Leaders of Arts andamp; Sciences question the "legitimacy of business education," the memo states, and treat members of the education and communications faculties as "second-class citizens."
'The Game Here'Thomas <PERSON>D. Lairson</PERSON>, who holds appointments in both Arts andamp; Sciences and Professional Studies as a professor of political science and international business, said he initially defended Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> for taking the "regrettably necessary" step of creating a new college.
Mr. <PERSON>Lairson</PERSON> said he was dubious about "bad precedents," however, and believes faculty governance was again sidestepped in the recent decision to create a "plain Jane" undergraduate business major at <LOCATION>Rollins</LOCATION>. A new business department, in addition to the international-business department, will also be created.
"He believes we have to low-ball the quality of our programs to attract students," Mr. <PERSON>Lairson</PERSON> said of the president. "The game here is to attract students. We have to give them what they want."
And there's the rub. What Mr. <PERSON>Lairson</PERSON> describes as low-balling, Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> and his supporters would call being "student centered."
<PERSON>Debra K. Wellman</PERSON>, dean of the <ORGANIZATION>College of Professional Studies</ORGANIZATION> and a professor of education, said the undergraduate business major would meet the needs of students enrolled in <PERSON>Rollins</PERSON>'s evening program, known as <ORGANIZATION>Hamilton Holt School</ORGANIZATION>. The school, which has less-rigorous admissions standards and lower tuition, offers only a minor in business. Students who might have otherwise enrolled at <LOCATION>Holt</LOCATION>, Ms. <PERSON>Wellman</PERSON> said, choose instead to enroll in state colleges that offer business majors.
"Meeting the needs of students keeps them coming to <PERSON>Rollins</PERSON>," Ms <PERSON>Wellman</PERSON> said.
'All Done in Secret'The creation of the new business major, which will serve students in <PERSON>Holt</PERSON> and in the daytime residential program at <LOCATION>Rollins</LOCATION>, has rekindled concerns of administrative overreach. A majority of international-business faculty members recently voted against expanding their course offerings to the evening program, but four professors subsequently agreed to break off and start a new business major. Consequently, international-business professors expect to lose faculty members and students.
"This was all simply announced to us," Mr. <PERSON>Lairson</PERSON> said. "This was all done in secret. The concern was we were being punished for not doing what the administration asked."
Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON>, however, described the creation of a business major by a few professors as a natural path for "curricular innovation" at a college of <PERSON>Rollins</PERSON>'s size.
"It is no way a 'top down' edict, although there are some who would like to characterize it as such," Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> said in an e-mail. "I do personally support the effort."
As on many other campuses across the country, <PERSON>Rollins</PERSON> is ultimately engaged in a debate about the extent to which shared governance, as historically defined, is compatible with what many administrators and trustees, and some faculty members, perceive as the pressing need for transformation.
Indeed, some professors at <PERSON>Rollins</PERSON> say they see clear parallels between what their college has experienced in the last two years and the much higher-profile controversy at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Virginia</ORGANIZATION>, where a failed effort to oust the president was justified by the <ORGANIZATION>Board of Visitors</ORGANIZATION> as a harsh but necessary step toward repositioning the institution for the next millennia.
A senior professor of humanities at <ORGANIZATION>Rollins</ORGANIZATION>, who asked to remain anonymous because he is not an elected representative of the faculty, said there was wide agreement that technology will change how colleges do business. At the same time, he said, the "idea that we should panic over MOOCs, for example, seems really silly."
The proposals Mr. <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> has put forward, the professor said, "sound too much like <ORGANIZATION>New Coke</ORGANIZATION>," a reference to a failed effort by <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola</ORGANIZATION> in the 1980s to alter the recipe of the company's signature soft drink.
"I don't think the way you deal with that is by immediately saying we need to toss out everything we've been doing for 50 years and become much more like everybody else," the professor added. "Part of what's distinguished us and why our reputation has been good is that we have a distinctive brand."
Correction (3/28/2013, 10:35 a.m.):The original version of this article misidentified one of the departments that was moved out of Arts andamp; Sciences in 2011 to create the new College of Professional Studies. It was communications, not economics. The text has been corrected.
<PERSON>Jack Stripling</PERSON>