Foreign Policyon Monday named its“100 Top Global Thinkers 2012”list, and a face familiar to higher-education leaders sits in the top five. <PERSON>Sebastian Thrun</PERSON>,Udacity’s founderand a pioneer ofmassive open online courses,beat out <PERSON>Bill Gates</PERSON> and ranked just below <PERSON>Bill</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hillary Clinton</PERSON>.
Many observers have credited Mr. <PERSON>Thrun</PERSON>’s upstart company with spearheading a higher-education revolution, but this honor apparently has nothing to do with <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s.
The magazine’s editors insteadheap praiseon Mr. <PERSON>Thrun</PERSON> for working toward a different kind of revolution—namely, a driverless-car revolution.
Foreign Policysuggests that Mr. <PERSON>Thrun</PERSON>’s work on the futuristic car might make him “the <PERSON>Henry Ford</PERSON> of a new era.” It makes no mention of Udacity or classes enrolling hundreds of thousands of students. So here’s a bit of unsolicited advice for aspiring <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION> leaders who long to be mentioned in the same breath as the Clintons: Keep your day job, but try building some eye-popping robots, too.
Filed under:Research,MOOCsNick DeSantis