<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> has taken what its officials call an “experimental first step” into online education, releasing open-source software calledCourse Builderin hopes that universities will use it to deliver free online courses.
The search giant says it is in talks with edX—apartnership <ORGANIZATION>amongHarvard University</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION> tooffer free online courses—though officials declined to comment further. A post on <ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION>’s research blog this week also cited nine universities interested in using the platform, including <ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION>.
“We’ve been in touch with a number of universities, and I think it’s a confusing time or an exciting time,” said <PERSON>Peter Norvig</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION>’s director of research, in an interview withThe Chroniclelate Wednesday. “We’re close with <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>—<PERSON>Coursera</PERSON> and <PERSON>Udacity</PERSON> both came out of <LOCATION>Stanford</LOCATION>. They’re working on their own open-source project, and they’re also interested in working with us. I think schools are experimenting and they don’t know quite yet what they want to do.”
<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> tested the software when it offered a free open course this summer called Power Searching, which attracted 155,000 registered students. The software is available for download, but installing it requires some technical prowess and a server to run it on. <ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> has also releasedsuggestions for designing online courses.
This first version of Course Builder will be updated and could become a more polished <ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> service in the future depending on how it is received, Mr. <PERSON>Norvig</PERSON> said. The service could become a tool for anyone to build and deliver their own courses, he added.
Mr. <PERSON>Norvig</PERSON> is not a stranger to <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION>’s—he co-taught a free online artificial-intelligence course that helped spark interest in their potential and attracted some 160,000 students. He announced the release of Course Builder ina YouTube video Wednesday.
(Updated at 7:50 a.m. with comment from <ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION>.)
This entry was posted inCompany Watch,Distance Educationand taggedMOOC's. Bookmark thepermalink.