<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>PRWeb</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="fullWidth floatLeft dottedTop"&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  The Catholic Stand, a publishing arm of Little Vatican Management, published information regarding the strategic partnership between Edvance360 LMS-SN, the Catholic Distance Learning Association (part of the National Catholic Education Association), and Holy Apostles Seminary, a small Catholic Seminary. The article discusses the results yielded from the resulting MOOC (Massive Open Online Course), how MOOCs empower small schools, and how a small Catholic college might approach MOOCs differently than larger universities but with highly successful results.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  The article can be accessed at
  &lt;a href="http://catholicstand.com/holy-apostles-setting-a-trend-for-catholic-schools" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://catholicstand.com/holy-apostles-setting-a-trend-for-catholic-schools
  &lt;/a&gt;
  .
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  An excerpt from the article:
  “The attempt of Holy Apostles to launch a MOOC, then, resonates with what W. Joseph King and Michael Nanfito have written about the value of small colleges when considering “how they can use MOOC technology to continue creating and sustaining their collaborative tradition.” They further argue, “Take the ‘massive’ out of ‘massive open online course’ and you have a course delivery program/support model highly useful to liberal arts colleges for outreach and engagement.”
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Readers will learn:
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;ul class="releaseul"&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
   Why size of the hosting school does not matter
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
   About cultivating a community of learners regardless of the content
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
   What retention rates or completion rates signify in MOOCs
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
   Why the main goal is “relationality”
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
   Empowering participants to share experiences and ideas from which everyone can learn
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
   How MOOCs can help learners advance in specific areas of the careers
  &lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  In summary, readers will discover how MOOCs hosted by smaller schools might be better: “better, that is, for people with specific needs or interests who want to succeed but need the relationality that only small schools (and small MOOCs) know how to provide.”
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  About Edvance360
  Edvance360 is an internet-based Learner Management System (LMS) and secure social network that enables schools to implement a successful online academic program.  Edvance360 equips schools, corporations, and organizations to host online courses, implement modular courses, and revitalize residential courses to make them more interactive.  Edvance360 was designed by professors for professors, with input and oversight provided by many of the leading educational design experts, relational-learning experts, and partners.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Edvance360 provides an easy-to-use interface for students and faculty, course management and creation tools, hands-on training, fanatical support, a secure social network, Web 2.0 tools, and collaborative communities to help educational institutions build a networked learning environment.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Our clients enjoy a high return on their investment, personalized support, and customizable solutions.  We do not believe a one-size-fits-all approach is beneficial to our clients, so we are steadfastly committed to adapting Edvance360 to fit the needs of the rapidly changing world of education.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Our team members are experienced educators whose vision is to provide an easy to use, affordable, learner-centered LMS that enables students and faculty to engage in collaborative learning process.  All features in Edvance360 contribute toward engaging students in critical thinking, network building, and life-long learning habits.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Edvance360 is headquartered in Norfolk, Virginia, with operations in Georgia, Florida, North Carolina, and Washington state. For more information, please visit
  &lt;a href="http://www.Edvance360.com" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://www.Edvance360.com
  &lt;/a&gt;
  or call 866-458-0360.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Edvance360 and the Edvance360 logo are trademarks of Edvance360 Corporation. All other company and product names mentioned herein may be trademarks of their respective owners.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  About the Catholic Distance Learning Network
  The Catholic Distance Learning Network of the Seminary Department of the National Catholic Educational Association provides resources for the training of teachers in online teaching and learning and in teaching research design.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Their website can be accessed at
  &lt;a href="http://www.catholicdistance.org" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://www.catholicdistance.org
  &lt;/a&gt;
  .
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  About Holy Apostles College &amp;amp; Seminary
  Holy Apostles College &amp;amp; Seminary hosts two completely online Master of Arts programs in Philosophy and Theology and has online undergraduate courses available. Holy Apostles is accredited by the New England Association of Schools and Colleges.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Their website can be accessed at
  &lt;a href="http://www.holyapostles.edu" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://www.holyapostles.edu
  &lt;/a&gt;
  .
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>PRWeb</pub_title>
  <document_url>http://www.prweb.com/releases/2013/2/prweb10386869.htm</document_url>
  <author></author>
  <abstract>The Catholic Stand, a publishing arm of Little Vatican Management, published information regarding the strategic partnership between Edvance360 LMS-SN, the Catholic Distance Learning Association (part of the National Catholic Education Association), and Holy Apostles Seminary, a small Catholic Seminary.</abstract>
  <title>Edvance360’s Strategic Partnership Sets Trend for Catholic Educational Institutions</title>
  <database>PRWeb</database>
  <query>Massive Open Online Course</query>
  <pub_date>February 04, 2013</pub_date>
  <document_id>prweb-10386869</document_id>
  <source>Edvance360</source>
</DOCUMENT>
