<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>PRWeb</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="fullWidth floatLeft dottedTop"&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  As everyone from Tom Friedman to Malcolm Gladwell has acknowledged, the world is flat and getting flatter. Industries are more and more interconnected (as evidenced by the sudden Massive Open Online Course hysteria) and the same can be said for point of sale software. Just in time for the New Year, AccuPOS has taken the world by storm and opened its Israel office, promising to deliver point of sale systems in more locations. This will allow restaurants, retailers, bars, and lounges from North America to the Middle East to enjoy all that AccuPOS’ point of sale hardware and software has to offer.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  New location for a New Year
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Located on the central coast of Israel in the western part of the Tel Aviv district, AccuPOS is bringing its point of sale software to Herzliya. The location ranks as one of the most educated as well as having one of the highest qualities of life. A sister city to Beverly Hills, California, Herzliya is home to many ambassadors, business leaders, and diplomats and boasts some of the most pristine beaches and a vibrant cultural scene. It is also a prospering hub for tech companies, AccuPOS included.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Breaking free from the local area network
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Just as AccuPOS has expanded beyond its own local area, its point of sale software no longer needs to be tied to a local area network. This will enable any user in any restaurant or retail store to learn and use the system almost instantly.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Restaurants and retailers across the globe can now enjoy the following:
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;ul class="releaseul"&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
   Point of sale software with line item accounting integration for users of QuickBooks, Peachtree, Simply Accounting, MAS 90 and 200, and Line 50
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
   Point of sale for Android
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
   Integrated credit card processing that eliminates human error and increases your return on investment
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
   Increasing software diversity for an increasingly diverse world!
  &lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  About Attitude POSitive:
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Attitude POSitive is the creator of AccuPOS (Point of Sale) inventory management and time clock software for the retail and hospitality industries. The AccuPOS family of products, designed to be faster and easier than a cash register, offers unmatched ease of use, security and cost-effectiveness to streamline the sales process.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  AccuPOS products, based on open standards, expand the capabilities of an existing accounting program and allow users to grow and change without being locked into proprietary vendor products. AccuPOS products are integrated with the most widely used accounting packages, including the QuickBooks, Sage 50 – U.S. Edition, Sage 50 – Canadian Edition and Sage 100 ERP products.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Founded in 1999, Attitude POSitive is headquartered in Los Angeles with regional offices throughout the United States as well as in Europe and Israel. For more information, visit
  &lt;a href="http://www.accupos.com" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://www.accupos.com
  &lt;/a&gt;
  .
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Contact:
  AccuPOS
  Alexandra Le
  800-906-5010 x615
  alexandral(at)accupos(dot)com
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>PRWeb</pub_title>
  <document_url>http://www.prweb.com/releases/2012/12/prweb10208213.htm</document_url>
  <author></author>
  <abstract>Get ready for more POS software in more places. AccuPOS rings in the new year by expanding its reach across the globe.</abstract>
  <title>Mazel Tov to AccuPOS’ Israel Office Launch</title>
  <database>PRWeb</database>
  <query>Massive Open Online Course</query>
  <pub_date>December 05, 2012</pub_date>
  <document_id>prweb-10208213</document_id>
  <source>AccuPOS</source>
</DOCUMENT>
