<LOCATION>Wellesley</LOCATION>, a prestigious women's college, on Tuesday joined a nonprofit venture known as edX that offers free online higher education to the world.The announcement was the latest development in the fast-unfolding movement to provide massive open online courses, or MOOCs.Led by <ORGANIZATION>Harvard University</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>, edX launched in May. The <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION> joined in July, and the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION> system joined in October.<LOCATION>Wellesley</LOCATION> will offer four courses on theMOOCplatform starting in fall 2013."This is a grand experiment, and what we learn will benefit <LOCATION>Wellesley</LOCATION> students as well as students all over the world," said <PERSON>H. Kim Bottomly</PERSON>, president of the <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> liberal arts college.OtherMOOCplatforms include <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON> and Udacity. In the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> region, the universities of <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Johns Hopkins University</ORGANIZATION> are <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON> participants.Many higher education leaders wonder how offering free online courses will shake up the market. Demand for the courses from brand-name schools has surged this year worldwide.