<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>The Chronicle Review</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="article-body" id="article-body"&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   News
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Pepperdine-Us-President/137517/"&gt;
      Pepperdine U.'s President Faces One Problem He Can't Solve
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/High-Profile-Plagiarism/137515/"&gt;
      High-Profile Plagiarism Prompts Soul-Searching in German Universities
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The esteemed academic home of Humboldt and Hegel struggles to root out scholarly fraud
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Threat-of-Sequester-Has/137533/"&gt;
      Threat of Sequester Has Researchers, Aid Officers Scrambling
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Unless Congress acts, thousands of scientists will lose their jobs and thousands of students will lose their financial aid.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Uncle-Sams-Gift-to-Military/137519/"&gt;
      Uncle Sam's Gift to Military Children
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Federal education benefits and related programs make college possible not only for veterans but for military families, too.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Jury-Is-Out-on-the-New/137531/"&gt;
      The Jury Is Out on New College Scorecard
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     &lt;em&gt;
      The Chronicle
     &lt;/em&gt;
     asked five higher-education and student-aid experts to weigh in on the White House's new tool for families to use to compare colleges.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Pay-Increase-for-Top/137525/"&gt;
      Pay Increase for Top Administrators Barely Outpaces Inflation
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Their median base pay rose by 2.3 percent last year, an improvement over the previous year, an annual survey found.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/High-School-Dropouts-Get-a/137521/"&gt;
      High-School Dropouts Get a Taste of College at Texas Academy
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The program has helped an impoverished school district graduate more than 1,000 off-track students since 2007.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/For-Adviser-to-Historically/137529/"&gt;
      For Adviser to Historically Black Colleges, Good Governance Is Key
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     John W. Garland is the first president in residence of the Thurgood Marshall College Fund. He hopes to help member colleges harness their "transformative power."
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Yale-Theologian-Is-Drawn-to/137527/"&gt;
      Yale Theologian Is Drawn to Lead a Divinity School With a Progressive Edge
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Emilie M. Townes at first didn't want the pressure of being dean at Vanderbilt Divinity School. But she was taken by what it stood for.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Transitions-President-of/137523/"&gt;
      Transitions: President of Caltech to Lead Saudi University; Math Professor to Take Helm at Southwestern U.
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Jean-Lou Chameau will become the second president of King Abdullah University of Science and Technology. Read about that and other job-related news.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/How-EdX-Plans-to-Earn-and/137433/"&gt;
      How EdX Plans to Earn, and Share, Revenue From Free Online Courses
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The nonprofit is giving university partners two options for sharing in the money its MOOCs bring in. But first, they have to bring it in.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Emory-Faculty-Seek-More/137407/"&gt;
      Emory Faculty Seek More Contrition From Their President
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The president has apologized for using a racially sensitive episode in U.S. history to make a point, but critics say the way he apologized was confusing.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Gifts-to-US-Colleges-Rose/137409/"&gt;
      Gifts to U.S. Colleges Rose 2.3% in 2012, Narrowly Outpacing Inflation
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The growth was well below 2011's 8.2-percent rise and, when adjusted for inflation, came to an increase of just 0.2 percent, says the Council for Aid to Education.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Planned-Military-Research-at/137381/"&gt;
      Planned Military Research at Yale Medical School Draws Criticism
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Critics say the center would train interrogators using immigrants as subjects. The psychiatrist who would lead the project says its purpose is misunderstood.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/blogs/headcount/ranking-colleges-by-desirability/33873"&gt;
      Ranking Colleges by 'Desirability'
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     A new paper proposes a model based on students’ “revealed preferences”: the colleges they choose from among all those that accept them.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/In-Rare-Second-Act-Chapel/137375/"&gt;
      In Rare Second Act, Chapel Hill Chancellor Will Be Provost at Washington U.
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     H. Holden Thorp will take an unusual step down the administrative ladder in moving from North Carolina to St. Louis.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   The Chronicle Review
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/In-Ian-Morriss-Big-History/137415/"&gt;
      In Ian Morris's Big History, the Future Looms Large
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     His latest book analyzed 15,000 years of data to explain why the West is dominant. Now the intelligence community wants to know what will happen next.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/A-Battered-Bag-of-Memories/137417/"&gt;
      A Battered Bag of Memories
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Years ago, a writer lost a satchel full of student humiliation. Then one night a stranger calls …
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Closer-to-God-Religion-and/137421/"&gt;
      Closer to God: Religion and the American Space Program
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Astronauts' experiences, theologians' pronouncements, and churches in space-enclave communities all factor in to a new cultural history.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Myths-Behind-the-Age-of/137423/"&gt;
      The Myths Behind the Age of Martyrs
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The documentary record does not support the ideologically charged narrative of early Christian martyrdom.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Aaron-Swartz-Was-Right/137425/"&gt;
      Aaron Swartz Was Right
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The current academic publishing system is prettied-up extortion. He defied it, and the rest of us should too.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   Views
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Give-AP-Credit-Where-Credit-Is/137543/"&gt;
      Give AP Credit Where Credit Is Due
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Colleges have the right to choose which high-school-level work to credit. But they should think about what their decisions mean for high schoolers.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Its-Time-for-Graduate-Science/137541/"&gt;
      Ph.D. Student in the Sciences? Time to Get Real
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The number of Ph.D.'s produced outweighs the number of jobs for them in academe. Departments should tell students more about alternative careers.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/A-Liberal-Arts-Home-for-the/137539/"&gt;
      A Liberal-Arts Home for the Military
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     If we are to remain a democratic republic, we must reacquaint academic America with the military.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Were-Not-a-Hierarchy-Were/137461/"&gt;
      We're Not a Hierarchy, We're an Ecosystem
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Graduate programs should ignore the rankings and find their niche.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Bloopers-to-Avoid-in-Job/137449/"&gt;
      Bloopers to Avoid in Job Interviews
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Here are 12 things you should never say or do as a job candidate.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>Chronicle</pub_title>
  <author></author>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <title>Volume 59, Issue 25: March 1, 2013</title>
  <comments></comments>
  <document_url>http://chronicle.com/article/Volume-59-Issue-25-March-1/137561/</document_url>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>February 25, 2013</pub_date>
  <document_id>chronicle-137561</document_id>
</DOCUMENT>
