<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>The Chronicle Review</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="article-body" id="article-body"&gt;
 &lt;div style="width: 250px; float: left; margin: 0 18px 3px 5px;"&gt;
  &lt;p style="margin-bottom: 10px; padding-bottom: 0; font-weight: normal; font-size: 12px;"&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
   What is it like to teach a free online course to tens of thousands of students? Dozens of professors are doing just that, experimenting with a format known as
   &lt;a href="/blogs/wiredcampus/u-of-illinois-at-springfield-offers-new-massive-open-online-course/31853"&gt;
    Massive Open Online Courses.
   &lt;/a&gt;
   And there are more providers than ever, some working with elite universities, and others that
   &lt;a href="/blogs/wiredcampus/4-start-ups-are-offering-free-online-courses/35355"&gt;
    allow any professor to join in.
   &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
   &lt;em&gt;
    The Chronicle
   &lt;/em&gt;
   asked four professors, teaching on different platforms, to share their thoughts on the experience so far. The responses are based on e-mail interviews, which have been condensed and edited for publication.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;ul class="mooc"&gt;
  &lt;li class="mooc-bylines"&gt;
   &lt;img alt="Peter Struck" class="mooc-photo-1 interactive_headshot" src="http://chronicle.com/img/photos/biz/pstruck.jpg"/&gt;
   &lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;a href="/article/Reworking-a-Course-Into-an/132129/"&gt;
     Reworking a Course Into an Online Format: 'Sort of Like Moving'
    &lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;/h4&gt;
   &lt;p class="nytint-bylines"&gt;
    Peter Struck: Associate professor of classical studies, University of Pennsylvania, teaching via Coursera
   &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;em&gt;
    "You find things in the version of the course you know well and wonder, Now why did I hang onto that? And then you run into other things and are reminded of why they're so important."
   &lt;/em&gt;
   &lt;p&gt;
   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li class="mooc-bylines"&gt;
   &lt;img alt="David Evans" class="participants mooc-photo-4 interactive_headshot" src="http://chronicle.com/img/photos/biz/devans.jpg"/&gt;
   &lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;a href="/article/Turning-Muddled-Recordings/132131/"&gt;
     Turning 'Muddled Recordings' Into a 'Seamless Video'
    &lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;/h4&gt;
   &lt;p class="nytint-bylines"&gt;
    David Evans: Associate professor of computer science, University of Virginia, teaching via Udacity
   &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;em&gt;
    "This is different from classroom lecturing since the students are not there when you are doing it (most of the recording is done alone), and the recording will be edited to produce the class."
   &lt;/em&gt;
   &lt;p&gt;
   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li class="mooc-bylines"&gt;
   &lt;img alt="Margaret Soltan" class="mooc-photo-2 interactive_headshot" src="http://chronicle.com/img/photos/biz/msoltan.jpg"/&gt;
   &lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;a href="/article/Sharing-a-Passion-for-Poetry/132133/"&gt;
     Sharing a Passion for Poetry With Students Around the World
    &lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;/h4&gt;
   &lt;p class="nytint-bylines"&gt;
    Margaret Soltan: Associate professor of English, George Washington University, teaching via Udemy
   &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;em&gt;
    "I hope that the willingness of American university professors to do free MOOC's will enhance the image of universities among Americans, many of whom think of tenured university professors as people always looking to get out of teaching, always obsessed with their own research."
   &lt;/em&gt;
   &lt;p&gt;
   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li class="mooc-bylines"&gt;
   &lt;img alt="Curtis Bonk" class="participants mooc-photo-3 interactive_headshot" src="http://chronicle.com/img/photos/biz/cbonk.jpg"/&gt;
   &lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;a href="/article/Building-Different-MOOCs-for/132127/"&gt;
     Building Different MOOC’s for Different Pedagogical Needs
    &lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;/h4&gt;
   &lt;p class="nytint-bylines"&gt;
    Curtis Bonk: Professor of education, Indiana University at Bloomington, teaching via Blackboard
   &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;em&gt;
    "Some people seem to treat MOOC's as a type of religious experience."
   &lt;/em&gt;
   &lt;p&gt;
   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>Chronicle</pub_title>
  <author>Jeffrey R. Young</author>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <title>4 Professors Discuss Teaching Free Online Courses for Thousands of Students</title>
  <comments></comments>
  <document_url>http://chronicle.com/article/4-Professors-Discuss-Teaching/132125/</document_url>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>June 11, 2012</pub_date>
  <document_id>chronicle-132125</document_id>
</DOCUMENT>
