<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>The Chronicle Review</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="article-body" id="article-body"&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   News
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Employment-Mismatch/137625/"&gt;
      A College Degree Sorts Job Applicants, but Employers Wish It Meant More
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/National-Association-of/137607/"&gt;
      National Association of Scholars, at 25, Shows Signs of Age
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The group that seeks to maintain traditionalism in higher learning struggles to attract members and money.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/U-of-Colorado-Is-in-Search-of/137567/"&gt;
      U. of Colorado Is in Search of a Scholar of Conservative Thought
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The visiting scholar's position, supported by private donations, was created in part to counter public perceptions of ideological bias at the flagship.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/White-House-Delivers-New/137549/"&gt;
      White House Delivers New Open-Access Policy That Has Activists Cheering
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The Obama administration says federally financed research should be made freely available within 12 months of publication in a peer-reviewed journal.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/NSF-Anticipates-Pushing/137553/"&gt;
      NSF Anticipates Pushing Boundaries on Open-Access Plan
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The science foundation is among the agencies that were asked to set policies on how long publishers can restrict access to federally sponsored research.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Getting-Down-to-the-Reality-of/137637/"&gt;
      Getting Down to the Reality of a $10,000 Bachelor's Degree
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     With a YouTube comment and a governor's challenge, the idea has grown into a kind of Rorschach test for how Americans view higher education.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/In-Helping-Immigrant-Students/137563/"&gt;
      In Helping Immigrant Students, Jesuit Colleges Hope to Lead the Way
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     More than two dozen of the colleges pledge to assist students who are in the country illegally, and three colleges issue a paper on what needs to be done.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/To-Foster-Financial-Literacy/137581/"&gt;
      To Foster Financial Literacy, Students Need More Than Information, Report Says
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     For financial-literacy training at colleges to work, it must also tackle students' attitudes and behaviors, according to an analysis of survey results.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Bandwith-Divide/137633/"&gt;
      The Bandwith Divide
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     A new kind of digital divide means that online courses might not be available for everyone.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/blogs/wiredcampus/online-courses-could-widen-achievement-gaps-among-students/42521"&gt;
      Wired Campus: Online Courses Could Widen Achievement Gaps Among Students
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     In a study of students who took more classes online, those in underrepresented groups fell further behind than if they were taking face-to-face courses.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/U-of-Phoenix-Expects/137565/"&gt;
      U. of Phoenix Expects Probation From Its Accreditor
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     A review team has recommended probation, saying the institution lacks sufficient autonomy from its corporate owner. The company plans to appeal.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Adjunct-Orientations-Take/137631/"&gt;
      Adjunct Orientations Take Hold, With a Variety of Approaches
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Unheard of in years past, formal introductory programs for part-timers are becoming more common.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Canceled-Conference-Revives/137559/"&gt;
      Canceled Conference Revives Concerns About Academic Freedom in the Persian Gulf
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The London School of Economics has shut down an event in the United Arab Emirates over "restrictions imposed on the intellectual content."
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/High-Debt-Loads-May-Deter-Men/137555/"&gt;
      High Debt Loads May Deter Men From Graduating, Research Finds
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Women may tolerate student-loan debt more than men do because they have more to gain in earnings potential by completing a college degree.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Energy-Makeovers-for-Labs/137643/"&gt;
      Energy Makeovers for Labs Create Breathing Room in the Bottom Line
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Changes in ventilation systems have added up to big savings at campuses in Arizona and California.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/For-Profit-Group-Suggests-Best/137583/"&gt;
      For-Profit Group Suggests Best Practices for Serving Military and Veteran Students
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The Association of Private Sector Colleges and Universities assembled a panel of experts to produce the guidelines, which are intended for all colleges.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Georgia-State-U-Scholar-Leads/137639/"&gt;
      Georgia State U. Scholar Leads Strengthened Oral-History Group
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The Oral History Association's first-ever executive director, Clifford M. Kuhn, must lead it through the rocky terrain of legal challenges and digital advances.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/A-Dean-Seeks-Ways-to-Recruit/137641/"&gt;
      A Dean Seeks Ways to Recruit Minority Scholars to Liberal-Arts Colleges
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Shirley M. Collado, of Middlebury College, is one of the leaders of an effort to persuade certain doctoral students to consider teaching at small, rural colleges.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/U-of-Wyoming-Names-New/137647/"&gt;
      U. of Wyoming Names New President; Amherst College Hires Dean of Students From Gates Foundation
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The university's next leader will be Robert J. Sternberg, provost at Oklahoma State University. Read about that and other job-related news.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Engineer-Brought-a-Passion-for/137645/"&gt;
      Engineer Brought a Passion for Teaching to the Presidency of a Georgia University
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Beheruz N. Sethna, who is retiring as president of the University of West Georgia, wanted to raise the institution's status, and he did.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Dr-Garbage-Studies-Local/137651/"&gt;
      'Dr. Garbage' Studies Local Tribe Many Prefer to Ignore
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The tribe examined by an anthropologist at NYU works in plain sight in Manhattan, with lingo, rules, and customs all its own.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   The Chronicle Review
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Fixing-Financial-Aid/137593/"&gt;
      Fixing Financial Aid
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     For 40 years, federal money has sustained higher education while enabling its worst tendencies. That's about to change.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Synthetic-Biology-Comes-Down/137587/"&gt;
      Synthetic Biology Comes Down to Earth
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Jim Collins was there when the promise of engineered life generated waves of press. It's quieted down since then, and that's not all bad.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Real-Digital-Change-Agent/137589/"&gt;
      The Real Digital Change Agent
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     MOOCs get the marquee billing. But open access has far greater potential to transform society, and to save colleges money in the process.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Fearthe-Legacy-of-the-New/137595/"&gt;
      Fear and the Legacy of the New Deal
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The program was forged under the distinctive political pressures of its anxious times, but its imperfections continue to influence our own era.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Comedy-Club/137591/"&gt;
      Comedy Club
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Which do you think is harder: getting tenure or getting into the Friars Club?
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/In-Pursuit-of-the-Impossible/137585/"&gt;
      In Pursuit of the Impossible Equation
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     A new book explores the challenges of reducing the computationally confounding to the conceivably calculable.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   Views
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/As-Colleges-Evolve-So-Must/137635/"&gt;
      As Colleges Evolve, So Must Their Presidents
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Academe is in a period of profound change, and a new generation of leaders will have to change with it.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Lets-Help-Computer-Science/137649/"&gt;
      Let's Help Computer-Science Students Crack the Code
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Successful professional programmers grab code from the Web, work in teams, and critique one another. Our students should be doing the same.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Avoiding-Bad-Advice-From-Your/137655/"&gt;
      Avoiding Bad Advice From Your Colleagues
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Tips on how to ignore, reject, or only pretend to follow terrible guidance.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Bittersweet-Task-of/137657/"&gt;
      The Bittersweet Task of Running a Grant Program
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     From drafting the call for proposals to announcing the results, here's what you need to know.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Caps-on-Data-Use-Dim-Online/137653/"&gt;
      Caps on Data Use Dim Online Learning's Bright Future
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Educators believe new online courses could make higher education more available and affordable for all. But what about people who can't afford the Internet?
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>Chronicle</pub_title>
  <author></author>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <title>Volume 59, Issue 26: March 8, 2013</title>
  <comments></comments>
  <document_url>http://chronicle.com/article/Volume-59-Issue-26-March-8/137673/</document_url>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>March  4, 2013</pub_date>
  <document_id>chronicle-137673</document_id>
</DOCUMENT>
