<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>The Chronicle Review</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="article-body" id="article-body"&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   News
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Youre-Distracted-This/138079/"&gt;
      You're Distracted. This Professor Can Help.
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Cuts-May-Force-Long-Awaited/138123/"&gt;
      Cuts May Force Eagerly Awaited Efficiencies on NIH
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Sequestration means an immediate 5-percent reduction in spending at an agency whose budget doubled from 1998 to 2003.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/EfficiencyAcademic/138115/"&gt;
      Efficiency and Academic Freedom Clash at CUNY
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Fueling the debate are broader worries about the marginalization of the faculty and impatience with the slow pace of change at a time of shrinking public support.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/In-Win-for-Libraries-Over/137999/"&gt;
      In Win for Libraries Over Publishers, Supreme Court Upholds Reselling of Foreign Books
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The case stemmed from a graduate student's importing of less-expensive textbooks to the United States from abroad, and then reselling them at a profit.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Unintended-Consequences-of/138103/"&gt;
      The Unintended Consequences of Ending Merit Aid
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The discounts that colleges give applicants for good grades are coming under criticism. But cutting such merit aid won't necessarily mean more money for need-based aid.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Why-One-University-Became-a/138105/"&gt;
      Why One University Became a Hispanic-Serving Institution
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Notre Dame de Namur University, in California, saw significant advantages in acknowledging reality. The move has paid off.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-White-House-Nudger-Is/138119/"&gt;
      The White House 'Nudger' Is Back on Campus
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Cass Sunstein, former regulatory czar, is teaching "Inside Governemnt," a course at Harvard with Lawrence Summers, and has written a memoir of his time in the Obama...
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Researchers-Protest-Canadian/138111/"&gt;
      Researchers Protest Canadian Government's New Restrictions on Sharing Data
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Critics say the confidentiality rule is the latest in a series of efforts to limit public access to government-sponsored research.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Average-Pay-Increases-for/138125/"&gt;
      Average Pay Increases for Academic Professionals Trailed Inflation This Year
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The median base salary for professional staff members on college campuses increased by 2 percent in 2012-13.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Aspen-Prize-Honors-2-Community/138001/"&gt;
      Aspen Prize Honors 2 Community Colleges for Students' Successes
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Santa Barbara City College and Walla Walla Community College were chosen, respectively, for achievements in academic and job-training efforts.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Student-Aid-Can-Be-Awarded-for/137991/"&gt;
      Student Aid Can Be Awarded for 'Competencies,' Not Just Credit Hours
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     In a long-awaited letter, the Education Department spells out how colleges may apply to use federal aid for new models of education.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Outrage-Over-Lavish-Spending/138097/"&gt;
      Outrage Over Lavish Spending at St. John's U. Threatens Its President
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The suicide of a dean on trial for theft from the New York university hasn't eased a crisis that may reach the highest levels of the administration.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Double-Majors-Produce-Dynamic/137917/"&gt;
      Double Majors Produce Dynamic Thinkers, Study Finds
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Double majors tend to gain creative-thinking skills, and they do so largely on their own, despite obstacles put in their way by academe.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Professors-See-a-Lack-of/138005/"&gt;
      Professors See a Lack of Professionalism Among Students
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     More than one-third of those surveyed said fewer than half of their upper-class students exhibited traits associated with being professional in the workplace.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/In-London-the-Ultimate/138121/"&gt;
      In London, the Ultimate Teaching Evaluation Comes With a $100,000 Prize
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Four business professors delivered lectures before a group of students who would determine which one deserved a sizable award.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Foundation-Chief-Is-Named-Dean/138127/"&gt;
      Foundation Chief Is Named Dean of Columbia Journalism School; Oberlin Dean to Lead Kenyon College
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Steve Coll, departing president of the New America Foundation, will succeed Nicholas Lemann. Read about that and other job-related news.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/A-Cal-State-Chief-Is-Named/137989/"&gt;
      A Cal State Chief Is Named Sole Finalist for Top Job at LSU
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     If confirmed, F. King Alexander would step into a new position at Louisiana State that merges the posts of system president and flagship chancellor.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Psychology-Professor-Engages-a/138117/"&gt;
      Psychology Professor Engages a Whole Campus in Protecting Student Mental Health
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     For a year, Robin D. Everall looked into mental-health needs at the University of Alberta. Now she's helping lead efforts to improve emotional health on the campus.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Selected-New-Books-on-Higher/138113/"&gt;
      Selected New Books on Higher Education
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Topics include the first-year college experiences of five "at risk" Mexican-American students and guidance for unemployed college graduates.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/US-Commerce-Secretary-Is/137987/"&gt;
      U.S. Commerce Secretary Is Tapped to Lead U. of Wisconsin at Madison
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Rebecca M. Blank, a former public-policy dean at Michigan, will lead a campus that has been at the center of debates over the role of public flagship institutions.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   The Chronicle Review
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-New-Industrial-Revolution/138015/"&gt;
      The New Industrial Revolution
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The next wave of robots could change the meaning of work.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Robots-Arent-the-Problem-/138007/"&gt;
      Robots Aren't the Problem: It's Us
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Automation will engender neither utopia nor dystopia. Humans alone are responsible for our society's economic future.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Barbed-Gift-of-Leisure/138011/"&gt;
      The Existential Quandaries of Robo-Serviced Utopia
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The gravest danger of offloading work is not a machine uprising but a human downgrading.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Soul-of-Invention/138017/"&gt;
      The Soul of Invention
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Technology shifts gears. The workers who control it need to learn how to shift gears, too.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/When-Bots-Go-Bad/138009/"&gt;
      Robots Behind Bars
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Can robots commit crimes? And if so, a law scholar wonders, should they be rehabilitated or reprogrammed?
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/I-Dont-Want-to-Be-Moocd/138013/"&gt;
      I Don't Want to Be Mooc'd
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Creative destruction is a fine economic theory, until you become its object.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   Views
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Lets-Do-Lunch/138083/"&gt;
      Let's Do Lunch
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Treating graduate students as people, not just scholars in training, will make them better professionals.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Considering-Adjunct-Misery/138085/"&gt;
      Considering Adjunct Misery
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Alex Kudera's novel offers a realistic depiction of the life and psychology of a contingent faculty member.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Walk-Deliberately-Dont-Run/138109/"&gt;
      Walk Deliberately, Don't Run, Toward Online Education
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Let's experiment, but in assessing outcomes and cost savings, let's also insist on hard evidence.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Brave-New-World-of-College/138107/"&gt;
      The Brave New World of College Branding
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Elite colleges are ultimately in the business of maximizing status, not revenue. That's one of the reasons they don't mind running MOOCs at a loss.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>Chronicle</pub_title>
  <author></author>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <title>Volume 59, Issue 29: March 29, 2013</title>
  <comments></comments>
  <document_url>http://chronicle.com/article/Volume-59-Issue-29-March-29/138145/</document_url>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>March 25, 2013</pub_date>
  <document_id>chronicle-138145</document_id>
</DOCUMENT>
