<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>The Chronicle Review</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="article-body" id="article-body"&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   News
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Herbert-Richardson-v-the/138497/"&gt;
      Herbert  Richardson v. the World
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/A-New-President-Seeks-to-Move/138519/"&gt;
      A New President Seeks to Move Historic Morehouse College Into the Future
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     John S. Wilson Jr., who left a post in the White House, wants to give his alma mater the great future he imagined it could have when he was a student there.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Presidents-Plan-Would/138473/"&gt;
      President's Plan Would Increase Pell Grants and Add Incentives on Some Student Aid
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The president's proposals include $8-billion for job training at community colleges and rewards for colleges that keep tuition down and meet other goals.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Obama-Budget-Seeks-to-Slowly/138469/"&gt;
      Obama Budget Seeks to Slowly Rebuild Spending on Scientific Research
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The president proposed a 4-percent increase in spending on science, with an emphasis on favored fields that include clean energy and biotechnology.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Obama-Renews-Effort-to-Limit/138475/"&gt;
      Obama Renews Effort to Limit Charitable Deduction
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Advocates for colleges and other nonprofits, who have helped defeat previous attempts to limit tax savings on deductions, geared up to oppose the plan.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/International-Education/138467/"&gt;
      International-Education Programs Face Challenges in President's Budget
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Some academic exchanges would see cuts, although programs to support foreign languages and research would get increases.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/ArtsHumanities-Endowments/138471/"&gt;
      Arts and Humanities Endowments Would Edge Up Under Obama's Budget
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The cultural endowments would see their budgets go up by $200,000 each.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/In-Disturbing-Reversal/138405/"&gt;
      In 'Disturbing' Reversal, Chinese Applications Fall at U.S. Graduate Schools
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     After seven years of double-digit increases, the number of Chinese applications to graduate programs in the United States this spring fell an unexpected 5 percent.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Business-School-Accreditor/138447/"&gt;
      Business-School Accreditor Approves New, More-Flexible Standards
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The updates, the first since 2003, come at a time of rapid growth in the number of foreign business schools seeking recognition from the accreditor.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/I-Fully-Expect-to-Die-With/138507/"&gt;
      'I Fully Expect to Die With This Debt'
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Student-loan debt is growing more quickly among people age 60 and older than in any other age group.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Behind-the-Webcams-Watchful/138505/"&gt;
      Behind the Webcam's Watchful Eye
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     "What we look for is eye movement," says one veteran of the online-test-proctoring industry. It's "almost instrusive," says another.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/A-Radical-Anthropologist-Finds/138499/"&gt;
      A Radical Anthropologist Finds Himself in Academic 'Exile'
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     David Graeber, a scholar of the radical left, can't find a job. Maybe American anthropology departments aren't as liberal as you think.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Report-Examines-Levels-of-Debt/138455/"&gt;
      Report Examines Levels of Debt for College Dropouts Across Sectors
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Federal student-loan debt as a percentage of annual income varied by the type of institution students first attended, the Education Department report shows.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Create-2-Pathways-for-Pell/138431/"&gt;
      Create 2 Pathways for Pell Grants, Group Proposes
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     A panel's report, "Rethinking Pell Grants," calls for new types of grants to promote social mobility for younger students and job training for adults.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Sale-to-Elsevier-Casts-Doubt/138449/"&gt;
      Sale to Elsevier Casts Doubt on Mendeley's Openness
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The acquisition of the popular reference-management and PDF-organizer platform has spurred skepticism among its 2.3 million users.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Scholars-Increasingly-Use/138407/"&gt;
      Scholars Increasingly Use Online Resources but Value Traditional Formats Too
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     For publishing their own research, faculty members still seek out journals with the highest prestige, regardless of format, a survey finds.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/For-Adjuncts-Who-Take-a-Role/138429/"&gt;
      For Adjuncts Who Take a Role in Contract Talks, Job Protection Is Rare
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Adjuncts can come to the bargaining table, speakers at a conference on academic labor said, but doing so can cost them their jobs.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Universities-Benefit-From/138353/"&gt;
      Universities Benefit From Their Faculties' Unionization, Study Finds
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Institutions generally become more efficient and effective when their professors form collective-bargaining units, says a paper being presented at a conference this weekend.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Professors-Rhetorical/138357/"&gt;
      Professor's Rhetorical Question About Rape Draws Firestorm of Protest
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     A petition demands censure of a University of Rochester scholar who mused on a blog: Should rape be illegal if the victim is unconscious and no harm results?
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/blogs/wiredcampus/coursera-takes-a-nuanced-view-of-mooc-dropout-rates/43341"&gt;
      Wired Campus: Coursera Takes a Nuanced View of MOOC Dropout Rates
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Why students wash out of MOOCs was one of the topics discussed at a weekend conference involving the company and its university partners.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/blogs/percolator/democracy-and-terrorism/32605"&gt;
      Percolator: Democracy and Terrorism
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Beth McMurtrie, at the International Studies Association conference in San Francisco, talks to Erica Chenoweth, whose forthcoming book explores a surprisingly nurturing...
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/blogs/percolator/historians-dabbling-in-science-fiction-evoke-a-climate-collapse/32517"&gt;
      Percolator: Historians, Dabbling in Science Fiction, Evoke a Climate Collapse
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Neglect of the threat of global warming today leads to “a second Dark Age” in the West by 2041. But oddly the authors seem to suggest that there’s little we can do to...
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Florida-Atlantic-U-Faculty/138355/"&gt;
      Florida Atlantic U. Faculty Worries About Long-Term Effects of Recent Controversies
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Administrators' responses to several high-profile incidents have left some professors concerned about their freedom to teach controversial subjects.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/A-Leading-Philosopher-Is-Drawn/138513/"&gt;
      A Leading Philosopher Is Drawn From Rutgers to Yale
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Jason Stanley says Yale offers him access to top people in all the areas he wants to explore.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/U-of-Texas-Ransom-Center-to/138509/"&gt;
      U. of Texas' Ransom Center to Get New Director; Next Law Dean Named at New York U.
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Stephen Enniss, of the Folger Shakespeare Library, will lead the humanities-research library and museum. Read about that and other job-related news.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   The Chronicle Review
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/How-Conservatives-Captured-the/138461/"&gt;
      How Conservatives Captured the Law
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     From modest academic roots, the Federalist Society has become a major force in scholarship, politics, and policy.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Biblical-Blame-Shift/138457/"&gt;
      Egyptologist Fuels Anti-Semitism Under Guise of Analyzing It
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Cherry-picking from shaky evidence, the German Egyptologist Jan Assmann argues that the ancient Hebrews sparked centuries of religious violence.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Seasons-of-a-Phrase/138463/"&gt;
      Arabs Keeping Their Spring
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The seemingly companionable term "Arab Spring" has elicited some thoughtful objections in the press and academe.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Linen-Legions/138459/"&gt;
      The Linen Legions
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     A hands-on historian studies how Alexander the Great and his army suited up for victory.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Mystery-Man/138465/"&gt;
      A Messy Story of Identity in America
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     After her Mexican dad gave himself an American makeover, a historian comes to terms with her own identity.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   Views
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Why-Not-a-2-Tier-System-/138521/"&gt;
      Why Not a Two-Tier System?
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     It's time to blow up the old faculty career track and put something else in its place.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Realities-of/138515/"&gt;
      The Realities of Reauthorization
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Two worn but never weary travelers on the higher-education-reform road offer some perspective on policy and politics.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Corporate-Responsibility/138495/"&gt;
      Corporate Responsibility Should Start in Business School
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Business schools should do more to imbue students with a sense of social values.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/How-We-Can-Be-Better-Stewards/138503/"&gt;
      How We Can Be Better Stewards of the American Dream
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Today's higher-education leaders have become gatekeepers of upward mobility.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/blogs/onhiring/the-graceful-goodbye/37233"&gt;
      On Hiring: The Graceful Goodbye
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     When it comes to resigning, a little graciousness and advance notice go a long way, writes Gene C. Fant Jr.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/blogs/onhiring/part-time-faculty-handbook/37249"&gt;
      On Hiring: Part-Time Faculty Handbook
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Eliana Osborn considers what information new adjuncts need most.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>Chronicle</pub_title>
  <author></author>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <title>Volume 59, Issue 32: April 19, 2013</title>
  <comments></comments>
  <document_url>http://chronicle.com/article/Volume-59-Issue-32-April-19/138535/</document_url>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>April 15, 2013</pub_date>
  <document_id>chronicle-138535</document_id>
</DOCUMENT>
