<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>The Chronicle Review</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="article-body" id="article-body"&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   News
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Dissertation-Can-No-Longer/137215/"&gt;
      The Dissertation Can No Longer Be Defended
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/3-PhD-Candidates-Who-Are/137223/"&gt;
      3 Ph.D.'s Doing Digital Dissertations
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Information technology contributes to studies of prison newspapers, frontier post offices, and medieval fortresses.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Great-Possibilities-Thwarted/137219/"&gt;
      Great Possibilities, Thwarted Hopes
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     American colleges seek to build campuses, partnerships, and research opportunities in India, but red tape, poor facilities, and other problems keep getting in the way.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Americans-Value-Higher/137023/"&gt;
      Americans Value Higher Education but Question Its Quality, National Survey Finds
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     They also worry about cost and favor making it easier for working adults to earn degrees, including the awarding of credit for prior learning.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Tough-Times-Push-More-Small/137229/"&gt;
      Tough Times Push More Small Colleges to Join Forces
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Working together can help save money and provide more options to students, but colleges are still concerned about preserving their identities.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Colleges-Ask-Education-Dept/137225/"&gt;
      Colleges Ask Education Dept. to Clarify Rules on Competency and Credit
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Programs that award credit for prior learning have been around for a while, but they haven't been using federal student aid. That may be about to change.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Digital-Devices-Invade-Campus/137217/"&gt;
      Digital Devices Invade Campus, and Networks Feel the Strain
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     One hundred students in the library with their smartphones and iPads can mean more than 200 bandwidth-guzzling Wi-Fi connections.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Flap-Over-Study-Linking/136947/"&gt;
      Flap Over Study Linking Poverty to Biology Exposes Gulfs Among Disciplines
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     A study by two economists that used genetic diversity as a proxy for ethnic and cultural diversity has drawn fierce rebuttals from anthropologists and geneticists.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Common-Application-Adopts-New/137017/"&gt;
      Common Application Adopts New Essay Prompts and a Longer Word Count
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     The changes seek to offer applicants flexibility while encouraging them to focus on what they want others to know about themselves.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Work-Force-Demand-for-STEM/137231/"&gt;
      Work-Force Demand for STEM Students Spurs Efforts at Community Colleges
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     As concerns grow over work-force shortages in science, technology, engineering, and math fields, the colleges ready students for jobs or more education.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/College-Presidents-and/137015/"&gt;
      College Presidents and Education Secretary Push for Stricter Gun Control
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Officials at the National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities' annual meeting spoke out in favor of "common sense" gun-reform legislation.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/American-Council-on-Education/137155/"&gt;
      American Council on Education Recommends 5 MOOCs for Credit
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Approval of the Coursera-provided classses could be a major step toward bridging the gap between massive open online courses and traditional higher education.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/blogs/wiredcampus/georgia-tech-and-coursera-try-to-recover-from-mooc-stumble/42167"&gt;
      Georgia Tech and Coursera Try to Recover From MOOC Stumble
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     When Fatimah Wirth decided to teach a massive open online course about how to run a virtual classroom successfully, she did not expect it to turn into a case study for the...
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Bridge-Program-Offers-Another/137233/"&gt;
      Bridge Program Offers Another Chance to Students Who Have Foundered
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Landmark College's Bridge Semester is designed to help learning-disabled students get back on track at the colleges they previously attended.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/US-Supreme-Court-Is-Urged-to/137159/"&gt;
      U.S. Supreme Court Is Urged to Rule on Michigan Affirmative-Action Case
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Supporters of the state's ban on race-conscious college admissions are challenging an appeals court's ruling that found the ban to be unconstitutional.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Researcher-Is-Lauded-for/137237/"&gt;
      Researcher Is Lauded for Discovering How Students Spend Their Time
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     George D. Kuh, who developed an oft-used and sometimes-criticized study of student engagement, was honored by alumni at the University of Pennsylvania.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/NSFs-Director-Is-Leaving-to/137031/"&gt;
      NSF's Director Is Leaving to Become Head of Carnegie Mellon U.
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Subra Suresh, who has led the federal agency since late 2010, says the unexpected offer from Carnegie Mellon was an opportunity he could not turn down.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Transitions-Chief-Economist/137235/"&gt;
      Transitions: Chief Economist at Regulatory Agency Joins MIT; Xavier U. of Louisiana Hires Its First Provost
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Andrei Kirilenko is now a professor of the practice of finance at MIT's Sloan School of Management. Read about that and other job-related news.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Faces-of-Research-Faces-of/137205/"&gt;
      Slide Show: Faces of Research, Faces of Resistance
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     &lt;span&gt;
      Glimpses of life in academe from around the world.
     &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   The Chronicle Review
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/How-Much-Do-You-Pay-for/137043/"&gt;
      How Much  Do You Pay for College?
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Students are talking more openly about their socioeconomic status. The rest of us should, too.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Armed-in-Anxiety/137035/"&gt;
      Better Sound Than Safe
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     In debating gun policies, we must consider not just our vulnerability but also our humanity.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Quest-for-Permanent/137039/"&gt;
      The Quest for Permanent Novelty
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Artists have created some of their most powerful works by exploring our yearning for ever-fresh sensation.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Why-Narnia-/137037/"&gt;
      Why Narnia?
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Strange, lovely, and symbolically untidy, C.S. Lewis’s fictional kingdom remains a narrative tonic for our spiritual renewal.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Teaching-Ethics-in-a-Dark/137033/"&gt;
      Teaching Ethics in a Dark World
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     An ethicist is painfully reminded of demagoguery’s brute power. Is that a lesson he should share with his idealistic students?
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/A-Leviathan-Task-of-Biography/137041/"&gt;
      A Leviathan Task of Biography
     &lt;/a&gt;
     &lt;img alt="Premium Link" class="premium-icon" src="/img/premium.gif"/&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     More than a decade after the publication of his career-defining Melville volumes, Hershel Parker strikes back at his critics in a genre-bending new work.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;div class="module1"&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;
   Views
  &lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Enough-With-the-Talk-Lets/137213/"&gt;
      Enough With the Talk. Let's Start Fixing It.
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Faculty members and administrators need to get together and start testing solutions to make higher education work for students.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/The-Reality-of-Writing-a-Good/137207/"&gt;
      The Reality of Writing a Good Book Proposal
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Once the crazy submissions are shooed away, publishers are left with a bunch of equally viable candidates.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/Stop-the-Courts-From-Weakening/137221/"&gt;
      Stop the Courts From Weakening Student Journalism
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     A Supreme Court ruling in a 1988 case involving children is now being applied to college and graduate-school students.
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/On-Being-a-Rookie-Chair/137209/"&gt;
      On Being A Rookie Chair
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     Everyone assumes my life is now extraordinarily difficult and stressful. Should I let them?
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li class="sub-promo"&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;
     &lt;a href="/article/College-Presidents-Bruised/137227/"&gt;
      College Presidents: Bruised, Battered, and Loving It
     &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     They can change the world: Who wouldn't want a job like that?
    &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>Chronicle</pub_title>
  <author></author>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <title>Volume 59, Issue 23: February 15, 2013</title>
  <comments></comments>
  <document_url>http://chronicle.com/article/Volume-59-Issue-23-February/137251/</document_url>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>February 11, 2013</pub_date>
  <document_id>chronicle-137251</document_id>
</DOCUMENT>
