<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>PRWeb</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="fullWidth floatLeft dottedTop"&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  &lt;a href="http://www.edvance360.com" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   Edvance360 LMS-SN
  &lt;/a&gt;
  today announced it has received an award for “Most Supportive and Innovative LMS Vendor of 2012” from the
  &lt;a href="http://www.catholicdistance.org" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   Catholic Distance Learning Network of the Seminary Department of the National Catholic Educational Association
  &lt;/a&gt;
  .  The award was conferred for both excellence in support shown by the staff at Edvance360 and innovative learning tools in Edvance360 LMS-SN. Edvance360, the CDLN, and the Holy Apostles Seminary teamed together this fall to host a highly successful
  &lt;a href="https://www.edvance360.com/press_release/mooc/" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   MOOC
  &lt;/a&gt;
  featuring two certificates.  (The MOOC will also be offered again in January 2013.)
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  “The professional staff at Edvance360 provided ongoing and instant support whenever a question arose not only from the administration and faculty supporting the MOOC but also from the students enrolled in the MOOC, for which we are grateful,” said Msgr. Jeremiah McCarthy, SJ Executive Director, Seminary Department of the NCEA.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  “Edvance360 provided support above and beyond what any institution would expect. Also, the additional assistance their experts provided in redesigning the MOOC for the Spring 2013 session based on the data received in its first fall 2012 run was exceptional,” said Dr. Sebastian Mahfood, OP Coordinator of the Catholic Distance Learning Network.  “We highly recommend Edvance360 to any of the schools in our network.”
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  From Edvance360:
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  “This award reinforces what we know to be true about our employees and our software – we have highly talented individuals who are committed to deliver results above and beyond our clients’ expectations,” said Cathy Garland, Vice-President of Marketing &amp;amp; Sales.  “Our software is not only easy to use but perfect for creating an effective environment for life-long learning.  This award from the NCEA/CDLN is an honor.  It is a privilege to serve Catholic educators around the world.”
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  About Edvance360
  Edvance360 is an internet-based Learner Management System (LMS) and secure social network that enables schools to implement a successful online academic program.  Edvance360 equips schools, corporations, and organizations to host online courses, implement modular courses, and revitalize residential courses to make them more interactive.  Edvance360 was designed by professors for professors, with input and oversight provided by many of the leading educational design experts, relational-learning experts, and partners.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Edvance360 provides an easy-to-use interface for students and faculty, course management and creation tools, hands-on training, fanatical support, a secure social network, Web 2.0 tools, and collaborative communities to help educational institutions build a networked learning environment.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Our clients enjoy a high return on their investment, personalized support, and customizable solutions.  We do not believe a one-size-fits-all approach is beneficial to our clients, so we are steadfastly committed to adapting Edvance360 to fit the needs of the rapidly changing world of education.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Our team members are experienced educators whose vision is to provide an easy to use, affordable, learner-centered LMS that enables students and faculty to engage in collaborative learning process.  All features in Edvance360 contribute toward engaging students in critical thinking, network building, and life-long learning habits.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Edvance360 is headquartered in Norfolk, Virginia, with operations in GA, FL, NC, and WA. For more information, please visit
  &lt;a href="http://www.Edvance360.com" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://www.Edvance360.com
  &lt;/a&gt;
  or call 866-458-0360.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Edvance360 and the Edvance360 logo are trademarks of Edvance360 Corporation. All other company and product names mentioned herein may be trademarks of their respective owners.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  About the Catholic Distance Learning Network
  The Catholic Distance Learning Network of the Seminary Department of the National Catholic Educational Association provides resources for the training of teachers in online teaching and learning and in teaching research design.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Their website can be accessed at
  &lt;a href="http://www.catholicdistance.org" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://www.catholicdistance.org
  &lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>PRWeb</pub_title>
  <document_url>http://www.prweb.com/releases/2012/12/prweb10233444.htm</document_url>
  <author></author>
  <abstract>Edvance360 LMS-SN receives “Most Supportive &amp; Innovative LMS Vendor of 2012” award from the Catholic Distance Learning Network of the Seminary Department of the National Catholic Educational Association.</abstract>
  <title>Edvance360 LMS-SN Awarded “Most Supportive &amp; Innovative LMS Vendor of 2012” from CDLA</title>
  <database>PRWeb</database>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>December 13, 2012</pub_date>
  <document_id>prweb-10233444</document_id>
  <source>Edvance360</source>
</DOCUMENT>
