<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>PRWeb</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="fullWidth floatLeft dottedTop"&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  A new open online course planned for next month by the
  &lt;a href="http://ischool.syr.edu" onclick="linkClick(this.href)" title="School of Information Studies - Syracuse University"&gt;
   School of Information Studies (iSchool) at Syracuse University
  &lt;/a&gt;
  will offer an introduction to the field of data science. This first open course offered by the University is currently accepting signups for enrollment consideration.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  The free course, which will last four weeks and be delivered completely online, will provide a taste of what comprises this emerging science, and an understanding of what it means to work as a data scientist. Using Professor and Senior Associate Dean Jeffrey Stanton’s e-book, "An Introduction to Data Science" as a guide, class participants will ramp up on the most popular open source data science tool, the R statistical analysis and visualization system.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  As the world's data grow exponentially, organizations across all sectors, including government and not-for-profit, need to understand, manage and use big, complex data sets—known as Big Data, a term spreading through forward-thinking business dialogue and building exponential job market demand.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  The iSchool’s distinct perspective approaches data science with a view of the full data life cycle, going beyond what most discuss as data analytics.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  "At the iSchool, we’ve been a leader in online education for two decades,” said Stanton. “Beyond the instructional technology, which is evolving very quickly, we also have a deep reservoir of extraordinary faculty talent - some of our faculty had taught dozens of online courses before the acronym MOOC was even coined."
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Stanton will teach the course along with Adjunct Instructor Gary Krudys.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Enrollment in this open online course will be limited to the first 500 students, to ensure a high quality experience for all. No Syracuse University credit will be offered for the course, however, a letter of completion, signed by iSchool Dean Elizabeth Liddy, will be provided to each student who completes the course satisfactorily. To learn more and to register to participate, visit the
  &lt;a href="http://ischool.syr.edu/future/cas/introtodatascience.aspx" onclick="linkClick(this.href)" title="Data Science Online Open Course Registration"&gt;
   open course website
  &lt;/a&gt;
  .
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>PRWeb</pub_title>
  <document_url>http://www.prweb.com/releases/data-science/online-course/prweb10364153.htm</document_url>
  <author></author>
  <abstract>The School of Information Studies (iSchool) at Syracuse University is offering a free open online course that provides an introduction to the field of data science.</abstract>
  <title>Open Course Offers Introduction to Data Science</title>
  <database>PRWeb</database>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>January 28, 2013</pub_date>
  <document_id>prweb-10364153</document_id>
  <source>School of Information Studies - Syracuse University</source>
</DOCUMENT>
