<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>PRWeb</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="fullWidth floatLeft dottedTop"&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Edvance360, winner of the 2011 CODiE Award for Best Post-Secondary Course or Learning Management System, will exhibit at the NCEA Conference 2013 in Houston, Texas. The conference will be held from April 2-4 and is open to all member and candidate schools in both Higher Ed and K-12.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  As a part of the NCEA technology expert exhibitors, Edvance360 will provide answers to attendees regarding online learning, demonstration our relationship-building tools, as well as help interested schools consider MOOCs and their benefits for marketing and increasing online enrollments.  Edvance360 invites attendees to join the MOOCs Decoded Workshop as MOOC experts breakdown MOOCs (Massive Open Online Courses) – the latest online learning evolution – and their impact on smaller educational institutions.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  “Before Edvance360, online education software was both expensive and difficult to implement, which kept small to medium-sized religious schools from being able to take advantage of the financial growth that online enrollments can provide,” said Cathy Garland, Vice-President of Marketing &amp;amp; Sales. “Now, with Edvance360, they can afford our easy to use software, backed by a fanatical support team!  With our social networking and retention features, these schools can build relationships with students and alumni that will last a lifetime.”
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  About Edvance360 LMS™
  Edvance360 is an internet-based Learner Management System (LMS) and secure social network that enables schools to implement an online academic program.  Edvance360 equips schools, businesses, and organizations to host online courses, implement modular courses, and revitalize residential courses to make them more interactive.  For more information go to Edvance360.com or call 866-458-0360.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  About NCEA
  The National Catholic Education Association is f NCEA is a voluntary association of educators and institutions. The Association's structure is based on a departmental arrangement whereby member institutions hold Association membership through one of the constitutive departments. NCEA is the largest private professional education organization in the world, representing 200,000 Catholic educators serving 7.6 million students in Catholic elementary and secondary schools, in religious education programs, in seminaries, and in colleges and universities.
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>PRWeb</pub_title>
  <document_url>http://www.prweb.com/releases/2013/3/prweb10545471.htm</document_url>
  <author></author>
  <abstract>Edvance360, a leading provider of eLearning services and software solutions and a CODiE 2011 winner, announced plans to exhibit and sponsor the NCEA Conference 2013. Edvance360 provides LMS software and support to Catholic education institutions and the Catholic Distance Learning Network (CDLN).</abstract>
  <title>Edvance360 LMS™ Sponsors NCEA (National Catholic Education Association) Annual Conference in Houston, TX, April 2-4, 2013</title>
  <database>PRWeb</database>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>March 19, 2013</pub_date>
  <document_id>prweb-10545471</document_id>
  <source>Edvance360</source>
</DOCUMENT>
