<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>PRWeb</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="fullWidth floatLeft dottedTop"&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  JWT, the world’s best-known marketing communications brand, today released its annual list of 100 Things to Watch for the year ahead.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  “Our list spotlights developments that are bubbling up across sectors, including travel, technology, food, retail and sustainability,” says Ann Mack, director of trendspotting at JWT. “It also reflects broader shifts that we’re forecasting for the year ahead, including the rise in Peer Power, Predictive Personalization and Intelligent Objects.”
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Many of JWT’s Things to Watch are technology-centric, including the proliferation of “appcessories,” digital ecosystems, flexible screens and responsive Web design. The list also includes new foods or ingredients to watch (faux meat, teff), new types of goods or businesses (quiet products, shopping hotels), new behaviors (mindful living, privacy etiquette) and ideas with the potential to ladder up to bigger trends.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  JWT’s 100 Things to Watch in 2013, unranked and in alphabetical order (descriptions of each can be found in the “2013 and beyond” section of
  &lt;a href="http://www.jwtintelligence.com/2013-and-beyond/" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   JWTIntelligence.com
  &lt;/a&gt;
  ):
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  1.    3D Bioprinting
  2.    Adult Playgrounds
  3.    African Tech Stars
  4.    Allergen-Free
  5.    Alternative Brand Currencies
  6.    Ambushed by Amazon
  7.    Appcessories
  8.    The Arabic Web
  9.    B2C/P2P Partnerships
  10.     Bee Venom
  11.     Biometric Authentication
  12.     Blocking Social Media Bores
  13.     Chia Seeds
  14.     Click-and-Collect Shopping
  15.    “Cloaking”
  16.     Coaching Brands
  17.     Cool Techie Camps
  18.     Crowdsourced Translation
  19.     Cutting out the Middleman
  20.     Cyber War
  21.     Dads in the Aisles
  22.     Data Scientists: The New Hotshots
  23.     Decline of Chinese Bling
  24.     Desalination
  25.     Detoxifying Life
  26.     Digital Ecosystems
  27.     Drones
  28.     ecoATM
  29.     Egg Freezing
  30.     Emotion Recognition
  31.     The End of Voicemail
  32.     Faux Meat
  33.     Fitness Beyond the Gym
  34.     Flexible Screens
  35.     Food Sharing
  36.     Frontier Markets
  37.     G20 Devolves to G-Zero
  38.     Gender-Blurred Toys
  39.     Geofencing
  40.     Green Growth
  41.     Handwriting = Hieroglyphics
  42.     Hotels in Africa
  43.     Human-Centered Tech
  44.     Humane Food
  45.     Hyper-Personalized Customer Service
  46.     Impact Sourcing
  47.     Imperfection
  48.     Individual Attention
  49.     Instant-Erase Apps
  50.     JOMO (Joy Of Missing Out)
  51.     Live-Streaming Life
  52.     Low-Cost Robots
  53.     Low-Tech Device Charging
  54.     Media That Gets to Know You
  55.     Medical Smartphones
  56.     Menu-Free Dining
  57.     Midcalorie Foods
  58.     Mindful Living
  59.     Mobile-Optimized Goes Mainstream
  60.     MOOC Stars
  61.     Nature As Antidote
  62.     Neurotechnology
  63.     New Digital Royalty
  64.     News Bites
  65.     NFC Tags
  66.     Objects With Attitude
  67.     Offset Thinking
  68.     Online Groceries
  69.     Paperless Education
  70.     Passwords 2.0
  71.     Patchwork Earnings
  72.     Personal Data Ownership
  73.     Prime Time for Second Screen
  74.     Privacy Etiquette
  75.     Quiet Products
  76.     Reduced-Guilt Candy
  77.     Responsive Web Design
  78.     Retailers Enable Recycling
  79.     River Cruising
  80.     Self-Service
  81.     Serialized Digital Fiction
  82.     Set Jetting
  83.     Shopping Hotels
  84.     Social Media Hacks
  85.     Standup Desks
  86.     Stress-Monitoring Apps
  87.     Sugru
  88.     Tablet Shopping
  89.     Tech-Enabled Farm-to-Fork
  90.     Teff
  91.     Trade School
  92.     Trust Ratings
  93.     User-Based Insurance
  94.     Variable Pricing
  95.     Vegetable Boxes
  96.     Vertical Farming
  97.     Video Games As Art
  98.     Window Shopping
  99.     Wireless Charging
  100.  Yogurt Shops
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  This is the seventh year JWT is publishing such a list, a complement to JWT’s annual 10 Trends forecast. Some of the things JWT has spotlighted in the past include Crowdsourced Learning, Gen Z and Smart Clothing (in 2012); P-to-P Car Sharing, YouTube the Broadcaster and The Nail Polish Economy (in 2011); Mobile Money, Coconut Water and Bacon Everywhere (in 2010); Lady Gaga, Crowdfunding, WikiLeaks and Gluten-Free (in 2009); Radical Transparency and Staycations (in 2008); and Barack Obama, Jennifer Hudson, Companies Going Green and Age Shuffling (in 2007).
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  ABOUT JWT
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  JWT is the world’s best-known marketing communications brand. Headquartered in New York, JWT is a true global network with more than 200 offices in over 90 countries employing nearly 10,000 marketing professionals. JWT consistently ranks among the top agency networks in the world and continues a dominant presence in the industry by staying on the leading edge—from producing the first-ever TV commercial in 1939 to today, developing award-winning branded content. JWT embraces a “worldmade” philosophy, making things inspired by the world through blending technological innovation with international imagination. JWT has forged deep relationships with clients including Bayer, Bloomberg, Brand USA, Cadbury, Diageo, DTC, Ford, HSBC, Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson, Kellogg’s, Kimberly-Clark, Kraft, Macy’s, Nestlé, Nokia, Rolex, Royal Caribbean, Schick, Shell, Smirnoff, Unilever, Vodafone and many others. JWT’s parent company is WPP (NASDAQ: WPPGY). For more information, please visit
  &lt;a href="http://www.jwt.com" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://www.jwt.com
  &lt;/a&gt;
  and follow us
  &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/jwt_worldwide" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   @JWT_Worldwide
  &lt;/a&gt;
  .
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  ABOUT JWTINTELLIGENCE
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  JWTIntelligence is a center for provocative thinking that is a part of JWT. We make sense of the chaos in a world of hyper-abundant information and constant innovation—finding quality amid the quantity. We focus on identifying changes in the global zeitgeist so as to convert shifts into compelling opportunities for brands. We have done this on behalf of multinational clients across several categories including pharmaceuticals, cosmetics, food, home and personal care. For more information, please visit
  &lt;a href="http://www.jwtintelligence.com" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://www.jwtintelligence.com
  &lt;/a&gt;
  and follow us
  &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/jwtintelligence" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   @JWTIntelligence
  &lt;/a&gt;
  .
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  ###
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  PRESS CONTACTS:
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  USA AND CANADA
  For Broadcast and Print:
  Deborah Kohan
  +1 212-593-5885
  deborah(dot)kohan(at)finnpartners(dot)com
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  USA AND CANADA
  For online:
  Eric Glover
  +1 212-715-1559
  eric(dot)glover(at)finnpartners(dot)com
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  WORLDWIDE
  All Enquiries:
  Jinie Kwak
  +1 646-244-6190
  jinie(dot)kwak(at)jwt(dot)com
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>PRWeb</pub_title>
  <document_url>http://www.prweb.com/releases/2012/12/prweb10263970.htm</document_url>
  <author></author>
  <abstract>Annual List Includes Adult Playgrounds, Chia Seeds and Instant-Erase Apps</abstract>
  <title>JWT's 100 Things to Watch In 2013</title>
  <database>PRWeb</database>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>December 26, 2012</pub_date>
  <document_id>prweb-10263970</document_id>
  <source>USA AND CANADA (BROADCAST AND PRINT)</source>
</DOCUMENT>
