<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>PRWeb</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="fullWidth floatLeft dottedTop"&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  What:Join Academic Partnerships’ Faculty eCommons for a 3-week micro-MOOC (Massive Open Online Course) on Engaging Technology and Online Pedagogy. Led by guest speaker Brian Mull, Innovation Director of November Learning, we will explore new tools and the characteristics that makeup effective — and ineffective — online learning technologies. We will examine how to choose tools based on pedagogical styles used in online instruction. MOOC participants will also have the opportunity to re-create an assignment from a current course using a new technology tool and share the end product with other webinar participants.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  When: November 8 at 1:30 PM CST
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Where:Free registration
  &lt;a href="http://facultyecommons.com/engaging-technology-and-online-pedagogy-etop12-micro-mooc/" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://facultyecommons.com/engaging-technology-and-online-pedagogy-etop12-micro-mooc/
  &lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Who: Brian Mull, Innovation Director of November Learning
  Brian has been an educator, a technology director and a curriculum specialist. He now assists Institutions schools and districts in the building of robust and rigorous educational environments by tapping into today’s wealth of information and tools.
  Described as having an infectious enthusiasm and incredible depth of knowledge, Brian shares a powerful vision for teaching and learning with administrators, teachers, and students. He focuses on critical thinking, motivating students through authentic tasks and developing collaborative partnerships. He was named as one of Google’s first 200 certified educators, and he has developed a professional network of global peers who continue to expand and challenge his thinking.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  About Faculty eCommons
  Developed by Academic Partnerships, Faculty eCommons is a social learning ecosystem for faculty across the globe to work together and better online education.  The site offers industry research, guidance, best practices, and professional development, with a focus on national quality standards.  Academic Partnerships has a strategic alliance with Sloan Consortium and a subscription to the Quality Matters™ program, which are available to AP Partner faculty.  For more information, visit:
  &lt;a href="http://facultyecommons.com" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://facultyecommons.com
  &lt;/a&gt;
  .
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  About Academic Partnerships
  Dallas-based Academic Partnerships partners with public universities to deliver students full degree programs online. The company was founded by social entrepreneur,
  &lt;a href="http://www.RandyBest.com" onclick="linkClick(this.href)" title="Randy Best"&gt;
   Randy Best
  &lt;/a&gt;
  , an 18-year veteran of developing innovative learning experiences to improve education. Academic Partnerships helps universities increase access by taking quality of a public university to scale. It provides the technology, marketing, student recruitment and faculty support necessary to serve online students. Academic Partnerships is guided by the principle that the opportunities presented through distance learning make higher education more accessible and achievable for students in the U.S. and globally. For more information, please visit
  &lt;a href="http://www.academicpartnerships.com" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://www.academicpartnerships.com
  &lt;/a&gt;
  .
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>PRWeb</pub_title>
  <document_url>http://www.prweb.com/releases/2012/11/prweb10100498.htm</document_url>
  <author></author>
  <abstract>Will explore new tools and the characteristics that makeup effective online learning technologies</abstract>
  <title>Academic Partnerships Hosts 3-Week Micro-MOOC on Engaging Technology and Online Pedagogy</title>
  <database>PRWeb</database>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>November 06, 2012</pub_date>
  <document_id>prweb-10100498</document_id>
  <source>Group SJR</source>
</DOCUMENT>
