<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>PRWeb</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="fullWidth floatLeft dottedTop"&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  What:     Join Academic Partnerships’
  &lt;a href="http://www.facultyecommons.com/" onclick="linkClick(this.href)" title="Faculty eCommons"&gt;
   Faculty eCommons
  &lt;/a&gt;
  for a roundtable webinar with open education pioneers
  &lt;a href="http://davidwiley.org/" onclick="linkClick(this.href)" title="David Wiley"&gt;
   David Wiley
  &lt;/a&gt;
  and
  &lt;a href="http://blog.elearning.sbctc.edu/" onclick="linkClick(this.href)" title="Cable Green"&gt;
   Cable Green
  &lt;/a&gt;
  as they discuss Open Education Resources (OER) that develop and enrich an educator’s instruction. They will review Creative Commons License and share how to access the most effective and reliable instructional resources.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  This roundtable is part of an ongoing micro-MOOC series organized by Faculty eCommons, a social learning community site to support faculty across the globe with resources to work together and enhance online education.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  When:         December 14, 12 at 1:30 PM CST
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Where:     Free registration
  &lt;a href="http://facultyecommons.com/learning-open-educational-resources-loer12-micro-mooc/" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://facultyecommons.com/learning-open-educational-resources-loer12-micro-mooc/
  &lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Who:     David Wiley, Associate Professor of Instructional Psychology and Technology at Brigham Young University
  Dr. David Wiley is Associate Professor of Instructional Psychology and Technology at Brigham Young University, where he also leads the Access to Knowledge Initiative in the David O. McKay School of Education's Center for the Improvement of Teacher Education and Schooling.
  David is founder and board member of the Open High School of Utah and Chief Openness Officer of Flat World Knowledge. David was formerly Associate Professor of Instructional Technology and Director of the Center for Open and Sustainable Learning at Utah State University. David is the Founder of OpenContent.org and was recently named one of the 100 Most Creative People in Business.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Cable Green, Director of Global Learning at Creative Commons
  As Director of Global Learning, Cable Green leads the Education projects at Creative Commons. He works with the global open community to leverage open licensing, open content, open policies, and the affordances of digital things to significantly improve access to quality, affordable, education and research resources. Previously, as Director of eLearning &amp;amp; Open Education for the Washington State Board for Community &amp;amp; Technical Colleges, he led a project to build and share highest enrolled courses under a CC BY license. They call it the “Open Course Library.”
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Faculty eCommons
  Developed by Academic Partnerships, Faculty eCommons is a social learning ecosystem for faculty across the globe to work together and better online education.  The site offers industry research, guidance, best practices, and professional development, with a focus on national quality standards.  Academic Partnerships has a strategic alliance with Sloan Consortium and a subscription to the Quality Matters™ program, which are available to AP Partner faculty.  For more information, visit:
  &lt;a href="http://facultyecommons.com" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://facultyecommons.com
  &lt;/a&gt;
  .
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Academic Partnerships
  Dallas-based Academic Partnerships partners with public universities to deliver students full degree programs online. The company was founded by social entrepreneur,
  &lt;a href="http://www.randybest.com/" onclick="linkClick(this.href)" title="Randy Best"&gt;
   Randy Best
  &lt;/a&gt;
  , an 18-year veteran of developing innovative learning experiences to improve education. Academic Partnerships helps universities increase access by taking quality of a public university to scale. It provides the technology, marketing, student recruitment and faculty support necessary to serve online students. Academic Partnerships is guided by the principle that the opportunities presented through distance learning make higher education more accessible and achievable for students in the U.S. and globally. For more information, please visit
  &lt;a href="http://www.academicpartnerships.com" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   http://www.academicpartnerships.com
  &lt;/a&gt;
  .
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  For more information contact: Sam Friedman, (646) 493-1105; ap(at)groupsjr(dot)com
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>PRWeb</pub_title>
  <document_url>http://www.prweb.com/releases/2012/12/prweb10209457.htm</document_url>
  <author></author>
  <abstract>Academic Partnerships’ Faculty eCommons host a roundtable webinar with open education pioneers David Wiley and Cable Green as they discuss Open Education Resources (OER)</abstract>
  <title>Academic Partnerships Hosts Open Education Resources (OER) Roundtable Webinar with Education Pioneers David Wiley and Cable Green</title>
  <database>PRWeb</database>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>December 06, 2012</pub_date>
  <document_id>prweb-10209457</document_id>
  <source>Email</source>
</DOCUMENT>
