<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>PRWeb</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="fullWidth floatLeft dottedTop"&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  &lt;a href="http://www.ace.edu" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   American College of Education,
  &lt;/a&gt;
  an accredited online college that provides online degree programs for educators, announces that it will offer a massive online open course (MOOC) on Digital Tools for the K-12 Classroom from May 6, 2013, to June 9, 2013.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  The free online course is designed primarily for K-12 educators and other professionals who want to implement current web-based tools in order to promote engagement. The course examines free web-based tools like Animoto, Glogster and Prezi as well as best practices for teacher-led and student-driven activities in the K-12 classroom.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  American College of Education’s Department of Digital Learning and Teaching Chair Dr. Catherine Dutton and Dr. Rebekah McPherson created the course to provide an open forum for educators to gather, discuss and explore online tools.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  The course is accessible to all professionals who want to keep pace with changes in technology, including those who may not have time for a traditional graduate course. “We have designed a course that encourages interaction and allows students opportunities to apply their knowledge, but the benchmarks for the course will not be graded assignments,” said Dr. Dutton. “We have designed the discussions to be areas where students can participate and truly discuss the topic. Whether you feel compelled to contribute or you just want to listen, that’s perfectly fine!”
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Previously, Dr. Dutton taught high school in Dallas and Lewisville, Texas, and was the Manager of Instructional Technology at Texas Woman’s University. Dr. McPherson is a Texas certified Master Technology Teacher and has taught for six years at the middle school and high school levels in addition to two years of university experience.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  Enrollment is limited through the Canvas online learning platform, so students are encouraged to sign up as soon as possible. Enrolled students also may access the course through Canvas’s mobile app.
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
  To learn more or to sign up for the course, please visit
  &lt;a href="https://www.canvas.net/courses/digital-tools-for-the-k-12-classroom" onclick="linkClick(this.href)"&gt;
   https://www.canvas.net/courses/digital-tools-for-the-k-12-classroom
  &lt;/a&gt;
  .
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>PRWeb</pub_title>
  <document_url>http://www.prweb.com/releases/2013/4/prweb10639022.htm</document_url>
  <author></author>
  <abstract>Online college offers free course on web-based technology for educators.</abstract>
  <title>American College of Education Announces Digital Tools for the K-12 Classroom Online Course</title>
  <database>PRWeb</database>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>April 18, 2013</pub_date>
  <document_id>prweb-10639022</document_id>
  <source>American College of Education</source>
</DOCUMENT>
