Download imageNEW <LOCATION>DELHI</LOCATION>,February 5, 2013/PRNewswire/ --<ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION> (www.sunstone.in) is the Leading Specialized Management School for Working Professionals in the IT/ITES Industry inDelhiand <LOCATION>Pune</LOCATION> RegionDelivering on its commitment of creating business leaders for a tech-centric world, <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION>, released the placement report of its founding batch that graduated inJuly 2012. The students received thumbs up from the industry with offers in Product Management, Consulting, <ORGANIZATION>General Management</ORGANIZATION>, Business Development roles. The salary offered was in the range of Rs. 22 Lacs - Rs. 51 Lacs per annum.(Logo:http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20130124/586283)"21 students graduated from <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone</ORGANIZATION> founding batch. Among those who have changed jobs or even internal promotion, there has been a significant increase in compensation (ranging from 50% - 100%), but more importantly, they have been able to switch to business-centric roles and are likely to get more and more interesting roles from here on. Median would be about 25L annual CTC as an output," said Mr.<PERSON>Rajul Garg</PERSON>, Director, <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION>.<ORGANIZATION>Sunstone</ORGANIZATION> students have gotten into several companies large and small with recruiters such as Adobe, Times, <ORGANIZATION>Expedia</ORGANIZATION>, Opera Solutions, <ORGANIZATION>Bharti SoftBank</ORGANIZATION>, Citrus Payments, and Mountain Apollo. Few students have switched from technical roles to strategy and client facing roles within their companies such as TCS and <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>. Four of the students chose to become entrepreneurs and are currently focusing on their ventures."Given that our program is for working professionals, they are generally more discerning about the kind of opportunities they get into. When you go to a campus program and have an <ORGANIZATION>EMI</ORGANIZATION> to pay, you try to get a job, any job by the end of it. In our case, our students only switch if they find something that changes their career trajectory. We are very excited to see our students joining business-centric roles in Venture Capital, Consumer, Enterprise product and professional consulting companies," added Mr. <PERSON>Garg</PERSON>.<ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION> runs a formal <ORGANIZATION>Career Counseling Cell</ORGANIZATION> headed byMrityunjay <PERSON>Kumar</PERSON>, which focuses on individual's career path after <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone</ORGANIZATION>. "Our small batch size allows us to focus on individual needs of students and help them transition from delivery centric roles to business roles. I am proud of the Sunstone offering that is providing opportunity and education to IT/ITES professionals to take up C level positions in the industry," saidMrityunjay <PERSON>Kumar</PERSON>.One of the students,<PERSON>Aditya Chaturvediwho</PERSON> took up the role of Group <ORGANIZATION>CTO</ORGANIZATION> at a Venture Capital firm after leaving his delivery role in an IT company says, "Transitioning from a technology role to a business role requires a huge mindset shift. The emphasis of the program on real business problem solving skills and one-on-one mentoring from industry leaders helped me get the right opportunity."To know more about 1-year Program in Management by <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone</ORGANIZATION>:http://sunstone.in/management-program/sunstone-business-school/program-details/For more info, write tocontactus@sunstone.in.About <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION>:<ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION> (www.sunstone.in) is the leading specialized Management School for working professionals in the IT/ITES industry in <LOCATION>Delhi</LOCATION> andPune. <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone</ORGANIZATION>'s 1-year Post Graduate Program in Management has gained recognition as a premier management program accepted by the industry. The school's problem-based pedagogy involves some top notch faculty fromHarvard, <ORGANIZATION>McKinsey</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>BCG</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>INSEAD</LOCATION>, and offers students a robust grounding in business strategies and implementation. Since its inception 2 years back, it is running small batches (30-40) of high quality professionals and has completely restructured management education by using Problem Based Pedagogy.Primary Media Contact:Dinesh Singh,dinesh@sunstone.in, 91-9871743222Secondary Media Contact: <PERSON>Paras</PERSON> Gupta,paras@sunstone.in, 91-9873805309SOURCE <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION>