Download imageCHARLOTTESVILLE, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>,Feb. 28, 2012/PRNewswire-USNewswire/ -- The <ORGANIZATION>Darden School</ORGANIZATION> is the only business school in the world to be in the top 20th percentile of MBA graduate satisfaction in teaching quality for 24 consecutive years, according to a new study published on24 February 2012by the MBA websitePoets andamp; Quants.(Logo:http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20100916/DC66431LOGO)The study is based on theBusinessWeek(nowBloomberg <ORGANIZATION>Businessweek</ORGANIZATION>) satisfaction surveys of more than 83,000 MBA graduates since 1988. <PERSON>Darden</PERSON> leads the storyBusiness Schools With the Best MBA Teaching <PERSON>FacultybyJohn Byrne</PERSON>, who launchedBusinessWeek's groundbreaking rankings of business schools in the 1980s."Only one school of all those surveyed over that 24-year span has scored in the top 20th percentile of teaching grades from graduating MBAs: the <ORGANIZATION>Darden School</ORGANIZATION>," wrote <PERSON>Byrne</PERSON>. "It is an extraordinary feat achieved through the ups and downs of economic cycles, ever-rising expectations and changing student attitudes."<PERSON>Byrne</PERSON>'s companion articleDarden: Where Great Teachers Are Godsgoes inside the classroom of <PERSON>Darden</PERSON> ProfessorYiorgos Allayannisfor a discussion of the <ORGANIZATION>Darden Business Publishing</ORGANIZATION> case study "The Weekend That Changed Wall Street," about the bankruptcy of <ORGANIZATION>Lehman Brothers</ORGANIZATION>. An abbreviated article about <PERSON>Allayannis</PERSON> in the classroom, also written by <PERSON>Byrne</PERSON>, appears in <LOCATION>Fortune.com</LOCATION> and CNNMoney entitled "What Makes a Master B-School Professor?"To describe <PERSON>Allayannis</PERSON>' energy in the classroom, <PERSON>Byrne</PERSON> wrote, "The 46-year-old, Greek-born professor É moves around like a human tornado, whirling this way and that, up and down the tiered steps in the center of the class, waving his arms in the air, raising and lowering his voice as if an actor on a stage."Dean <PERSON>Bob Bruner</PERSON>, in his 30th year on the <PERSON>Darden</PERSON> faculty said, "We take pride in being the world's best teaching school for graduate management education. Using the triathlete as a model, we recruit faculty who teach, research and develop the curriculum."The Darden experience, which receives the highest marks in student satisfaction, develops principled and complete leaders through its distinctive combination of top-ranked faculty, the case study method and a tight-knit learning environment.<PERSON>Byrne</PERSON> worked as editor-in-chief of BusinessWeek.com, executive editor ofBusinessWeekand editor-in-chief ofFast Companybefore launching the MBA website Poets andamp; Quants, which forms part of <PERSON>Byrne</PERSON>'s digital media company <ORGANIZATION>C-Change Media Inc</ORGANIZATION>. Poets andamp; Quants articles are featured regularly on Fortune.com and CNNMoney.For questions or information, contactcommunication@darden.virginia.eduor a member of theCommunication team.SOURCEUniversity of <ORGANIZATION>VirginiaDarden School</ORGANIZATION> of BusinessRELATED LINKShttp://www.darden.virginia.edu