Download imageCHARLOTTESVILLE, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>,Feb. 11, 2011/PRNewswire-USNewswire/ -- <ORGANIZATION>TheUniversity of VirginiaDarden School of Business</ORGANIZATION> and the Ê<ORGANIZATION>Darden School Foundation</ORGANIZATION> announced the appointment of <PERSON>Trip Davis</PERSON> as Êpresident of the foundation and senior associate dean for external Êrelations.(Logo:http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20100916/DC66431LOGO)<PERSON>Davis</PERSON>, age 43, will lead the <ORGANIZATION>Darden School</ORGANIZATION>'s external relations activities and will oversee core functions of the <ORGANIZATION>Darden School Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, including development, alumni affairs, communication and marketing, <PERSON>Darden</PERSON> Executive Education and hospitality.<ORGANIZATION>Egon Zehnder International</ORGANIZATION> conducted a national search and worked Êclosely with a search committee, comprised of faculty, staff and Êtrustees. The search yielded over 100 nominees and four finalists -- three of these finalists did extensive on-Grounds interviews at <PERSON>Darden</PERSON>."We are confident that in Trip we have found a dynamic and experienced Êleader who will energize the School's mission to improve society and Êfurther elevate <PERSON>Darden</PERSON>'s reputation among the world's leading business Êschools," said <PERSON>Darden</PERSON>'sDean <PERSON>Bob Bruner</PERSON>.<PERSON>Henry Skelsey</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Darden School Foundation Board of Trustees</ORGANIZATION>, emphasizes <PERSON>Davis</PERSON>' track record of innovation. "Trip is a Êrecognized entrepreneur and general manager who built two highly successful companies from the ground up," said <PERSON>Skelsey</PERSON>. "He is skilled at managing complex organizations in a global world, and his leadership will be pivotal in meeting <PERSON>Darden</PERSON>'s vision for world-class impact and stature."<PERSON>Davis</PERSON> co-founded and served as CEO and chairman of TRX, a global leader in travel technology and data services. He led the company from start-up in 1999 to$118 millionin revenue and an IPO in 2005. TRX processes Êtravel transaction data from over 400 sources in 50 countries and employs 800 people inthe <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,<LOCATION>United Kingdom</LOCATION>,GermanyandIndia.Prior to TRX, <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> was senior vice president and general manager of the <ORGANIZATION>Travel Industry Practice Group</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>iXL</ORGANIZATION>, and CEO and co-founder of <ORGANIZATION>Green ÊRoom Productions</ORGANIZATION>, an Internet travel services company, which he sold to ÊiXL in 1998. Before starting <ORGANIZATION>Green Room</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> worked in new ventures Êfor <ORGANIZATION>The Travel Channel at Landmark Communications</ORGANIZATION>. Prior to entering the MBA program at <PERSON>Darden</PERSON> in 1992, he worked as an associate producer for Ê<ORGANIZATION>ESPN</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Jobson Sailing</PERSON>, covering the <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s Cup.<PERSON>Davis</PERSON> has served as an adjunct faculty member at <PERSON>Darden</PERSON> and <LOCATION>U.Va.</LOCATION>'s Ê<ORGANIZATION>McIntire School of Commerce</ORGANIZATION>, lecturing on such topics as Êentrepreneurship, financing new ventures and operations. He has Êco-authored several <ORGANIZATION>Darden Business Publishing</ORGANIZATION> case studies and, since 2009, has served as co-faculty director of <PERSON>McIntire</PERSON>'s Galant Center for ÊEntrepreneurship, where he worked with donors, faculty and Êadministration to create the Entrepreneurship Track curriculum for Êfourth-year students.<PERSON>Davis</PERSON> earned a B.A. in English fromDartmouthin 1990 and an MBA from Êthe <ORGANIZATION>Darden School of Business</ORGANIZATION> in 1994. He and his wife, <PERSON>Nicol</PERSON>, have Êthree children. He is a triathlete, marathon runner and competitive sailor.To learn more, contactcommunication@darden.virginia.eduor a member of Êthe Communication Team.This news release was issued on behalf of Newswise(TM). For more information, visithttp://www.newswise.com.SOURCEUniversity of <ORGANIZATION>VirginiaDarden School of Business</ORGANIZATION>