<LOCATION>ST. PETERSBURG</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>,Feb. 14, 2013/PRNewswire-USNewswire/ -- The <ORGANIZATION>Poynter Institute's News University</ORGANIZATION> (https://www.newsu.org) announced today it has teamed up with the <ORGANIZATION>National Sexual Violence Resource Center</ORGANIZATION> (http://nsvrc.org) to create a free, self-directed course for journalists, educators and the public on how to cover the complex topic of sexual violence. The course will help journalists go beyond conventional reporting to help audiences learn more about the reality of sexual violence, and will help them cover the topic with context, accuracy and sensitivity."Statistics show that twenty percent of the population will experience sexual violence during their lifetime," saidTracy <ORGANIZATION>Cox</ORGANIZATION>, communications director, <ORGANIZATION>National Sexual Violence Resource Center</ORGANIZATION>. "With numbers that high, it's imperative that journalists, journalism students and educators have a clear and accurate understanding of sexual violence, where to obtain credible information and how to help news consumers understand its impact."The free massive online open course (or MOOC), called "Reporting on Sexual Violence,"https://www.newsu.org/courses/reporting-sexual-violencewill teach journalists how to report on sexual violence in a factual, trustworthy manner; how to generate story ideas that go beyond crime reports; and how to help audiences understand the impact of sexual violence and engage them in prevention efforts. Participants will also obtain facts and statistics about sexual violence, such types of abuse, who is affected and forms of vulnerability and victimization. They will learn the role that video, photographs and audio play in telling stories about sexual violence, as well as how to eliminate bias from reporting and dispel commonly-held myths on the topic."We are delighted to be working with <ORGANIZATION>NSVRC</ORGANIZATION> to offer this valuable training," saidVicki <PERSON>Krueger</PERSON>, director of interactive learning at <ORGANIZATION>The Poynter Institute</ORGANIZATION>. "It's an exciting opportunity for Poynter to use its e-learning platform on NewsU to help journalists, educators and anyone interested in this timely topic.""Reporting on Sexual Violence"https://www.newsu.org/courses/reporting-sexual-violenceis the latest Massive Online Open Course (or MOOC) available at <LOCATION>Poynter</LOCATION>'s NewsU and is funded by a grant from <ORGANIZATION>NSVRC</ORGANIZATION>. The course takes two to three hours to complete and participants can work through it on their own schedules. For more information on this course, please visithttps://www.newsu.org/courses/reporting-sexual-violence.About Poynter's News UniversityPoynter's <ORGANIZATION>News University</ORGANIZATION> (http://www.newsu.org) offers the world's largest online journalism curriculum, with more than 250 interactive courses and 240,000 students in 225 countries.The <ORGANIZATION>Poynter Institute for Media Studies</ORGANIZATION> is an international leader in journalism education, and a strategy center that stands for uncompromising excellence in journalism, media and 21st century public discourse. <PERSON>Poynter</PERSON> faculty teach at seminars and workshops at the Institute inSt. <PERSON>Petersburg</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, and at conferences and organizational sites around the world. The Institute's website,Poynter.org(http://www.poynter.org),Êproduces 24-hour coverage of news about media, ethics, technology, the business of news and the trends that currently define and redefine journalism news reporting. The world's top journalists and media innovators come to <LOCATION>Poynter</LOCATION> to learn Ð and to teach new generations of reporters, storytellers, media inventors, designers, visual journalists, documentarians and broadcast producers, and to build public awareness about journalism, media and the First Amendment-protected discourse that ensures public good and the democracy that serves it.About the National Sexual Violence Resource CenterFounded by the <ORGANIZATION>Pennsylvania Coalition Against Rape</ORGANIZATION> in 2000, the <ORGANIZATION>National Sexual Violence Resource Center</ORGANIZATION> (NSVRC) (http://www.nsvrc.org/) identifies, develops and disseminates resources regarding all aspects of sexual violence prevention and intervention. NSVRC activities include training and technical assistance, referrals, consultation, systems advocacy, resource library, capacity-building, integrating research findings with community-based projects, coordinating Sexual Assault Awareness Monthco-sponsoring national conferences and events, and creating web-based and social networking resources.<PERSON>CONTACTVicki Krueger</PERSON>, Director, Interactive Learning, The Poynter Institutevkrueger@poynter.org, 727-821-9494Jessica <PERSON>Blais</PERSON>, Director of Marketing, The Poynter Institutejblais@poynter.org, 727-821-9494Tracy <ORGANIZATION>Cox</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Director of Communications</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>National Sexual Violence Resource Center</ORGANIZATION> (NSVRC)tcox@nsvrc.orgSOURCE  Poynter's News University