Download imageDownload imageWESTLAKE VILLAGE, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>,June 15, 2012/PRNewswire-USNewswire/ --Ê"Dr.<PERSON>Bernard Luskin</PERSON>, Professor of <ORGANIZATION>Media Psychology</ORGANIZATION> and Family Therapy, Senior Provost and CEO forTouro UniversityWorldwide has been chosen President Elect for the Media Psychology Division of the <ORGANIZATION>American Psychological Association</ORGANIZATION>," announced Dr.<PERSON>Mary Alvord</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Elections Committee Chair</ORGANIZATION>.(Photo:http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20120615/DC25539)(Logo:http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20111123/DC12194LOGO)"Dr. <PERSON>Luskin</PERSON> has an exceptional history as an administrator, educator and leader in media psychology.<PERSON>Bernie Luskinhas</PERSON> made many contributions and pioneered new programs," said Dr.<PERSON>Judith Kuipers</PERSON>, President Emeritus of Fielding Graduate University. "While at FGU, <PERSON>Bernie</PERSON> developed and launched the first MA Ph.D. program in Media Psychology and EdD program in Media Studies in any university. Partnering with <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> Extension, he launched a successful Master's degree program in Media Psychology and Social Change, and atTouro UniversityWorldwide he launched an MA degree program in Media and Communications Psychology," said <PERSON>Kuipers</PERSON>."In 1998, with Dr.<PERSON>Lilli Friedland</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bernie</PERSON> co-directed a major study on behalf of the <ORGANIZATION>Media Psychology Division</ORGANIZATION> entitledMedia Psychology and <ORGANIZATION>New Technologies</ORGANIZATION>, a major milestone in shaping this field. He writes a frequent Blog for Psychology Today Magazine called 'The Media Psychology Effect,' and continues to prolifically write and produce diverse media applications," explained Dr.<PERSON>Toni Luskin</PERSON>, Professor of Media Psychology at TUW."<PERSON>Bernie Luskinhas</PERSON> pioneered media psychology where ever he has been," saidGlenn <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, CEO ofJones International, <ORGANIZATION>Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, and founder ofJones <ORGANIZATION>International University</ORGANIZATION>. "While at <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bernie</PERSON> was central to the launch ofJones <ORGANIZATION>International University</ORGANIZATION>, the first accredited fully online university. In addition, we pioneered <ORGANIZATION>Mind Extension University</ORGANIZATION>, a precursor for many of the online university programs of today, including what are now being called emerging MOOC strategies," added <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>.Author of ten books, many films, television series and CDs, Dr. <PERSON>Luskin</PERSON> won two Emmys from the <ORGANIZATION>Academy of Television Arts and Sciences</ORGANIZATION>, served as Chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>American Association of Community Colleges</ORGANIZATION>, president <ORGANIZATION>ofOrange Coast College</ORGANIZATION>,<ORGANIZATION>Coastline Community College</ORGANIZATION>, and CEO of <ORGANIZATION>Philips Interactive Media, Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, where he pioneered digital media in the private sector."A licensed marriage and family therapist and school psychologist, <PERSON>Bernie</PERSON> and I are now working within the <ORGANIZATION>American Association of Marriage and Family Therapy</ORGANIZATION> to foster application of theories in media psychology in improving global understanding of family issues such as ADD, Obesity, Autism, Depression, PTSD, Addictions and other social concerns facing society," saidScott <PERSON>Sobel</PERSON>, President of <ORGANIZATION>Media and Communications Strategies, Inc.</ORGANIZATION>In addition to his lifetime achievement recognition by the <ORGANIZATION>APA Media Psychology Division</ORGANIZATION>, Dr. <PERSON>Luskin</PERSON> has received lifetime achievement awards from the <ORGANIZATION>UCLA Doctoral Alumni Association</ORGANIZATION>,<ORGANIZATION>University of Florida</ORGANIZATION>,<ORGANIZATION>California State University</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>,<ORGANIZATION>Long Beach City College</ORGANIZATION>, the Irish Government and <ORGANIZATION>European Commission</ORGANIZATION>."I look forward to continuing to contribute as President and Member of the Board of Directors of the <ORGANIZATION>APA Media Psychology</ORGANIZATION> Division. Media Psychology is a 21st century specialization whose time is now," said Dr. <PERSON>Luskin</PERSON>.To discuss a program or find out how you can apply or participate in programs atTouro UniversityWorldwide, please contact:<PERSON>Heather Grace Hoglund</PERSON>, Director of Enrollment Management 818-874-4121,Heather.Hoglund@tuw.eduMatteo <PERSON>Indelicato</PERSON>, Senior Program Advisor 818-874-4118,Matteo.Indelicato@tuw.eduTouro UniversityWorldwide (TUW)TUW presently offers online Master's Degree Programs in Business (MBA), Industrial and <ORGANIZATION>Organizational Psychology</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Media and Communications Psychology</ORGANIZATION>, Physician Assistant, and Marriage and Family Therapy.Ê For program and enrollment information, visit:www.TUW.edu.About theTouro <ORGANIZATION>Collegeand University</ORGANIZATION> SystemTourois a system of non-profit institutions of higher and professional education.Touro Collegewas chartered in 1970 primarily to enrich the Jewish heritage, and to serve the larger American and global community. Approximately 19,000 students are currently enrolled in its various schools and divisions.Touro Collegehas branch campuses, locations and instructional sites in theNew Yorkarea, as well as branch campuses and programs inBerlin,<LOCATION>Jerusalem</LOCATION>,<LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>,<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, andFlorida.<ORGANIZATION>Touro UniversityCalifornia</ORGANIZATION> and itsNevadabranch campus, as well asTouro <ORGANIZATION>UniversityLos Angeles</ORGANIZATION> and itsTouro UniversityWorldwide division is are members of theTouro <ORGANIZATION>Collegeand University System</ORGANIZATION>.Ê For further information onTouro College, please go to:http://www.touro.edu/media/SOURCETouro UniversityWorldwideRELATED LINKShttp://www.TUW.edu