<LOCATION>LOS ANGELES</LOCATION>, Dec.Ê28, 2012 /PRNewswire-USNewswire/ --ÊLeaders in online education initiatives will convene atUCLAonJanuary 8, 2013, to bring awareness and discuss key issues regarding the potential for online education to lower costs and improve higher education inCalifornia. The conference is sponsored by the 20 <ORGANIZATION>Million Minds Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, a non-profit dedicated to lowering the cost of higher education.Themed "Rebooting Higher Education: Leveraging Innovations in Online Education to Improve Cost Effectiveness and Increase Quality," the event will bring together participants from key sectors, including: <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> President proTem <PERSON>Darrell Steinberg</PERSON>; Lt. Gov.<PERSON>Gavin Newsom</PERSON>;<PERSON>Sebastian Thrun</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Udacity</LOCATION>;<PERSON>Burck Smith</PERSON>, StraighterLine;<PERSON>Candace Thille</PERSON>, Open Learning Initiative; andmore. Other key panelists will include students, policymakers, faculty and members of the Academic <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> from the UC, <ORGANIZATION>CSU</ORGANIZATION> and community college systems. The conference will be webcast live onJanuary 8that20mm.organd will feature a special introduction bySalman Khan, innovative educator and founder of <ORGANIZATION>Khan Academy</ORGANIZATION>, a free online education platform and nonprofit serving over 6 million students per month.Conference panelists will center on the crisis the <ORGANIZATION>Golden State</ORGANIZATION> is facing in its ability to fully support public higher education. Follow-up discussions will focus on how online education and the associative technologies would enable the improvement of and access to academic programs inCalifornia.GovernorJerry Brownrecently highlighted the state's education crisis and the need for arresting the cost of education while maintaining or even increasing quality.Ê He asked theUniversity of CaliforniaRegents to invite leaders in free online education to share ways UC can more aggressively get into the digital classroom.There has been a significant increase in investment and funding for new educational delivery models in the past few years, with much of the innovation originating inCalifornia. One of the effects of this new-found interest in online education and educational technology is a new opportunity to talk about how these innovations can be brought to bear on the cost effectiveness problem. By enlisting active participation from educators, faculty, and providers, participants attending the conference can assist in accelerating efforts to take advantage of the cost-saving potential inherent in online education while maintaining or improving the quality of education thatCalifornia's institutions have been providing to students.*Individuals can sign up for Webcast at20mm.org inviteand participate by submitting live tweets @20mmReboot or using hashtag #20mmRebootCONTACT:<PERSON>Mayra Lombera</PERSON>(626) 396-7071SOURCE  20 Million Minds FoundationRELATED LINKShttp://www.20mm.org