On heels of <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION> announcement re-inventing textbooks, <ORGANIZATION>Assemblyand Senate</ORGANIZATION> examine potential for open-source books to cut costsSACRAMENTO, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>,Jan. 31, 2012/PRNewswire-USNewswire/ -- The following is being released by the 20 Million Minds Foundation:The <ORGANIZATION>California Joint Legislative Audit Committee</ORGANIZATION> (JLAC), chaired by Assembly Member <PERSON>Ricardo Lara</PERSON> (D –Bell Gardens), will hold a hearing Wednesday to investigate the high cost of college textbooks and the potential for e-textbooks to cut costs and increase access to higher education.Textbook prices have spiraled out of control over the last four years, at four times the rate of inflation. The average annual cost for college textbooks is now$1,260.  At <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s community colleges, attended by more than 2.8 million students, textbook costs make up 75 percent of total student expenditures.  On average, publishers release a new edition every three years, with each one costing 12 percent more than the last.State AuditorElaine Howlewill present an audit report on the affordability of college textbooks, followed by testimony from representatives ofCalifornia's three public systems of higher education, <ORGANIZATION>Academic Senate</ORGANIZATION> presidents, <LOCATION>Cal PIRG</LOCATION>, publishers and non-profit foundations."We want to explore whatCalifornia's three public higher education systems have done to help students with these unmanageable book costs since the report was issued 900 days ago," said JLAC Chair <PERSON>Lara</PERSON>.  "The state auditor's report strongly suggested new education technology solutions as a way to lower the cost, and we are hitting the 'refresh button' to let students know we have not forgotten about them."Non-profit 20 Million Minds Foundation has been working on making college more affordable by lowering the cost of textbooks and recently unveiled an "open source" Collaborative Statistics e-textbook, available at Kno.com, which is free and available to professors to adopt, providing students with an interactive experience using videos, applets, graphics, exercises and a variety of navigation and enhancement features."Californiacan do better by offering our students quality, free and open access to college textbooks," saidDean <PERSON>Florez</PERSON>, president of 20 <ORGANIZATION>Million Minds Foundation</ORGANIZATION> and a past <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Majority Leader inCalifornia.  "It is unacceptable that students are dropping out of class because they can't afford a textbook.  This hearing comes at a time when students are wondering whether legislators are even aware of the high costs of textbooks.  It is a hearing long overdue."The State Auditor's report can be found at:http://www.bsa.ca.gov/pdfs/reports/2007-116.pdf.What: Joint <ORGANIZATION>Legislative Audit Committee Hearing</ORGANIZATION> on Textbook CostsWhen:  Wednesday, February 1, 2012;2-5 p.m.Where: <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> State Capitol, Room 444,<LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>, CACONTACT: <PERSON>Beryl Chong</PERSON>, 775-682-0152SOURCE  The 20 Million Minds FoundationRELATED LINKSwww.20MM.ORG