Textbook savings measure for students landson GovernorJerry <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>'s DeskSACRAMENTO, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>,Aug. 31, 2012/PRNewswire-USNewswire/ -- Only a signature away, <PERSON>GovernorJerry Brownwill</PERSON> have an opportunity to lower the cost of college textbooks by creating the nation's first free open source digital library for college students and faculty.Today, the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> State Senate unanimously passed the first of its kind open educational resource digital library, or (OER), offering students free access to textbooks in the most commonly taken lower-division courses at public postsecondary institutions."At a time when the cost of attendingCalifornia's public colleges and universities is skyrocketing, relief is only a signature away as both SB 1052 and 1053 await <PERSON>GovernorJerry Brown</PERSON>'s signature," said20 Million MindsFoundation PresidentDean <PERSON>Florez</PERSON>. The foundation has been supportive of policy measures to create quality open source textbooks for college students throughout the nation. "This is the first time government has come in with substantial dollars that match philanthropic efforts to create a library where students can access free textbooks and faculty can utilize their skills to remix, revise and repurpose these textbooks for their students."Introduced by <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> President proTem <PERSON>Darrell Steinberg</PERSON>(D-Sacramento) in February, SB 1052 provides for the selection, development and administration of the free open digital textbooks for the most popular lower-division courses overseen by the establishment of the "California Open Education Resources Council" (COERC). <LOCATION>COERC</LOCATION>, established by the legislation, will be comprised of faculty members from theUniversity of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,<ORGANIZATION>California State Universityand Community Colleges</ORGANIZATION> to determine which courses merit inclusion.  Its companion bill, SB 1053, creates the California Open Source Digital Library to house the open source textbooks and courseware.The legislation creates a competitive "Request for Proposals" (RFP) process inviting faculty, publishers, and others to develop high quality digital open source textbooks and related courseware.  The materials would be placed under a "Creative Commons" licensing structure that would not only allow students and faculty free access, but would also allow instructors to create customized materials from the textbooks and other courseware.  To ensure the materials meet the rigorous standards of college core curricula, all material would be reviewed and approved by subject matter experts.20 Million Mindsis a non-profit organization dedicated to greatly reducing textbook costs. The foundation is currently leveraging leading-edge technologies to create more affordable, engaging and effective educational materials for college students throughout the nation. Visitwww.20mm.orgCONTACT:<PERSON>Beryl Chong</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Communications Director20 Million Minds Foundation</ORGANIZATION> 916.442.9300SOURCE  The 20 Million Minds FoundationRELATED LINKShttp://www.20mm.org