Download imageDELRAY BEACH, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>,April 1, 2013/PRNewswire/ -- <ORGANIZATION>Colloquy, Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a leading provider of global solutions for online higher education, announced today its participation in four upcoming conferences.(Logo:http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20130401/FL86281LOGO)"Right now, universities are in pursuit of the right strategy for online programs, distance education and what the MOOC phenomenon means to them as institutions," saidTim <PERSON>Gilbert</PERSON>, president. "Obstacles include tight budgets and thin staffing, which prevent them from doing the right planning and analysis, the marketing and recruiting, and the infrastructure to launch in a timely way."Colloquy is internationally recognized for its end-to-end "school as a service" offerings. It partners with institutions likeGeorge <ORGANIZATION>Mason University</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>University</ORGANIZATION> ofAdelaide, andCalifornia <ORGANIZATION>State University</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Monterey Bay</LOCATION> to strategize, launch, and operate graduate programs and other distance education offerings.At the Sloan-C <ORGANIZATION>Emerging Technologies for Online Learning Conference</ORGANIZATION> in April,<PERSON>Jennifer L. Scott</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Colloquy's</ORGANIZATION> vice president for academic and institutional services, will present "Putting Your Data to Work," discussing methods to translate your <ORGANIZATION>LMS</ORGANIZATION>, surveys, and other analytics data into practical improvements to course design. Ms. <PERSON>Scott</PERSON>'s presentation will include case studies on course set-up and user data, relevant to faculty or administrators overseeing multiple courses or sections.The four upcoming 2013 conferences are:UPCEA Annual Meeting inBoston, April 3–5AACSB - <ORGANIZATION>International Conference</ORGANIZATION> and Annual Meeting (ICAM) inChicago, April 7–9Sloan-C Emerging Technologies for Online Learning inLas Vegas, April 9–11Sloan-C Blended Learning Conference inMilwaukee, July 8–9About ColloquyColloquy, <ORGANIZATION>Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, is a leading provider of online education strategy, consulting, and delivery to higher education. Colloquy's solutions are designed to help institutional leaders execute their vision for online delivery of degrees.As a division of <ORGANIZATION>Kaplan, Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, part of <ORGANIZATION>The Washington Post</ORGANIZATION> (NYSE:WPO), Colloquy leverages  75 years of expertise in global education services. Colloquy offers the full range of resources and knowledge necessary to plan, execute, launch, and manage a total online experience both domestically and internationally.Using its proprietary Colloquy 360° Methodology, Colloquy applies a best-practices approach to market research, marketing and recruiting, curriculum design and development, learning management systems, and student success services.Visit us atwww.colloquy360.com.Averie ConnellBusiness Development ManagerColloquy, Inc.3333 <ORGANIZATION>S. Congress Ave.</ORGANIZATION>, Suite 100Delray Beach, <ORGANIZATION>FL33445561-381-6350SOURCE  Colloquy, Inc.</ORGANIZATION>RELATED LINKShttp://www.colloquy360.com