Download imagePALM SPRINGS, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>,Sept. 5, 2012/PRNewswire/ -- <ORGANIZATION>World Education University</ORGANIZATION> (pronounced "we-you"), the first tuition-free, global, online higher education institution designed to provide comprehensive course offerings and full degrees to students, today announced the signing of its initial academic leadership team. Joining <ORGANIZATION>WEU</ORGANIZATION>, which has originated the term "Education Should Be Free" (ESBF), are 10 faculty representing the positions of University President, <PERSON>Deans</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Schools of Medicine and Health</ORGANIZATION>, Education, Psychology, Engineering, Law, and Arts, and Directors of Curriculum, Education Design and Standards and Compliance. <ORGANIZATION>WEU</ORGANIZATION> executives are still in the process of recruiting a Dean for the School of Business.(Logo:http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20120905/CG68371LOGO)"We are honored to be welcoming this top-caliber group of higher education professionals to the <ORGANIZATION>WEU</ORGANIZATION> staff," saysCurtis <PERSON>Pickering</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>WEU</ORGANIZATION> Co-Founder and Chairman/CEO. "These individuals, established leaders and practitioners in both academia and private - sector worlds, share <ORGANIZATION>WEU</ORGANIZATION>'s dedication to transforming higher education to reflect a more inclusive, equitable environment. Among our faculty are experts in the high needs areas of STEM, differentiated learning, business entrepreneurship, management, and educational leadership who are poised to help students achieve a solid academic education that also includes mastery of the 21st century skills employers say are crucial to success in today's workplace."New faculty include:Dr.<PERSON>James Waddell</PERSON>– University President, Chief Academic OfficerDr.<PERSON>Jim Waddellholds</PERSON> aDoctor of Philosophy degree in Philosophical Theology from theUniversity of <LOCATION>Oxford</LOCATION>, is a Foundation Fellow ofHarris <ORGANIZATION>Manchester College</ORGANIZATION>,<ORGANIZATION>Oxford University</ORGANIZATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Fellow of the Royal Society</ORGANIZATION> for the <ORGANIZATION>Encouragement of Arts</ORGANIZATION>, Manufacturing, and Commerce. Dr. <PERSON>Waddell</PERSON> has taught atPrinceton, been president ofMenlo CollegeinCalifornia, and as president of the <ORGANIZATION>Waddell Group</ORGANIZATION>, assisted colleges, universities, and corporations in launching, developing, and expanding programs in management, humanities, and education.Dr.<PERSON>Sally Kilgore</PERSON>– Dean of the School of EducationDr.<PERSON>Sally Kilgoreis</PERSON> former Director of the Office of Research for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of Education</ORGANIZATION>, co-principal investigator of a <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> study of mathematics and science achievement, founder and former CEO of <ORGANIZATION>Modern Red School House</ORGANIZATION>, and author of the recent bookFrom Silos to Systems. She has served on the faculties of several universities, includingEmory University. Dr. <PERSON>Kilgore</PERSON> holds a doctorate in sociology from theUniversity of <LOCATION>Chicagoand</LOCATION> has an undergraduate degree fromBaylor University.Dr.<PERSON>Penny Orr</PERSON>– Dean of the School of PsychologyDr.<PERSON>Penny Orr</PERSON>'s extensive training and work in psychology, education, and creative fields has driven her to be a student-centered advocate and a creative innovator in developing programs that meet student needs while ensuring academic rigor. Dr. <PERSON>Orr</PERSON> is a registered and board certified Art Therapist, and Art Therapy Certified Supervisor and holds a Bachelor of Arts degree fromFurman University, a Master of Arts in Art Therapy from <ORGANIZATION>The School of the Arts Institute</ORGANIZATION> ofChicago, and a Ph.D. in Curriculum and Instruction fromPurdue University.<PERSON>Debra Rocha</PERSON>, <PERSON>J.D.</PERSON> – Dean of the School of LawDr.<PERSON>Debra Rochahas</PERSON> been on the faculty of several higher learning institutions, has instructed adult learners in undergraduate and graduate degree programs, authored over 400 online law related courses and developed 13 law related degree programs. Dr. <PERSON>Rocha</PERSON> holds aJuris <ORGANIZATION>Degreefrom American College Law</ORGANIZATION> with course work completed atSuffolk UniversityCollege of Law inBoston, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>. She also holds a Master of Science degree in Criminal Justice fromSalve <ORGANIZATION>Regina University</ORGANIZATION>, a Bachelor of Science degree in <ORGANIZATION>Administration of Justice</ORGANIZATION> and a Paralegal Certificate fromRoger <ORGANIZATION>Williams University</ORGANIZATION>. Dr. <PERSON>Rocha</PERSON> was also founding Dean of the CaliforniaSouthern UniversityCollege of Law.Dr.<PERSON>Vanessa Sheldon</PERSON>– Dean of the School of ArtsDr.<PERSON>Vanessa Sheldonis</PERSON> aninternationally-known practicing musician,on the faculty of several southernCaliforniacolleges, a member of the <ORGANIZATION>National Honor Society of Phi Kappa Phi</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Golden Key International Honour Society</ORGANIZATION>. Dr. <PERSON>Sheldon</PERSON> holds Bachelor's and Master's Degrees of Music in instrumental performance fromCalifornia <ORGANIZATION>State University</ORGANIZATION>(CSU)<LOCATION>Los Angelesand</LOCATION> a Doctorate of Musical Arts in harp and musicology from theUniversity of <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>.Dr.<PERSON>Philip Slocum</PERSON>– Dean of the <ORGANIZATION>School of Medicine</ORGANIZATION> and Health SciencesDr.<PERSON>Philip Slocum</PERSON>'s academic career spans more than three decades in both private and public medical schools, as both a faculty member and administrator. Dr. <PERSON>Slocum</PERSON> holds a Doctor of <ORGANIZATION>Osteopathic Medicine</ORGANIZATION> degree fromtheKirksville College of Osteopathic Medicine. His interest in the interface of the principles of higher education with the principles of medical education led him to complete theHarvard <ORGANIZATION>University</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Graduate School of Education's Management and Leadership in Education</ORGANIZATION> and the Institute of Educational Management programs. He is a recognized national leader in medical education, and noted for his critical views of the current state of health professions education and medical education.Dr.<PERSON>Goran Trajkovski</PERSON>- Dean of the School of EngineeringDr.<PERSON>Goran Trajkovskihas</PERSON> conceptualized, developed, and launched more than 25 undergraduate and graduate programs in a variety of engineering disciplines for online delivery, and led the development of close to 200 online courses for a variety of clients. Dr. <PERSON>Trajkovski</PERSON>'s research focuses on Theories of Learning, Cognitive and <ORGANIZATION>Developmental Robotics</ORGANIZATION>, and Emergent Phenomena in Multi-agent Societies. Dr. <PERSON>Trajkovski</PERSON> holds a BSc in Applied Informatics, MSc in Mathematical and <ORGANIZATION>Computer Sciences</ORGANIZATION>, and Doctorate in Technical Sciences (Computing Sciences) from the <ORGANIZATION>University Saints Cyril</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Methodius</ORGANIZATION> inSkopje, <LOCATION>Macedonia</LOCATION>.Dr.<PERSON>Nathan Church</PERSON>–Director of Curriculum Development and PedagogyDr.<PERSON>Nathan Churchhas</PERSON> over 37 years of experience in undergraduate, graduate and professional education as a faculty member, consultant and administrator. He has served as the Vice President and Chief Student Affairs Officer forSt. <ORGANIZATION>Cloud State University</ORGANIZATION>,<ORGANIZATION>Touro UniversityandSouthern California Universityof Health Sciences</ORGANIZATION>.  He also served as the Western Regional Vice President for Business Development and Operations for <ORGANIZATION>Collegiate Health Care</ORGANIZATION> (a management services company for health and counseling services in higher education) as well as the <ORGANIZATION>Director of Counseling and Health Services forWestern Washington University</ORGANIZATION>,<ORGANIZATION>Pepperdine Universityand College</ORGANIZATION> of the Desert.<PERSON>Kathleen Mirabile</PERSON>, <PERSON>J.D.</PERSON> – Director of Standards and ComplianceDr.<PERSON>Kathleen Mirabilehas</PERSON> 12 years of executive and operations experience in the distance-learning field and has been a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Distance Education and Training Council Research and Educational Standards Sub-Committee</ORGANIZATION> since 2003. Dr. <PERSON>Mirabile</PERSON> holds a Bachelor of Science degree from theUniversity of <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, a Master of Arts in Jurisprudence from <ORGANIZATION>Harrison Middleton University</ORGANIZATION> and an Executive <PERSON>Juris Doctor</PERSON> fromConcord UniversitySchool of Law. She is currently President and Chief Academic Officer ofBrightonCollege inScottsdale, <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>.Dr.<PERSON>Cici Remy</PERSON>- Director of Educational DesignDr.<PERSON>Cici Remyis</PERSON> a specialist in psychobiology and neuropsychology, focusing her medical research on how the mind learns and recalls memories. Dr. <PERSON>Remy</PERSON> graduated with honors from TheUniversity of Southern Californiawith an undergraduate degree in Psychobiology and received her Medical Degree fromMedical College of <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>. Dr. <PERSON>Remy</PERSON> has practiced medicine predominantly in the field of pediatrics, most recently with theUniversity of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, DavisMedical Group and is expanding her interests in learning and information processing as an advisory board member for an artificial intelligence program, as well as developing web based learning modules for medical providers.To see the full bios of the <ORGANIZATION>WEU</ORGANIZATION> academic leadership team, visitwww.theweu.com/Current-Faculty.html. <ORGANIZATION>WEU</ORGANIZATION> plans to launch in late fall 2012.<ORGANIZATION>About World Education UniversityWorld Education University</ORGANIZATION> represents a game-changing paradigm shift in the American and global education model by providing tuition-free education to all.  Aiming to be a comprehensive education ecosystem with programs from "Pre-K to <PERSON>Gray</PERSON>," <ORGANIZATION>WEU</ORGANIZATION> first seeks to be an accredited provider of high-quality, university degrees and credentials that are offered to anyone, anytime, anywhere.With the education system as we know it in crisis, high schools failing students in masses and post-secondary programs offering varying levels of instructional quality at extraordinarily high cost, the time is ripe for <ORGANIZATION>WEU</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>WEU</ORGANIZATION> brings a completely fresh perspective to the education model, building content and programs around the needs of learners and the industries that will eventually offer them jobs.We believe that free university programs and degrees will have massive worldwide appeal, breaking down traditional economic, geographic and cultural barriers for students domestically and internationally.Contacts:Sue Hanson:sue@susanhanson.comSusan McLester:susan@mclestercontent.comSOURCE  <ORGANIZATION>World Education University</ORGANIZATION>