Download imageAUSTIN, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>,Oct. 25, 2012/PRNewswire-iReach/ -- With theprice of solar down 80%andnew data provingthat solar can be a reliable and substantial source of power generation across the grid, <ORGANIZATION>Austin Energy</ORGANIZATION>'s new "Value of Solar Tariff" has solved a crucial policy and incentive conundrum and set the stage for explosive growth in distributed solar. Meet the man behind the miracle.(Photo:http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20121025/CG00793)OnNovember 1, 2012at6:00 p.m. CDTSolPowerPeople, <ORGANIZATION>Inc.</ORGANIZATION>welcomes Guest Lecturer:<PERSON>Karl Rabago</PERSON>, Principal, <ORGANIZATION>Rabago Energy LLC</ORGANIZATION>"Net Metering 2.0, the <ORGANIZATION>Value of Solar Tariff</ORGANIZATION>"This#SolarMOOClecture is free and open to all as part of the world's first solar "Massive Open Online Course" (currently providing free ongoing advanced solar training to more than1,500 participantsfromover 75 countries). To attend this much anticipated webinar for free, enroll in#SolarMOOC Academyand receive an invitation to this WebEx session via email.<PERSON>Karl Rabago</PERSON>, heralded as one of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> energy industry's most brilliant, dynamic personalities, establishedRabago Energy LLCinJune 2012when he left his position as Vice President of Distributed Energy Services with <ORGANIZATION>Austin Energy</ORGANIZATION>. His more than 20 years in the clean energy and electric utility fields include service asPublic Utility Commissionerand Deputy Assistant Secretary at theUS Department of Energy.Austinhas a maturing solar market that supports over76 companies and as many as 2,109 direct and indirect jobs, and has been declared byMayor <PERSON>Lee Leffingwellas</PERSON> the "Clean Energy Capital of the World".To sustain this reputation as a shining star,<PERSON>Austin Energyneeded</PERSON> a simple, manageable program, de-coupled from other market incentives, that was fair overall to the utility while reimbursing customers for their clean power production at a rate fair to it's value.Ê At the same time, this program needed to exist without burdening non-solar customers with bearing the brunt of the cost of maintaining the utility structure on their own. And, most importantly, it would need to reward conservation and efficiency, rather than encouraging higher consumption at peak times when the utility needs the excess power the most.Working with utility and government stakeholders,third party researchers, and members of the burgeoningAustinsolar community,<PERSON>Karl Rabagoand</PERSON> his staff devised and implemented the "Value of Solar" rate, coupled with a tiered electricity rate structure. This program dubbed "Net Metering 2.0" has captured the attention of solar policymakers all over the world, earning <ORGANIZATION>Austin EnergySEPA</ORGANIZATION>'s "Public Power Utility of the Year"inJune 2012, and anInnovation Awardfrom the <ORGANIZATION>Interstate Renewable Energy Council</ORGANIZATION> inSeptember 2012.Thisone-hour lecturewill review the history and challenges of traditional net metering, whereby utility customers "net" their production of solar energy against their energy consumption (often describes as "spinning the meter backwards"), and describe the premise and mechanics of the <ORGANIZATION>Austin Energy</ORGANIZATION>'s innovative new program.SinceMarch 2012, SolPowerPeople's#SolarMOOChas provided ongoing weekly webinars, social media forums, and advanced solar training including reading assignments, practice problems, and interactive study sessions for participants preparing for internationally-recognized credentialing tests, such as the NABCEP PV Installerª and PV Technical Salesª Certification Exams. The#SolarMOOC Guest Lecturer <PERSON>Directoryis</PERSON> a virtual "Who's Who" among solar training and technical experts.Ê The #SolarMOOCNewsletter Archivelinks to published newsletters that include a treasure trove of information, links to recorded lectures, and press releases.The#SolarMOOCis one of a broad spectrum of solar training and marketing services from <ORGANIZATION>SolPowerPeople, Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, anAustin, TX-based company that burst into the solar industry in 2011, led byCathy Redson,<PERSON>Richard Stovall</PERSON>,<PERSON>Ryan Doty</PERSON>, andSarah <PERSON>Raymer</PERSON>. With combined experience of over 50 years in solar, education, and business development, SolPowerPeople's mission is to lead the renewable energy revolution, fueling widespread global adoption of solar energy technology through industry creative collaboration, "in-market" andamp; online market development services, and comprehensive education offerings.Empower yourself, and be a part of theThird Industrial Revolutionby joining theSolPowerPeoplemovement today!Media Contact:<PERSON>Sarah Raymer</PERSON> SolPowerPeople, <ORGANIZATION>Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, 512-299-1299,sraymer@solpowerpeople.comNews distributed by PR Newswire iReach:https://ireach.prnewswire.comSOURCE  SolPowerPeople, Inc.RELATED LINKShttp://solpowerpeople.com