<LOCATION>NEW DELHI</LOCATION>,December 20, 2012/PRNewswire/ --<ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION> (www.sunstone.in) is the <ORGANIZATION>Leading Specialized Management School for Working Professionals inIndiaSunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION>, the leading specialized <ORGANIZATION>Management School</ORGANIZATION>, today announced the launch ofIndia'sfirst MOOC (Massive Open Online Course). By pushing boundaries as an educational innovator, <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION> is bringing a paradigm shift by enabling the professionals aspiring to grow to receive the finest and continuous management education inIndia. <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone</ORGANIZATION> aims to offer free online courses across all management disciplines."The mindset of professionals today is changing - it's no more about getting a degree or a certificate, but about enhancing knowledge, and personality. However, there is a dearth of quality courses that allow professionals to up skill or cross skill along with managing professional and family lives. We saw a huge need for quality online courses delivered by taking real world problems and imparting concepts in the course of solving them. We have already seen huge success of <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> such as <LOCATION>Coursera</LOCATION>, edX, Udacity with millions of students enrolled so far. The MOOC is our effort in bridging this gap by opening up the knowledge for larger community and building a continuous and a flexible learning environment inIndia. These courses aim to equip professionals with relevant tools and concepts to advance their careers, learn from the best in the business and develop a higher level of personal confidence," said Mr.<PERSON>Rajul Garg</PERSON>, Director, <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION>.<ORGANIZATION>Sunstone</ORGANIZATION> started delivering its courses sinceDecember 2012and did a soft launch with a 3-week course onNegotiations. More than 1,000 students have applied so far for the course from all acrossIndiaas well as internationally. Students are able to earn academic certificate as credentials for completing courses. Now, <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone</ORGANIZATION> is launching its next course onEntrepreneurshipinJanuary 2013and is already seeing a huge interest in enrollment.<ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business School Open Courses</ORGANIZATION> is the only MOOC delivering courses using problem based learning approach unlike others that rely on the traditional lecture-centric approach. The key to delivery of the <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION> is the learning management system and the various pedagogical elements such as videos, webinars, simulation exercises, situation analysis, and discussions. Sunstone Open Courses are unique as it continues to leverage technology and still provide peer-to-peer exchanges with a prominent focus on "do it yourself" philosophy. "When a student joins one of the courses, he/she also joins a community of thousands of participants with diverse experience that enables students to further learn and network with the peer group. InIndia, the concept of <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION> is very new and we believe it will bring a long lasting paradigm shift in management education inIndia," said Ms.<PERSON>Megha Khatri</PERSON>, Program Manager for Open Courses at <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION>.About <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business SchoolSunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION> (www.sunstone.in) is the leading specialized <ORGANIZATION>Management School</ORGANIZATION> forhigh quality working professionalsin the IT/ITES industry. <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone</ORGANIZATION>'s one year Post Graduate Program in Management has gained recognition as a premier program accepted by the industry globally. The school's problem based pedagogy offers students a robust grounding in business strategies and implementation.To know more about the MOOC, please write toopencourses@sunstone.inor visit:http://sunstone.in/management-program/open-courses/Primary Media Contact:Dinesh Singh,dinesh@sunstone.in, 91-9871743222Secondary Media Contact:Megha Khatri,megha.khatri@sunstone.in, 91-8800393805SOURCE <ORGANIZATION>Sunstone Business School</ORGANIZATION>