<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>PR Newswire</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="news-col topics"&gt;
 &lt;div&gt;
  &lt;a name="linktopagetop"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;div class="featured"&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;b&gt;
    &lt;i&gt;
     Platform would allow faculty to create textbooks from the largest OER repository in the US
    &lt;/i&gt;
   &lt;/b&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;span class="xn-location" itemprop="contentLocation" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Place"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="geo" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/address"&gt;
     &lt;span itemprop="addressLocality"&gt;
      SACRAMENTO, Calif.
     &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   , Oct. 15, 2012 /PRNewswire-USNewswire/ -- Today the
   &lt;a href="http://www.20mm.org/" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    20 Million Minds Foundation
   &lt;/a&gt;
   announced the launch of 20 Million Minds Mix (
   &lt;a href="http://20mmix.org/" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    20MMix.org
   &lt;/a&gt;
   ) -- a custom-textbook platform which allows faculty to remix, revise, and repurpose open content to deliver more affordable learning materials to students.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   Powered by AcademicPub, 20MMix fulfills the Open Educational Resources (OER) promise to provide instructors with the ability to access, revise, remix, repurpose, and deliver open content all in one place.  With over 5 million units of material available from the country's largest OER repository – Connexions – and over 140 academic publishers, educators can now create custom textbooks using the web, self-generated works, and the site's extensive library.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   The platform allows faculty to effortlessly search and select content from a variety of sources. With 20MMix textbooks can be quickly composed, priced, and directly delivered to students in digital or print formats. The added convenience of real-time copyright-clearance for web articles and self-generated works further streamlines the development of these custom textbooks.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   "Our foundation is dedicated to providing high-quality low cost materials for students, at the same time we recognize the importance of academic freedom," said
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Dean Florez
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   , former Senate Majority Leader and President of the 20 Million Minds Foundation. "20MMix gives faculty the ability to create custom low cost textbooks for their students, it's about putting  faculty back in the driver's seat and giving them control over the content."
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   In addition to giving faculty more control over course materials 20MMix hosts a live running total feature that allows instructors to track the cost of their book as it is being developed. "We strongly believe that giving educators a space that provides an abundance of resources and the flexibility for building low cost textbooks is the perfect recipe for making substantive change in the textbook industry," said
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Dean Florez
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   .
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;b&gt;
    &lt;i&gt;
     20 Million Minds
    &lt;/i&gt;
   &lt;/b&gt;
   &lt;i&gt;
    is a non-profit organization dedicated to greatly reducing textbook costs. The foundation is currently leveraging leading-edge technologies to create more affordable, engaging and effective educational materials for college students throughout the nation. Visit
    &lt;a href="http://www.20mm.org/" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
     www.20mm.org
    &lt;/a&gt;
    .
   &lt;/i&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;span&gt;
    CONTACT:
    &lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
     &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
      Mayra Lombera
     &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span&gt;
    20 Million Minds Foundation
    &lt;br/&gt;
    916.442.9300
   &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
   SOURCE  20 Million Minds Foundation
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
  RELATED LINKS
  &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href="http://www.20mm.org" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank" title="Link to http://www.20mm.org"&gt;
   http://www.20mm.org
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>PR Newswire</pub_title>
  <document_url>http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/foundation-introduces-custom-textbook-creation-platform-for-open-educational-resources-174140401.html</document_url>
  <author></author>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <title>Foundation Introduces Custom Textbook Creation Platform for Open Educational Resources</title>
  <database>PR Newswire</database>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>2012-10-15T03:24:00Z</pub_date>
  <document_id>prnewswire-174140401</document_id>
  <source>20 Million Minds Foundation</source>
</DOCUMENT>
