<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>PR Newswire</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="news-col topics"&gt;
 &lt;div&gt;
  &lt;a name="linktopagetop"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;div class="featured"&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;span class="xn-location" itemprop="contentLocation" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Place"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="geo" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/address"&gt;
     &lt;span itemprop="addressLocality"&gt;
      BOSTON
     &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   ,
   &lt;span class="xn-chron"&gt;
    Feb. 11, 2013
   &lt;/span&gt;
   /PRNewswire/ --
   &lt;a href="http://aquent.com/blog/aquent-heads-up-app-launches-for-talent-updates-on-the-go" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    Aquent
   &lt;/a&gt;
   , the leading global staffing organization dedicated to marketing, creative, and digital professionals, and its new division
   &lt;a href="http://vitamintalent.com/lp/how-can-we-help-you?src=GOOG-VT-NA-Brand-Vitamin+T-vitamin+t-Broad" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    Vitamin T
   &lt;/a&gt;
   , announced today that they have been named to Inavero's
   &lt;a href="http://www.bestofstaffing.com/" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    2013 Best of Staffing™ Talent
   &lt;/a&gt;
   list of award winners. The companies received the Best Job Candidate Experience honor for their exceptional service to digital, creative, and marketing professionals. This year's list highlights a growing divide among the staffing industry's leaders and laggards, identifying Aquent and Vitamin T the most effective agencies for candidate job placement.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   "As a talent-focused staffing company, we are so proud to win this award because we're always providing innovative ways to give our digital, creative, and marketing talent a great experience," said
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Ann Webster
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   , president of Aquent. "Last year, we became the first staffing agency to offer a massive online open course (MOOC), providing free HTML 5 training to all. But we didn't stop there; we created a mobile app with check-in and timecard functionality, increased our referral payouts and launched expert technical interviews for Front End Developers."
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   "At Vitamin T, we've found some creative ways for our talent to have fun while also growing their careers," Said
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Susie Hall
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   , President of Vitamin T. "We're happy to show our fantastic
   &lt;b&gt;
   &lt;/b&gt;
   talent how much we appreciate them by giving them a blog filled with useful content for digital creatives, fast access to our staff, and a social network with information and access to other creatives."
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   Less than one percent of all staffing agencies in
   &lt;span class="xn-location" itemprop="contentLocation" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Place"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="geo" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/address"&gt;
     &lt;span itemprop="addressLocality"&gt;
      North America
     &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   receive the Best of Staffing award for service excellence. Utilizing the Net Promoter® methodology, the 2013 Best of
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Staffing Talent
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   winners achieved satisfaction scores more than double the industry average. This stark contrast in scores is a clear indication that the firms who have earned their way onto the 2013 Best of
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Staffing Talent
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   list truly stand out for their service quality. Aquent received satisfaction ratings of 9 or 10 out of 10, from 73 percent of their permanent and temporary employees, significantly higher than the industry's average of 48 percent.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   "Few things are more important to companies than the employees you hire," said Inavero Founder and CEO
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Eric Gregg
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   . "The same holds true for candidates on their quest for employment. Staffing agencies have proven to successfully connect companies with permanent and temporary employees. Since the end of the recession, the staffing and recruiting industry has created more jobs than any other single industry in the country**, yet so many companies and job seekers don't take advantage of this expertise and resource. Our hope is that both companies and job candidates use the Best of Staffing lists as a benchmark to help select a staffing agency that can either secure the talent or employment opportunity they need."
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   ®Net Promoter, NPS, and Net Promoter Score are trademarks of Satmetrix Systems, Inc., Bain &amp;amp; Company, and
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Fred Reichheld
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   . Net Promoter Score is calculated by taking the percentage of respondents who, on a scale of 0 to 10, rate their likelihood to recommend the staffing agency with a score of 9 or 10 (promoters) and subtracting the percentage who rate the staffing agency a 6 or lower (detractors).
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   **Bureau of Labor Statistics
   &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;b&gt;
    About Aquent
    &lt;br/&gt;
   &lt;/b&gt;
   At its core, Aquent is about helping companies adapt to change, find new ways to work, and stay competitive. Aquent offers a broad range of services, including contract and contract-to-hire staffing to help global companies add technical expertise to their marketing and creative departments, increase the bandwidth of their in-house teams, and more. With a notable client list, generous benefits and training opportunities, Aquent attracts and places thousands of in-demand talent on assignment worldwide. To learn more about Aquent's full range of services, please visit:
   &lt;a href="http://aquent.com/" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    http://aquent.com/
   &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;b&gt;
    About Inavero
   &lt;/b&gt;
   &lt;br/&gt;
   &lt;a href="http://www.inavero.com/" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    Inavero
   &lt;/a&gt;
   administers more staffing agency client and talent satisfaction surveys than any other firm in the world.  Inavero's team reports on satisfaction surveys from more than 500,000 staffing agency clients and talent each year and the company serves as the American
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Staffing Association
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   's exclusive research partner.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;b&gt;
    About Inavero's Best of Staffing Award
    &lt;br/&gt;
   &lt;/b&gt;
   Inavero's
   &lt;a href="http://www.bestofstaffing.com/" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    Best of Staffing™
   &lt;/a&gt;
   is the nation's only award that recognizes staffing agencies that receive remarkable reviews from their clients and the people they help find jobs (employed talent). The Best of Staffing winner lists are a central place that businesses and talent go to find the best staffing agencies to call when they are in need.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;b&gt;
    Contact
   &lt;/b&gt;
   &lt;br/&gt;
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Kelly Kane
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;br/&gt;
   SHIFT Communications
   &lt;br/&gt;
   &lt;a href="mailto:aquent@shiftcomm.com" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    aquent@shiftcomm.com
   &lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;br/&gt;
   (617) 779-1866
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
   SOURCE  Aquent
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
  RELATED LINKS
  &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href="http://www.aquent.com" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank" title="Link to http://www.aquent.com"&gt;
   http://www.aquent.com
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>PR Newswire</pub_title>
  <document_url>http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/aquent-and-vitamin-t-make-inaveros-2013-best-of-staffing-talent-list-190696061.html</document_url>
  <author></author>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <title>Aquent And Vitamin T Make Inavero's 2013 Best Of Staffing™ Talent List</title>
  <database>PR Newswire</database>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>2013-02-11T12:00:00Z</pub_date>
  <document_id>prnewswire-190696061</document_id>
  <source>Aquent</source>
</DOCUMENT>
