<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>PR Newswire</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="news-col topics"&gt;
 &lt;div&gt;
  &lt;a name="linktopagetop"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;div class="featured"&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;span class="xn-location" itemprop="contentLocation" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Place"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="geo" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/address"&gt;
     &lt;span itemprop="addressLocality"&gt;
      RICHMOND, Va.
     &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   ,
   &lt;span class="xn-chron"&gt;
    Aug. 1, 2011
   &lt;/span&gt;
   /PRNewswire/ -- SoftChalk, a leading developer of educational software, today announced SoftChalk 7, the next generation of its flagship content authoring solution. In coordination, SoftChalk is also launching SoftChalk CONNECT Plus, a significant enhancement to its Learning Object Repository and Hosting platform.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   SoftChalk 7 builds upon the success of previous versions of SoftChalk and responds to the needs of digital learners with new mobile functionality. SoftChalk 7 automatically generates a mobile-friendly version of content created in SoftChalk and detects the device a learner is using so that the appropriate version of the content is displayed. There are also six new mobile-friendly html5 learning activity templates available in SoftChalk 7, to enhance mobile learning content with interactives.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   CONNECT Plus takes
   &lt;a href="http://www.softchalkconnect.com/" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    SoftChalk's cloud-based Learning Object Repository
   &lt;/a&gt;
   (LOR) to the next level with powerful, subscription-based services that allow users to collaboratively create, share and track high-quality educational content. The CONNECT Plus account offers educators more personal hosting space, enhanced access control of content, collaborative content editing and automated versioning. CONNECT Plus also offers the ability to reliably track detailed student score data through SoftChalk ScoreCenter. CONNECT Plus offers the perfect combination for collaboratively building lessons among colleagues and a solution for educators who want an easy way to deliver content and track student results online - either with or without an LMS.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Kevin Reeve
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   , Enterprise Architect of Information Technology at
   &lt;span class="xn-org"&gt;
    Utah State University
   &lt;/span&gt;
   , beta tested SoftChalk 7 and said, "I am most excited about the new mobile features available. With these, I can easily bring interactive and engaging content to learners on the go. The ability to produce mobile friendly e-learning content is moving SoftChalk light-years ahead of other software providers out there."
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   "We are excited to provide educators the means to reach the digital students who demand learning outside of the classroom," stated
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Sue Evans
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   , co-founder and CEO of SoftChalk. She continued, "With SoftChalk 7 and CONNECT Plus, we've developed a complete solution for creating and delivering content, engaging learners and tracking student score results."
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;b&gt;
    About SoftChalk, LLC
   &lt;/b&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   SoftChalk, LLC is an award-winning provider of e-Learning software for worldwide education and business institutions. Specializing in the development of intuitive, easy-to-use solutions, SoftChalk products allow instructors to create powerful and professional-looking content for e-Learning and smart classrooms in K-12, higher education and corporate training. For more information, visit
   &lt;a href="http://www.softchalk.com/" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    http://www.softchalk.com
   &lt;/a&gt;
   .
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   CONTACT:
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Brittany Mullins
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;br/&gt;
   &lt;a href="mailto:brittany@softchalk.com" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    brittany@softchalk.com
   &lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;br/&gt;
   (877) 638-2425, ext. 117
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   This press release was issued through eReleases(R).  For more information, visit eReleases
   &lt;a href="http://www.ereleases.com/" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    Press Release Distribution
   &lt;/a&gt;
   at
   &lt;a href="http://www.ereleases.com/" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    http://www.ereleases.com
   &lt;/a&gt;
   .
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
   SOURCE  SoftChalk, LLC
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
  RELATED LINKS
  &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href="http://www.softchalk.com" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank" title="Link to http://www.softchalk.com"&gt;
   http://www.softchalk.com
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>PR Newswire</pub_title>
  <document_url>http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/softchalk-goes-mobile-with-the-release-of-softchalk-7-and-connect-plus-126527943.html</document_url>
  <author></author>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <title>SoftChalk™ Goes Mobile with the Release of SoftChalk 7 and CONNECT Plus</title>
  <database>PR Newswire</database>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>2011-08-01T13:49:00Z</pub_date>
  <document_id>prnewswire-126527943</document_id>
  <source>SoftChalk, LLC</source>
</DOCUMENT>
