<DOCUMENT>
  <publisher>PR Newswire</publisher>
  <fulltext>&lt;div class="news-col topics"&gt;
 &lt;div&gt;
  &lt;a name="linktopagetop"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;div class="featured"&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;span class="xn-location" itemprop="contentLocation" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Place"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="geo" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/address"&gt;
     &lt;span itemprop="addressLocality"&gt;
      MELBOURNE, Australia
     &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   ,
   &lt;span class="xn-chron"&gt;
    March 20, 2013
   &lt;/span&gt;
   /PRNewswire/ --
   &lt;span class="xn-location" itemprop="contentLocation" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Place"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="geo" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/address"&gt;
     &lt;span itemprop="addressLocality"&gt;
      Australia
     &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   's leader in online education, Open Universities Australia (OUA), today unveils its new, free online education venture, Open2Study.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   Demonstrating a high quality free online education experience, Open2Study is a new dimension in online learning, unlike anything else currently available worldwide.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   "Open2Study isn't a me-too MOOC; its objective is not merely attracting massive enrolments. It's the next evolution in online learning, centred on student success," says
   &lt;span class="xn-person" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person"&gt;
    &lt;span itemprop="name"&gt;
     Paul Wappett
    &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;/span&gt;
   , OUA CEO.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   Open2Study provides an engaging and compelling education based on a comprehensive pedagogical model that recognises online learners behave differently, and have different needs from on-campus learners.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   "With over 20 years in the industry, we're confident we know the online student. Open2Study offers the best possible digital environment and techniques to help students understand what's being taught," says Mr Wappett.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   A mixture of six to ten minute videos, animations, simulations and quizzes, designed using high production values, set a high standard for the online education experience.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   "Subjects are based on our research into demand, so we're offering what people want to study. They range from
   &lt;i&gt;
    Financial Planning
   &lt;/i&gt;
   to
   &lt;i&gt;
    Strategic Management
   &lt;/i&gt;
   and are completed in just four weeks," says Mr Wappett.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   "What's more, our subjects avoid overly technical subject matter traditionally associated with some MOOCs. They are designed for everyone, irrespective of educational background and are taught by leading academics from universities, vocational providers and industry experts.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   "Anyone can enrol online today – it takes less than 30 seconds. The subjects are relevant to students worldwide.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   "Students won't pay a cent – there are no hidden costs for textbooks, student admin or exams. Everything required to pass will be provided at no cost," says Mr Wappett.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   Open2Study's unique classroom environment ensures learning occurs in one place, allowing students to collaborate and support each other, while engaging with videos and subject matter.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   This is also where students access learning objectives, tips, hints and other resources to help them understand what's being taught.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   "Open2Study is based on the core principle that learning is life-long and should be accessible by all," says Mr Wappett.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   Classes commence in approximately one month, and due to multiple intake periods, these subjects will be available all year round.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   "Whilst we've launched with 10 subjects, there's a pipeline of a few hundred and we expect to offer 40 to 50 by the end of 2013," says Mr Wappett.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;b&gt;
    About Open2Study – Never stop learning
    &lt;br/&gt;
   &lt;/b&gt;
   Open2Study delivers free high quality online education. It offers everyone the chance to experience online tertiary and professional learning through a range of subjects, designed for everyday people.  Backed by
   &lt;a href="http://www.open.edu.au/" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    Open Universities Australia
   &lt;/a&gt;
   , Open2Study is based on the core principle that learning is life-long and should be accessible by all. And did we mention it was free? Visit
   &lt;a href="http://www.open2study.com/" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    www.open2study.com
   &lt;/a&gt;
   or access the Media Centre at
   &lt;a href="http://www.open2study.com/media-centre" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    www.open2study.com/media-centre
   &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p itemprop="articleBody"&gt;
   &lt;b&gt;
    For further information, please contact:
    &lt;br/&gt;
   &lt;/b&gt;
   Jessica Singh
   &lt;br/&gt;
   Manager, Corporate Communications, PR &amp;amp; Sponsorships
   &lt;br/&gt;
   Open2Study
   &lt;br/&gt;
   Ph: +61 (0)3 8628 2412
   &lt;br/&gt;
   Mobile: +61 (0)419 662 553
   &lt;br/&gt;
   E:
   &lt;a href="mailto:jessica.singh@open.edu.au" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank"&gt;
    jessica.singh@open.edu.au
   &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
   SOURCE  Open Universities Australia
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
  RELATED LINKS
  &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href="http://www.open2study.com" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank" title="Link to http://www.open2study.com"&gt;
   http://www.open2study.com
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href="http://www.open.edu.au" onclick="linkOnClick(this)" target="_blank" title="Link to http://www.open.edu.au"&gt;
   http://www.open.edu.au
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</fulltext>
  <pub_title>PR Newswire</pub_title>
  <document_url>http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/australia-sets-the-scene-for-free-online-education-199222891.html</document_url>
  <author></author>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <title>Australia sets the scene for free online education</title>
  <database>PR Newswire</database>
  <query>MOOC</query>
  <pub_date>2013-03-20T16:00:00Z</pub_date>
  <document_id>prnewswire-199222891</document_id>
  <source>Open Universities Australia</source>
</DOCUMENT>
