The latest must-have accouterment for your luxury <LOCATION>Upper Northwest</LOCATION> home: A hockey rink. This being <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, the homeowner's move to install a 30-by-64-foot icy expanse has raised hackles on his <ORGANIZATION>Wesley Heights</ORGANIZATION> block, the <ORGANIZATION>Post</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Annie Gowen</PERSON> reports. The house used to belong to <PERSON>Richard Nixon</PERSON>; now it belongs to <PERSON>Brooke Coburn</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Carlyle Group</ORGANIZATION> managing director, who is installing the rink after embarking on a major renovation of the home. "Can people do this?" asks his next-door neighbor. People indeed can do that, and after a permitting snafu, the rink is now installed and legal.In other news:Mother killed, baby wounded in Metrobus shooting in <LOCATION>Fairlawn</LOCATION> (Post, <ORGANIZATION>WJLA-TV</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>WTOP</ORGANIZATION>)<PERSON>Phil Mendelson</PERSON> begins to navigate <ORGANIZATION>D.C. Council</ORGANIZATION>'s racial minefield (Post)<LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> jail inmate who hanged himself last month had a history of mental illness (Post)Tonight, Democratic insiders will pick an at-large <ORGANIZATION>D.C. Council</ORGANIZATION> member. Is it time to ditch the party appointment process? (Examiner)Yes! Organic's east-of-the-river location lives, under a new name (<ORGANIZATION>Capital Business</ORGANIZATION>)Prosecutors need to detail what happened to the unreported money in <PERSON>Kwame Brown</PERSON>'s 2008 campaign (Post editorial)Airports Authority hiring rife with nepotism; "no clear-cut guidelines," says board member (Post)<PERSON>Darrell Issa</PERSON> says referendum would just delay budget autonomy (D.C. Wire)Colby King: "Check out <PERSON>Kwame Brown</PERSON> two years from now. Don't expect him to be down and out." (Post column)Is the <ORGANIZATION>Post</ORGANIZATION> being fair to Mayor <PERSON>Vincent Gray</PERSON>? (Post ombudsman)<PERSON>Dan Tangherlini</PERSON> makes the most of his time atop <ORGANIZATION>GSA</ORGANIZATION> (Capital Business)With the arts, <PERSON>Patrick Pope</PERSON> invigorates <LOCATION>Anacostia</LOCATION>'s Savoy Elementary (Post)Why was <PERSON>Christophe Tulou</PERSON> fired for asking reasonable questions? (Post editorial)Hoover Building's potential demise would mean end of a cultural icon (<ORGANIZATION>AP</ORGANIZATION>)Business tax is throwing off more than enough cash to pay off ballpark bonds (WaTimes)How many managers does it take to put bathroom stalls in a <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> high school? (Loose Lips)Unsurprising data point of the week: Most new <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> jobs go to suburban dwellers (Examiner)<PERSON>Gray</PERSON> administration makes common-sensical determination that residential parking permits are too cheap (D.C. Wire, DCist)Height Act study is "a win-win proposition for all stakeholders" (Post column)<PERSON>Tony Williams</PERSON>: <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> should fund infrastructure upgrades Rahm Emanuel style (Capital Business)<PERSON>Marion Barry</PERSON> accuses <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> Chamber CEO <PERSON>Barbara Lang</PERSON> of being an Aunt <PERSON>Tom</PERSON> (WBJ)And also takes shots at his colleagues (Examiner)DDOT study: Most new cyclists are men (<ORGANIZATION>WTOP</ORGANIZATION>)<PERSON>Deborah Simmons</PERSON> believes "New Urbanism" is to blame for gentrification ills (WaTimes)The socialists mobilize against school closings (<ORGANIZATION>World Socialist</ORGANIZATION>)<ORGANIZATION>Metro</ORGANIZATION> says cops, even plainclothes ones, still ride free (Post)<LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> moves to adopt eco-friendly building codes (WBJ, Housing Complex)After layoffs, LivingSocial shuffles its office portfolio (WBJ)<LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> gov's vacant space could incubate businesses (WBJ)Car drives into <PERSON>Adams Morgan</PERSON> McDonald's (Dr. Gridlock)For key public spaces, 14 more police surveillance cameras (Examiner)<PERSON>Harry Jaffe</PERSON> won't say what role he played in <PERSON>Michelle Rhee</PERSON>'s new book (City Desk)Planners put new restrictions on accessory dwellings in latest zoning proposal (GGW)The 1800 block(s) of <LOCATION>Columbia Road</LOCATION> is the best place ever (OPinions)Man, 73, accused of shooting 63-year-old girlfriend to death (Crime Scene)<LOCATION>Georgetown U.</LOCATION> joins theMOOCmovement (Post)But it did not win a national soccer championship (Post)<LOCATION>Marshall Heights</LOCATION> wins, <ORGANIZATION>Beacon House</ORGANIZATION> falls short in <LOCATION>Pop Warner</LOCATION> finals (DCist)Check out <PERSON>Don Peebles</PERSON>' soon-to-be-former <LOCATION>Massachusetts Avenue Heights</LOCATION> home (WSJ)<PERSON>Jacques Morgan</PERSON>, ponytailed proprietor of <ORGANIZATION>Adams Morgan</ORGANIZATION>'s Idle Time Books, has died at 62 (Post)