Global ClassroomMOOCMassive open online courses -- dubbed MOOCs -- have lured venture investors and universities, who have put millions of dollars into companies that partner with schools or instructors to offer free courses.-- "Startup Must-Reads," <LOCATION>WSJ.com</LOCATION>, Jan. 2Other "massive" acronyms include MMO (sometimes MMOG), a "massively multiplayer online game," MPPA, "massively parallel processor array," a type of circuit with many CPUs, and MPSS, "massive parallel signature sequencing," a technique used in genetic analysis.---Far From the TreedroppageLast month, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> cut its forecast for this season's citrus production in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> by 5%, to 146 million boxes from 154 million. Among the reasons it cited was an increased rate of droppage -- a term referring to fallen fruit -- now projected to be the highest since 1970.-- "Disease Rips Through <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> Citrus," <ORGANIZATION>U.S. News</ORGANIZATION>, Jan. 2"Droppage" is also used to refer to fallen fruit other than citrus, including stone fruit, grapes, cranberries and even tree nuts such as almonds.---Big BusinessjukochodaiMr. <PERSON>Abe</PERSON>, who served a difficult year as prime minister five years ago, is considered a staunch advocate for old-school manufacturers, known as "jukochodai" from the Japanese words for "heavy, thick, long and big."-- "<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s Big Businesses See Hope in Abe," International News, Jan. 2The opposite of the jukochodai heavy industries are the "keihakutansho" high-tech industries. Keihakutansho means "light, thin, short and small," and is also used to refer to the work done by retirees.---Cruise Shipsslow steamingSlowing down ships, a technique known as slow steaming, doesn't only offer environmental benefits. It also allows operators to offset the additional capacity created by their bigger ships, because vessels chartered on a given route make fewer rotations.-- "Container Ships Bulk Up, and Slow Down," <LOCATION>WSJ.com</LOCATION>, Dec. 30Superslow steaming, at 12 knots, can save up to $5,000 an hour in fuel costs. An engine that has been reconfigured to run at slower speeds (in order to avoid problems like increased fouling and higher exhaust) is said to be "derated."---Ms. <PERSON>McKean</PERSON>, a lexicographer, founded <PERSON>Wordnik</PERSON>, an online dictionary focusing on how words are used today.Subscribe to WSJ:Credit: By <PERSON>Erin McKean</PERSON>