LORD knows there's a lot of bad news in the world today to get you down, but there is one big thing happening that leaves me incredibly hopeful about the future, and that is the budding revolution in global online higher education. Nothing has more potential to lift more people out of poverty -- by providing them an affordable education to get a job or improve in the job they have. Nothing has more potential to unlock a billion more brains to solve the world's biggest problems. And nothing has more potential to enable us to reimagine higher education than the massive open online course, orMOOC, platforms that are being developed by the likes of <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION> and companies like <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON> and Udacity.Last May I wrote about Coursera -- co-founded by the Stanford computer scientists <PERSON>Daphne Koller</PERSON> and <PERSON>Andrew Ng</PERSON> -- just after it opened. Two weeks ago, I went back out to <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION> to check in on them. When I visited last May, about 300,000 people were taking 38 courses taught by <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> professors and a few other elite universities. Today, they have 2.4 million students, taking 214 courses from 33 universities, including eight international ones.<PERSON>Anant Agarwal</PERSON>, the former director of <ORGANIZATION>M.I.T.</ORGANIZATION>'s artificial intelligence lab, is now president of edX, a nonprofitMOOCthat <ORGANIZATION>M.I.T.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> are jointly building. <PERSON>Agarwal</PERSON> told me that since May, some 155,000 students from around the world have taken edX's first course: an <ORGANIZATION>M.I.T.</ORGANIZATION> intro class on circuits. "That is greater than the total number of <ORGANIZATION>M.I.T.</ORGANIZATION> alumni in its 150-year history," he said.Yes, only a small percentage complete all the work, and even they still tend to be from the middle and upper classes of their societies, but I am convinced that within five years these platforms will reach a much broader demographic. Imagine how this might change <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> foreign aid. For relatively little money, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> could rent space in an Egyptian village, install two dozen computers and high-speed satellite Internet access, hire a local teacher as a facilitator, and invite in any Egyptian who wanted to take online courses with the best professors in the world, subtitled in Arabic.YOU just have to hear the stories told by the pioneers in this industry to appreciate its revolutionary potential. One of <PERSON>Koller</PERSON>'s favorites is about "<PERSON>Daniel</PERSON>," a 17-year-old with autism who communicates mainly by computer. He took an online modern poetry class from Penn. He and his parents wrote that the combination of rigorous academic curriculum, which requires <PERSON>Daniel</PERSON> to stay on task, and the online learning system that does not strain his social skills, attention deficits or force him to look anyone in the eye, enable him to better manage his autism. <PERSON>Koller</PERSON> shared a letter from <PERSON>Daniel</PERSON>, in which he wrote: "Please tell <LOCATION>Coursera</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Penn</LOCATION> my story. I am a 17-year-old boy emerging from autism. I can't yet sit still in a classroom so [your course] was my first real course ever. During the course, I had to keep pace with the class, which is unheard-of in special ed. Now I know I can benefit from having to work hard and enjoy being in sync with the world."One member of the Coursera team who recently took a Coursera course on sustainability told me that it was so much more interesting than a similar course he had taken as an undergrad. The online course included students from all over the world, from different climates, incomes levels and geographies, and, as a result, "the discussions that happened in that course were so much more valuable and interesting than with people of similar geography and income level" in a typical American college.<PERSON>Mitch Duneier</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION> sociology professor, wrote an essay in The <ORGANIZATION>Chronicle of Higher Education</ORGANIZATION> in the fall about his experience teaching a class through Coursera: "A few months ago, just as the campus of <ORGANIZATION>Princeton University</ORGANIZATION> had grown nearly silent after commencement, 40,000 students from 113 countries arrived here via the Internet to take a free course in introductory sociology. ... My opening discussion of <PERSON>C. Wright Mills</PERSON>'s classic 1959 book, 'The Sociological Imagination,' was a close reading of the text, in which I reviewed a key chapter line by line. I asked students to follow along in their own copies, as I do in the lecture hall. When I give this lecture on the <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION> campus, I usually receive a few penetrating questions. In this case, however, within a few hours of posting the online version, the course forums came alive with hundreds of comments and questions. Several days later there were thousands. ... Within three weeks I had received more feedback on my sociological ideas than I had in a career of teaching, which significantly influenced each of my subsequent lectures and seminars."Agarwal of edX tells of a student in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> who was taking the circuits course and was having difficulty. In the class's online forum, where students help each other with homework, he posted that he was dropping out. In response, other students in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> in the same class invited him to meet at a teahouse, where they offered to help him stay in the course. A 15-year-old student in <LOCATION>Mongolia</LOCATION>, who took the same class as part of a blended course and received a perfect score on the final exam, added <PERSON>Agarwal</PERSON>, is now applying to <ORGANIZATION>M.I.T.</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>.As we look to the future of higher education, said the <ORGANIZATION>M.I.T.</ORGANIZATION> president, <PERSON>L. Rafael Reif</PERSON>, something that we now call a "degree" will be a concept "connected with bricks and mortar" -- and traditional on-campus experiences that will increasingly leverage technology and the Internet to enhance classroom and laboratory work. Alongside that, though, said <PERSON>Reif</PERSON>, many universities will offer online courses to students anywhere in the world, in which they will earn "credentials" -- certificates that testify that they have done the work and passed all the exams. The process of developing credible credentials that verify that the student has adequately mastered the subject -- and did not cheat -- and can be counted on by employers is still being perfected by all the MOOCs. But once it is, this phenomenon will really scale.I can see a day soon where you'll create your own college degree by taking the best online courses from the best professors from around the world -- some computing from <LOCATION>Stanford</LOCATION>, some entrepreneurship from <LOCATION>Wharton</LOCATION>, some ethics from <LOCATION>Brandeis</LOCATION>, some literature from <LOCATION>Edinburgh</LOCATION> -- paying only the nominal fee for the certificates of completion. It will change teaching, learning and the pathway to employment. "There is a new world unfolding," said <PERSON>Reif</PERSON>, "and everyone will have to adapt."Drawing (Drawing by Till Hafenbrak) (Sr11)