Online-education provider <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON> announced Thursday that 29 more schools have signed on to offer massive, open, online courses, dubbed MOOCs. The new partners include <ORGANIZATION>Northwestern University</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>IE Business School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>National Taiwan University</ORGANIZATION>, and nearly double the stable of schools providing instruction on <PERSON>Coursera</PERSON>'s platform, up to a total of 62 schools.Mountain View, Calif.-based Coursera, which launched less than a year ago with backing from <LOCATION>Silicon Valley</LOCATION> investors, has so far attracted nearly 2.8 million unique registered users.Meanwhile edX, a nonprofit <ORGANIZATION>MOOC</ORGANIZATION> founded by <ORGANIZATION>Harvard University</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>, is adding six schools to its partner roster. New partners include <ORGANIZATION>McGill University</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Rice University</ORGANIZATION> and the Australian <ORGANIZATION>National University</ORGANIZATION>. EdX has more than 700,000 users signed up for courses from elite <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> schools; this is the first time it has signed on international partners.Colleges have eagerly put forward faculty to teach the free courses, but few award credit to students who complete those classes. The <ORGANIZATION>American Council on Education</ORGANIZATION> recently recommended that schools consider granting credit for certain Coursera classes, and is weighing a similar decision for a handful of classes taught by rival Udacity. Separately, edX has made agreements to introduce classes into some Boston-area community colleges.Write to <PERSON>Melissa Korn</PERSON> atCredit: By <PERSON>Melissa Korn</PERSON>